<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="255" status="NAD Future">
<title>Why do <tt>basic_streambuf&lt;&gt;::pbump()</tt> and <tt>gbump()</tt> take an int?</title>
<section><sref ref="[streambuf]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>12 Aug 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The basic_streambuf members gbump() and pbump() are specified to take an
int argument. This requirement prevents the functions from effectively
manipulating buffers larger than std::numeric_limits&lt;int&gt;::max()
characters. It also makes the common use case for these functions
somewhat difficult as many compilers will issue a warning when an
argument of type larger than int (such as ptrdiff_t on LLP64
architectures) is passed to either of the function. Since it's often the
result of the subtraction of two pointers that is passed to the
functions, a cast is necessary to silence such warnings. Finally, the
usage of a native type in the functions signatures is inconsistent with
other member functions (such as sgetn() and sputn()) that manipulate the
underlying character buffer. Those functions take a streamsize argument.
</p>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
This is part of a bigger problem. If anyone cares enough, they should
write a paper solving the bigger problem of offset types in iostreams.
</p>
<p>
This is related to the paper about large file sizes. Beman has already
agreed to drop the section of that paper that deals with this.
</p>
<p>
int is big enough for reasonable buffers.
</p>
<p>
Move to NAD Future.
</p>
<p>
This is related to LWG <iref ref="423"/>.
</p>
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Change the signatures of these functions in the synopsis of template
class basic_streambuf (27.5.2) and in their descriptions (27.5.2.3.1, p4
and 27.5.2.3.2, p4) to take a streamsize argument.
</p>

<p>
Although this change has the potential of changing the ABI of the
library, the change will affect only platforms where int is different
than the definition of streamsize. However, since both functions are
typically inline (they are on all known implementations), even on such
platforms the change will not affect any user code unless it explicitly
relies on the existing type of the functions (e.g., by taking their
address). Such a possibility is IMO quite remote.
</p>

<p>
Alternate Suggestion from Howard Hinnant, c++std-lib-7780:
</p>

<p>
This is something of a nit, but I'm wondering if streamoff wouldn't be a 
better choice than streamsize.  The argument to pbump and gbump MUST be 
signed.  But the standard has this to say about streamsize 
(27.4.1/2/Footnote):
</p>

<blockquote><p>
     [Footnote: streamsize is used in most places where ISO C would use
     size_t.  Most of the uses of streamsize could use size_t, except for
     the strstreambuf constructors, which require negative values. It
     should probably be the signed type corresponding to size_t (which is
     what Posix.2 calls ssize_t). --- end footnote]
</p></blockquote>

<p>
This seems a little weak for the argument to pbump and gbump.  Should we 
ever really get rid of strstream, this footnote might go with it, along 
with the reason to make streamsize signed.
</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The LWG believes this change is too big for now.  We may wish to
reconsider this for a future revision of the standard.  One
possibility is overloading pbump, rather than changing the
signature.</p>
<note>
[2006-05-04: Reopened at the request of Chris (Krzysztof ?elechowski)]
</note>
</rationale>
</issue>
