<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="231" status="CD1">
<title>Precision in iostream?</title>
<section><sref ref="[facet.num.put.virtuals]"/></section>
<submitter>James Kanze, Stephen Clamage</submitter>
<date> 25 Apr 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>What is the following program supposed to output?</p>
<pre>#include &lt;iostream&gt;

    int
    main()
    {
        std::cout.setf( std::ios::scientific , std::ios::floatfield ) ;
        std::cout.precision( 0 ) ;
        std::cout &lt;&lt; 1.00 &lt;&lt; '\n' ;
        return 0 ;
    }</pre>
<p>From my C experience, I would expect &quot;1e+00&quot;; this is what 
<tt>printf(&quot;%.0e&quot; , 1.00 );</tt> does. G++ outputs 
&quot;1.000000e+00&quot;.</p>

<p>The only indication I can find in the standard is 22.2.2.2.2/11,
where it says &quot;For conversion from a floating-point type, if
(flags &amp; fixed) != 0 or if str.precision() &gt; 0, then
str.precision() is specified in the conversion specification.&quot;
This is an obvious error, however, fixed is not a mask for a field,
but a value that a multi-bit field may take -- the results of and'ing
fmtflags with ios::fixed are not defined, at least not if
ios::scientific has been set. G++'s behavior corresponds to what might
happen if you do use (flags &amp; fixed) != 0 with a typical
implementation (floatfield == 3 &lt;&lt; something, fixed == 1
&lt;&lt; something, and scientific == 2 &lt;&lt; something).</p>

<p>Presumably, the intent is either (flags &amp; floatfield) != 0, or
(flags &amp; floatfield) == fixed; the first gives something more or
less like the effect of precision in a printf floating point
conversion. Only more or less, of course. In order to implement printf
formatting correctly, you must know whether the precision was
explicitly set or not. Say by initializing it to -1, instead of 6, and
stating that for floating point conversions, if precision &lt; -1, 6
will be used, for fixed point, if precision &lt; -1, 1 will be used,
etc. Plus, of course, if precision == 0 and flags &amp; floatfield ==
0, 1 should be = used. But it probably isn't necessary to emulate all
of the anomalies of printf:-).</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Replace <sref ref="[facet.num.put.virtuals]"/>, paragraph 11, with the following 
sentence:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
For conversion from a floating-point type,
<tt><i>str</i>.precision()</tt> is specified in the conversion
specification.
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The floatfield determines whether numbers are formatted as if
with %f, %e, or %g.  If the <tt>fixed</tt> bit is set, it's %f,
if <tt>scientific</tt> it's %e, and if both bits are set, or 
neither, it's %g.</p>
<p>Turning to the C standard, a precision of 0 is meaningful
for %f and %e.  For %g, precision 0 is taken to be the same as 
precision 1.</p>
<p>The proposed resolution has the effect that if neither
<tt>fixed</tt> nor <tt>scientific</tt> is set we'll be
specifying a precision of 0, which will be internally
turned into 1.  There's no need to call it out as a special
case.</p>
<p>The output of the above program will be &quot;1e+00&quot;.</p>

<note>Post-Cura&ccedil;ao: Howard provided improved wording covering the case
where precision is 0 and mode is %g.</note>

</rationale>

</issue>
