<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
    <!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg_issue.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY nbsp " ">
     ]
>
<issue num="421" status="NAD">
    <title>is <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> copy-constructible?</title>
    <section><sref ref="[streambuf.cons]"/></section>
    <submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
    <date>18 Sep 2003</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The reflector thread starting with c++std-lib-11346 notes that the class
template <tt>basic_streambuf</tt>, along with <tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> and <tt>basic_filebuf</tt>,
is copy-constructible but that the semantics of the copy constructors
are not defined anywhere. Further, different implementations behave
differently in this respect: some prevent copy construction of objects
of these types by declaring their copy ctors and assignment operators
private, others exhibit undefined behavior, while others still give
these operations well-defined semantics.
</p>

<p>
Note that this problem doesn't seem to be isolated to just the three
types mentioned above. A number of other types in the library section
of the standard provide a compiler-generated copy ctor and assignment
operator yet fail to specify their semantics.  It's believed that the
only types for which this is actually a problem (i.e. types where the
compiler-generated default may be inappropriate and may not have been
intended) are locale facets.  See issue <iref ref="439"/>.
</p>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote><p>
NAD. Option B is already in the Working Draft.
</p></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
27.5.2 [lib.streambuf]:  Add into the synopsis, public section, just above the destructor declaration:
</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
basic_streambuf(const basic_streambuf&amp; sb);
basic_streambuf&amp; operator=(const basic_streambuf&amp; sb);
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>Insert after 27.5.2.1, paragraph 2:</p>
<blockquote>
<pre>
basic_streambuf(const basic_streambuf&amp; sb);
</pre>

<p>Constructs a copy of <tt>sb</tt>.</p>
<p>Postcondtions:</p>
<pre>
                eback() == sb.eback()
                gptr()  == sb.gptr()
                egptr() == sb.egptr()
                pbase() == sb.pbase()
                pptr()  == sb.pptr()
                epptr() == sb.epptr()
                getloc() == sb.getloc()
</pre>

<pre>
basic_streambuf&amp; operator=(const basic_streambuf&amp; sb);
</pre>

<p>Assigns the data members of <tt>sb</tt> to this.</p>

<p>Postcondtions:</p>
<pre>
                eback() == sb.eback()
                gptr()  == sb.gptr()
                egptr() == sb.egptr()
                pbase() == sb.pbase()
                pptr()  == sb.pptr()
                epptr() == sb.epptr()
                getloc() == sb.getloc()
</pre>

<p>Returns: *this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>27.7.1 [lib.stringbuf]:</p>

<p><b>Option A:</b></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Insert into the <tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> synopsis in the private section:</p>

<pre>
basic_stringbuf(const basic_stringbuf&amp;);             // not defined
basic_stringbuf&amp; operator=(const basic_stringbuf&amp;);  // not defined
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p><b>Option B:</b></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Insert into the <tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> synopsis in the public section:</p>

<pre>
basic_stringbuf(const basic_stringbuf&amp; sb);
basic_stringbuf&amp; operator=(const basic_stringbuf&amp; sb);
</pre>

<p>27.7.1.1, insert after paragraph 4:</p>

<pre>basic_stringbuf(const basic_stringbuf&amp; sb);</pre>

<p>
Constructs an independent copy of <tt>sb</tt> as if with <tt>sb.str()</tt>, and with the openmode that <tt>sb</tt> was constructed with.
</p>

<p>Postcondtions: </p>
<pre>
               str() == sb.str()
               gptr()  - eback() == sb.gptr()  - sb.eback()
               egptr() - eback() == sb.egptr() - sb.eback()
               pptr()  - pbase() == sb.pptr()  - sb.pbase()
               getloc() == sb.getloc()
</pre>

<p>
Note:  The only requirement on <tt>epptr()</tt> is that it point beyond the initialized range if an 
output sequence exists.  There is no requirement that <tt>epptr() - pbase() == sb.epptr() - sb.pbase()</tt>.
</p>

<pre>basic_stringbuf&amp; operator=(const basic_stringbuf&amp; sb);</pre>
<p>
After assignment the <tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> has the same state as if it were initially copy constructed 
from <tt>sb</tt>, except that the <tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> is allowed to retain any excess capacity it 
might have, which may in turn effect the value of <tt>epptr()</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>27.8.1.1 [lib.filebuf]</p>

<p>Insert at the bottom of the <tt>basic_filebuf</tt> synopsis:</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
private:
  basic_filebuf(const basic_filebuf&amp;);             // not defined
  basic_filebuf&amp; operator=(const basic_filebuf&amp;);  // not defined
</pre>
</blockquote>
<note>Kona: this is an issue for <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> itself and for its
  derived classes.  We are leaning toward allowing <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> to
  be copyable, and specifying its precise semantics.  (Probably the
  obvious: copying the buffer pointers.)  We are less sure whether
  the <tt>streambuf</tt> derived classes should be copyable.  Howard will
  write up a proposal.</note>

<note>Sydney: Dietmar presented a new argument against <tt>basic_streambuf</tt>
  being copyable: it can lead to an encapsulation violation. <tt>filebuf</tt>
  inherits from <tt>streambuf</tt>. Now suppose you inherit a <tt>my_hijacking_buf</tt>
  from <tt>streambuf</tt>. You can copy the <tt>streambuf</tt> portion of a <tt>filebuf</tt> to a
  <tt>my_hijacking_buf</tt>, giving you access to the pointers into the
  <tt>filebuf</tt>'s internal buffer. Perhaps not a very strong argument, but
  it was strong enough to make people nervous. There was weak
  preference for having <tt>streambuf</tt> not be copyable. There was weak
  preference for having <tt>stringbuf</tt> not be copyable even if <tt>streambuf</tt>
  is. Move this issue to open for now.
</note>

<note>
2007-01-12, Howard:
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2005/n1862.html#27.5.2%20-%20Class%20template%20basic_streambuf%3CcharT,traits%3E">Rvalue Reference Recommendations for Chapter 27</a>
recommends protected copy constructor and assignment for <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> with the same semantics
as would be generated by the compiler.  These members aid in derived classes implementing move semantics.
A protected copy constructor and copy assignment operator do not expose encapsulation more so than it is
today as each data member of a <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> is already both readable and writable by derived
classes via various get/set protected member functions (<tt>eback()</tt>, <tt>setp()</tt>, etc.).  Rather
a protected copy constructor and copy assignment operator simply make the job of derived classes implementing
move semantics less tedious and error prone.
</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>
27.5.2 [lib.streambuf]: The proposed <tt>basic_streambuf</tt> copy constructor
and assignment operator are the same as currently implied by the lack
of declarations: public and simply copies the data members.  This
resolution is not a change but a clarification of the current
standard.
</p>

<p>
27.7.1 [lib.stringbuf]: There are two reasonable options: A) Make
<tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> not copyable.  This is likely the status-quo of
current implementations.  B) Reasonable copy semantics of
<tt>basic_stringbuf</tt> can be defined and implemented.  A copyable
<tt>basic_streambuf</tt> is arguably more useful than a non-copyable one.  This
should be considered as new functionality and not the fixing of a
defect.  If option B is chosen, ramifications from issue 432 are taken
into account.
</p>

<p>
27.8.1.1 [lib.filebuf]: There are no reasonable copy semantics for
<tt>basic_filebuf</tt>.
</p>

</rationale>

</issue>
