<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1235" status="NAD Future">
<title>Issue with C++0x random number proposal</title>
<section><sref ref="[rand.concept.dist]"/></section>
<submitter>Matthias Troyer</submitter>
<date>12 Oct 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
There exist optimized, vectorized vendor libraries for the creation of
random number generators, such as Intel's MKL [1] and AMD's ACML [2]. In
timing tests we have seen a performance gain of a factor of up to 80
(eighty) compared to a pure C++ implementation (in Boost.Random) when
using these generator to generate a sequence of normally distributed
random numbers. In codes dominated by the generation of random numbers
(we have application codes where random number generation is more than
50% of the CPU time) this factor 80 is very significant.
</p>

<p>
To make use of these vectorized generators, we use a C++ class modeling
the <tt>RandomNumberEngine</tt> concept and forwarding the generation of random
numbers to those optimized generators. For example:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
namespace mkl {
 class mt19937 {.... };
}
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
For the generation of random variates we also want to dispatch to
optimized vectorized functions in the MKL or ACML libraries. See this
example:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
mkl::mt19937 eng;
std::normal_distribution&lt;double&gt; dist;

double n = dist(eng);
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
Since the variate generation is done through the <tt>operator()</tt> of the
distribution there is no customization point to dispatch to Intel's or
AMD's optimized functions to generate normally distributed numbers based
on the <tt>mt19937</tt> generator. Hence, the performance gain of 80 cannot be
achieved.
</p>

<p>
Contrast this with TR1:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
mkl::mt19937 eng;
std::tr1::normal_distribution&lt;double&gt; dist;
std::tr1::variate_generator&lt;mkl::mt19937,std::tr1::normal_distribution&lt;double&gt; &gt; rng(eng,dist);
double n = rng();
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
This - admittedly much uglier from an aestethic point of view - design
allowed optimization by specializing the <tt>variate_generator</tt> template for
<tt>mkl::mt19937</tt>:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
namespace std { namespace tr1 {

template&lt;&gt;
class variate_generator&lt;mkl::mt19937,std::tr1::normal_distribution&lt;double&gt; &gt; { .... };

} }
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
A similar customization point is missing in the C++0x design and
prevents the optimized vectorized version to be used.
</p>

<p>
Suggested resolution:
</p>

<p>
Add a customization point to the distribution concept. Instead of the
<tt>variate_generator</tt> template this can be done through a call to a
free function <tt>generate_variate</tt> found by ADL instead of
<tt>operator()</tt> of the distribution:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;RandomNumberDistribution, class RandomNumberEngine&gt;
typename RandomNumberDistribution ::result_type
generate_variate(RandomNumberDistribution const&amp; dist, RandomNumberEngine&amp; eng);
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
This function can be overloaded for optimized enginges like
<tt>mkl::mt19937</tt>.
</p>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
NAD Future.  No time to add this feature for C++0X.
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
