<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="926" status="NAD Editorial">
<title>Sequentially consistent fences, relaxed operations and modification order</title>
<section><sref ref="[atomics.order]"/></section>
<submitter>Anthony Williams</submitter>
<date>19 Oct 2008</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses UK 313</b></p>

<p>
There was an interesting issue raised over on comp.programming.threads
today regarding the following example
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
// Thread 1:
x.store(1, memory_order_relaxed);           // SX
atomic_thread_fence(memory_order_seq_cst);  // F1
y.store(1, memory_order_relaxed);           // SY1
atomic_thread_fence(memory_order_seq_cst);  // F2
r1 = y.load(memory_order_relaxed);          // RY

// Thread 2:
y.store(0, memory_order_relaxed);          // SY2
atomic_thread_fence(memory_order_seq_cst); // F3
r2 = x.load(memory_order_relaxed);         // RX
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
is the outcome <tt>r1 == 0</tt> and <tt>r2 == 0</tt> possible?
</p>
<p>
I think the intent is that this is not possible, but I am not sure the
wording guarantees that. Here is my analysis:
</p>
<p>
Since all the fences are SC, there must be a total order between them.
<tt>F1</tt> must be before <tt>F2</tt> in that order since they are in
the same thread. Therefore <tt>F3</tt> is either before <tt>F1</tt>,
between <tt>F1</tt> and <tt>F2</tt> or after <tt>F2</tt>.
</p>
<p>
If <tt>F3</tt> is <em>after</em> <tt>F2</tt>, then we can apply <sref
ref="[atomics.order]"/>p5 from
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2798.pdf">N2798</a>:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
For atomic operations <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> on an atomic object
<tt>M</tt>, where <tt>A</tt> modifies <tt>M</tt> and <tt>B</tt> takes
its value, if there are <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences <tt>X</tt>
and <tt>Y</tt> such that <tt>A</tt> is sequenced before <tt>X</tt>,
<tt>Y</tt> is sequenced before <tt>B</tt>, and <tt>X</tt> precedes
<tt>Y</tt> in <tt>S</tt>, then <tt>B</tt> observes either the effects of
<tt>A</tt> or a later modification of <tt>M</tt> in its modification
order.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
In this case, <tt>A</tt> is <tt>SX</tt>, <tt>B</tt> is <tt>RX</tt>, the
fence <tt>X</tt> is <tt>F2</tt> and the fence <tt>Y</tt> is <tt>F3</tt>,
so <tt>RX</tt> must see 1.
</p>
<p>
If <tt>F3</tt> is <em>before</em> <tt>F2</tt>, this doesn't apply, but
<tt>F3</tt> can therefore be before or after <tt>F1</tt>.
</p>
<p>
If <tt>F3</tt> is <em>after</em> <tt>F1</tt>, the same logic applies, but this
time the fence <tt>X</tt> is <tt>F1</tt>. Therefore again, <tt>RX</tt>
must see 1.
</p>
<p>
Finally we have the case that <tt>F3</tt> is <em>before</em> <tt>F1</tt>
in the SC ordering. There are now no guarantees about <tt>RX</tt>, and
<tt>RX</tt> can see <tt>r2==0</tt>.
</p>
<p>
We can apply <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/>p5 again. This time,
<tt>A</tt> is <tt>SY2</tt>, <tt>B</tt> is <tt>RY</tt>, <tt>X</tt> is
<tt>F3</tt> and <tt>Y</tt> is <tt>F1</tt>. Thus <tt>RY</tt> must observe
the effects of <tt>SY2</tt> or a later modification of <tt>y</tt> in its
modification order.
</p>
<p>
Since <tt>SY1</tt> is sequenced before <tt>RY</tt>, <tt>RY</tt> must
observe the effects of <tt>SY1</tt> or a later modification of
<tt>y</tt> in its modification order.
</p>
<p>
In order to ensure that <tt>RY</tt> sees <tt>(r1==1)</tt>, we must see
that <tt>SY1</tt> is later in the modification order of <tt>y</tt> than
<tt>SY2</tt>.
</p>
<p>
We're now skating on thin ice. Conceptually, <tt>SY2</tt> happens-before
<tt>F3</tt>, <tt>F3</tt> is SC-ordered before <tt>F1</tt>, <tt>F1</tt>
happens-before <tt>SY1</tt>, so <tt>SY1</tt> is later in the
modification order <tt>M</tt> of <tt>y</tt>, and <tt>RY</tt> must see
the result of <tt>SY1</tt> (<tt>r1==1</tt>). However, I don't think the
words are clear on that.
</p>

<note>
Post Summit Hans adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
In my (Hans') view, our definition of fences will always be weaker than
what particular hardware will guarantee.  <tt>Memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences
inherently don't guarantee sequential consistency anyway, for good
reasons (e.g. because they can't enforce a total order on stores).
 Hence I don't think the issue demonstrates a gross failure to achieve
what we intended to achieve.  The example in question is a bit esoteric.
 Hence, in my view, living with the status quo certainly wouldn't be a
disaster either.
</p>
<p>
In any case, we should probably add text along the lines of the
following between p5 and p6 in <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/>:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[Note: <tt>Memory_order_seq_cst</tt> only ensures sequential consistency for a
data-race-free program that uses exclusively <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt>
operations.  Any use of weaker ordering will invalidate this guarantee
unless extreme care is used.  In particular, <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences
only ensure a total order for the fences themselves.  They cannot, in
general, be used to restore sequential consistency for atomic operations
with weaker ordering specifications.]
</p></blockquote>

<p>
Also see thread beginning at c++std-lib-23271.
</p>

</blockquote>

<note>
Herve's correction:
</note>
<blockquote>
<p>
Minor point, and sorry for the knee jerk reaction: I admit to having
no knowledge of Memory_order_seq_cst, but my former boss (John Lakos)
has ingrained an automatic introspection on the use of "only".   I
think you meant:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
[Note: <tt>Memory_order_seq_cst</tt> ensures sequential consistency only
for . . . .  In particular, <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences ensure a
total order only for . . .
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Unless, of course, <tt>Memory_order_seq_cst</tt> really do nothing but ensure
sequential consistency for a data-race-free program that uses
exclusively <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> operations.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
NAD Editorial.  Solved by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2992.html">N2992</a>.
</p></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Add a new paragraph after <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/>p5 that says
</p>

<blockquote><p>
For atomic operations <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> on an atomic object
<tt>M</tt>, where <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> modify <tt>M</tt>, if there
are <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences <tt>X</tt> and <tt>Y</tt> such
that <tt>A</tt> is sequenced before <tt>X</tt>, <tt>Y</tt> is sequenced
before <tt>B</tt>, and <tt>X</tt> precedes <tt>Y</tt> in <tt>S</tt>,
then <tt>B</tt> occurs later than <tt>A</tt> in the modifiction order of
<tt>M</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
