<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2152" status="New">
<title>Instances of standard container types are not swappable</title>
<section><sref ref="[swappable.requirements]"/>, <sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Robert Shearer</submitter>
<date>13 Apr 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
Sub-clause <sref ref="[swappable.requirements]"/> defines two notions of swappability: a binary version defining
when two objects are <em>swappable with</em> one another, and a unary notion defining whether an object is 
<em>swappable</em> (without qualification), with the latter definition requiring that the object satisfy the 
former with respect to all values of the same type.
<p/>
Let <tt>T</tt> be a container type based on a non-propagating allocator whose instances do not necessarily 
compare equal. Then sub-clause <sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/> p7 implies that no object <tt>t</tt> 
of type <tt>T</tt> is swappable (by the unary definition).
<p/>
Throughout the standard it is the unary definition of "swappable" that is listed as a requirement (with the 
exceptions of <sref ref="[utility.swap]"/> p4, <sref ref="[pairs.pair]"/> p31, <sref ref="[tuple.swap]"/> p2, 
<sref ref="[alg.swap]"/> p2, and <sref ref="[alg.swap]"/> p6, which use the binary definition). This renders 
many of the mutating sequence algorithms of sub-clause <sref ref="[alg.modifying.operations]"/>, for example, 
inapplicable to sequences of standard container types, even where every element of the sequence is swappable 
with every other.
<p/>
Note that this concern extends beyond standard containers to all future allocator-based types.
<p/>
Resolution proposal:
<p/>
I see two distinct straightforward solutions:
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type:lower-roman">
<li>Modify the requirements of algorithms from sub-clause <sref ref="[alg.modifying.operations]"/>, and all other
places that reference the unary "swappable" definition, to instead use the binary "swappable with" definition 
(over a domain appropriate to the context). The unary definition of "swappable" could then be removed from the 
standard.
</li>
<li>Modify sub-clause <sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/> such that objects of standard container types 
are "swappable" by the unary definition.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
I favor the latter solution, for reasons detailed in the following issue.
</p>

<note>
2012-10 Portland: Move to Open 
</note>

<p>
The issue is broader than containers with stateful allocotors, although they are the most obvious
example contained within the standard itself.  The basic problem is that once you have a stateful
allocator, that does not <tt>propagate_on_swap</tt>, then whether two objects of this type can be
swapped with well defined behavior is a run-time property (the allocators compare equal) rather
than a simple compile-time property that can be deduced from the type.  Strictly speaking, any
type where the nature of swap is a runtime property does not meet the <tt>swappable</tt>
requirements of C++11, although typical sequences of such types are going to have elements that
are all <tt>swappable with</tt> any other element in the sequence (using our other term of art
for specifying requirements) as the common case is a container of elements who all share the
same allocator.
</p>

<p>
The heart of the problem is that the <tt>swappable</tt> requirments demand that any two objects
of the same type be <tt>swappable with</tt> each other, so if any two such objects would not
be <tt>swappable with</tt> each other, then the whole type is never <tt>swappable</tt>.  Many
algorithms in clause 25 are specified in terms of <tt>swappable</tt> which is essentially an
overspecification as all they actually need is that any element in the sequence is <tt>swappable
with</tt> any other element in the sequence.
</p>

<p>
At this point Howard joins the discussion and points out that the intent of introducing the
two swap-related terms was to support <tt>vector%lt;bool>::reference</tt> types, and we are
reading something into the wording that was never intended.  Consuses is that regardless of
the intent, that is what the words today say.
</p>

<p>
There is some support to see a paper reviewing the whole of clause 25 for this issue, and
other select clauses as may be necessary.
</p>

<p>
There was some consideration to introducing a note into the front of clause 25 to indicate
<tt>swappable</tt> requirements in the clause should be interpreted to allow such awkward
types, but ultimately no real enthusiasm for introducing a <tt>swappable for clause 25</tt>
requirement term, especially if it confusingly had the same name as a term used with a
subtly different meaning through the rest of the standard.
</p>

<p>
There was no enthusiasm for the alternate resolution of requiring containers with unequal
allocators that do not propagate provide a well-defined swap behavior, as it is not
believed to be possible without giving <tt>swap</tt> linear complexity for such values,
and even then would require adding the constraint that the container element types are
CopyConstructible.
</p>

<p>
Final conclusion: move to open pending a paper from a party with a strong interest in
stateful allocators.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
