<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="287" status="NAD">
<title>conflicting ios_base fmtflags</title>
<section><sref ref="[fmtflags.state]"/></section>
<submitter>Judy Ward</submitter>
<date>30 Dec 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The Effects clause for ios_base::setf(fmtflags fmtfl) says
&quot;Sets fmtfl in flags()&quot;.  What happens if the user first calls
ios_base::scientific and then calls ios_base::fixed or vice-versa?
This is an issue for all of the conflicting flags, i.e. ios_base::left
and ios_base::right or ios_base::dec, ios_base::hex and ios_base::oct.
</p>

<p>
I see three possible solutions: 
</p>

<ol>
<li>Set ios_base::failbit whenever the user specifies a conflicting
flag with one previously explicitly set. If the constructor is
supposed to set ios_base::dec (see discussion below), then
the user setting hex or oct format after construction will not
set failbit. </li>
<li>The last call to setf &quot;wins&quot;, i.e. it clears any conflicting
previous setting.</li>
<li>All the flags that the user specifies are set, but when actually 
interpreting them, fixed always override scientific, right always 
overrides left, dec overrides hex which overrides oct.</li>
</ol>

<p>
Most existing implementations that I tried seem to conform to resolution #3,
except that when using the iomanip manipulator hex or oct then that always 
overrides dec, but calling setf(ios_base::hex) doesn't. 
</p>

<p>
There is a sort of related issue, which is that although the ios_base
constructor says that each ios_base member has an indeterminate value
after construction, all the existing implementations I tried explicitly set 
ios_base::dec.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>
<tt>adjustfield</tt>, <tt>basefield</tt>, and <tt>floatfield</tt>
are each multi-bit fields.  It is possible to set multiple bits within
each of those fields.  (For example, <tt>dec</tt> and
<tt>oct</tt>). These fields are used by locale facets.  The LWG
reviewed the way in which each of those three fields is used, and
believes that in each case the behavior is well defined for any
possible combination of bits.  See for example Table 58, in <sref ref="[facet.num.put.virtuals]"/>, noting the requirement in paragraph 6 of that
section.
</p>
<p>
Users are advised to use manipulators, or else use the two-argument
version of <tt>setf</tt>, to avoid unexpected behavior.
</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
