<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="408" status="NAD Editorial">
<title>Is <tt>vector&lt;reverse_iterator&lt;char*&gt; &gt;</tt> forbidden?</title>
<section><sref ref="[iterator.requirements]"/></section>
<submitter>Nathan Myers</submitter>
<date>3 Jun 2003</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I've been discussing iterator semantics with Dave Abrahams, and a 
surprise has popped up.  I don't think this has been discussed before.
</p>

<p>
<sref ref="[iterator.concepts]"/> says that the only operation that can be performed on "singular"
iterator values is to assign a non-singular value to them.  (It 
doesn't say they can be destroyed, and that's probably a defect.)  
Some implementations have taken this to imply that there is no need 
to initialize the data member of a <tt>reverse_iterator&lt;&gt;</tt> in the default
constructor.  As a result, code like
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
  std::vector&lt;std::reverse_iterator&lt;char*&gt; &gt; v(7);
  v.reserve(1000);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
invokes undefined behavior, because it must default-initialize the
vector elements, and then copy them to other storage.  Of course many 
other vector operations on these adapters are also left undefined,
and which those are is not reliably deducible from the standard.
</p>

<p>
I don't think that 24.1 was meant to make standard-library iterator 
types unsafe.  Rather, it was meant to restrict what operations may 
be performed by functions which take general user- and standard 
iterators as arguments, so that raw pointers would qualify as
iterators.  However, this is not clear in the text, others have come 
to the opposite conclusion.
</p>

<p>
One question is whether the standard iterator adaptors have defined
copy semantics.  Another is whether they have defined destructor
semantics: is
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
  { std::vector&lt;std::reverse_iterator&lt;char*&gt; &gt;  v(7); }
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
undefined too?
</p>

<p>
Note this is not a question of whether algorithms are allowed to
rely on copy semantics for arbitrary iterators, just whether the
types we actually supply support those operations.  I believe the 
resolution must be expressed in terms of the semantics of the 
adapter's argument type.  It should make clear that, e.g., the 
<tt>reverse_iterator&lt;T&gt;</tt> constructor is actually required to execute
<tt>T()</tt>, and so copying is defined if the result of <tt>T()</tt> is copyable.
</p>

<p>
Issue <iref ref="235"/>, which defines <tt>reverse_iterator</tt>'s default
constructor more precisely, has some relevance to this issue.
However, it is not the whole story.
</p>

<p>
The issue was whether 
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
  reverse_iterator() { }
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
is allowed, vs. 
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
  reverse_iterator() : current() { }
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
The difference is when <tt>T</tt> is <tt>char*</tt>, where the first leaves the member
uninitialized, and possibly equal to an existing pointer value, or
(on some targets) may result in a hardware trap when copied.
</p>

<p>
8.5 paragraph 5 seems to make clear that the second is required to
satisfy DR <iref ref="235"/>, at least for non-class Iterator argument
types.
</p>

<p>
But that only takes care of <tt>reverse_iterator</tt>, and doesn't establish
a policy for all iterators.  (The reverse iterator adapter was just
an example.)  In particular, does my function
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
  template &lt;typename Iterator&gt;
    void f() { std::vector&lt;Iterator&gt;  v(7); } 
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
evoke undefined behavior for some conforming iterator definitions?
I think it does, now, because <tt>vector&lt;&gt;</tt> will destroy those singular
iterator values, and that's explicitly disallowed.
</p>

<p>
24.1 shouldn't give blanket permission to copy all singular iterators,
because then pointers wouldn't qualify as iterators.  However, it
should allow copying of that subset of singular iterator values that
are default-initialized, and it should explicitly allow destroying any
iterator value, singular or not, default-initialized or not.
</p>

<p>Related issues: <iref ref="407"/>, <iref ref="1012"/></p>
<note>
We don't want to require all singular iterators to be copyable,
because that is not the case for pointers.  However, default
construction may be a special case.  Issue: is it really default
construction we want to talk about, or is it something like value
initialization?  We need to check with core to see whether default
constructed pointers are required to be copyable; if not, it would be
wrong to impose so strict a requirement for iterators.
</note>

<note>
2009-05-10 Alisdair provided wording.
</note>

<blockquote><p>
The comments regarding destroying singular iterators have already been
resolved.  That just leaves copying (with moving implied).
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
This is related to LWG <iref ref="1012"/>.
</p>
<p>
Note that there is a bug in the proposed resolution to LWG <iref ref="1012"/>. The
change to <sref ref="[reverse.iter.con]"/> should be modified so that the word
"default" in the second sentence of the Effects clause is replaced by
"value."
</p>
<p>
We believe that the proposed fix to LWG <iref ref="1012"/> (now corrected) is
sufficient to solve the problem for reverse_iterator. However, Alisdair
pointed out that LWG <iref ref="1012"/> does not solve the general problem for authors
of iterator adaptors.
</p>
<p>
There are some problems with the proposed resolution. The phrase "safely
copyable" is not a term of art. Also, it mentions a
DefaultConstructible? concept.
</p>
<p>
Move to Review after Alisdair updates the wording.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07-31 Alisdair revised wording:
</note>

<note>
2009-08-17 Alisdair and Daniel collaborate on slightly revised wording.
This issue depends upon <iref ref="724"/>
</note>

<note>
2009-10-14 Daniel adds:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
There is a clear dependency on <iref ref="1213"/>, because the term "singular",
which is used as part of the resolution, is not properly defined yet.
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
Moved to Open. Alisdair will provide improved wording to make
this have "value semantics" and otherwise behave like a valid iterator.
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2010 Pittsburgh:  Moved to NAD Editorial.  Rationale added below.
</note>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>
Solved by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2010/n3066.html">N3066</a>.
</p>
</rationale>

<resolution>
<p>
Add a new paragrpah to Iterator concepts <sref
ref="[iterator.requirements]"/> after para 5 (the one describing
singular iterators)
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
Just as a regular pointer to an array guarantees that there is a pointer
value pointing past the last element of the array, so for any iterator
type there is an iterator value that points past the last element of a
corresponding container. These values are called <i>past-the-end</i> values.
Values of an iterator <tt>i</tt> for which the expression <tt>*i</tt> is defined are called
<i>dereferenceable</i>. The library never assumes that past-the-end values are
dereferenceable. Iterators can also have singular values that are not
associated with any container. [<i>Example:</i> After the declaration of an
uninitialized pointer <tt>x</tt> (as with <tt>int* x;</tt>), <tt>x</tt> must always be assumed to
have a singular value of a pointer. &mdash; <i>end example</i>] Results of most
expressions are undefined for singular values; the only exceptions are
destroying an iterator that holds a singular value and the assignment of
a non-singular value to an iterator that holds a singular value. In this
case the singular value is overwritten the same way as any other value.
Dereferenceable values are always non-singular.
</p>
<p><ins>
After value-initialization, any iterator that satisfies the
<tt>DefaultConstructible</tt> requirements ([defaultconstructible]) shall not introduce undefined behaviour
when used <ins>as</ins> the
source of a copy or move operation, even if it would
otherwise be singular. [<i>Note:</i> This guarantee is not offered for
default-initialization (<sref ref="[dcl.init]"/>), although the distinction only
matters for types with trivial default constructors such as pointers. &mdash;
<i>end note</i>]
</ins></p>

<!-- 
Any Iterator that satisfies the <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt> concept shall
be safely copyable after value-initialization, even if it would otherwise be
singular. [<i>Note:</i> This guarantee is not offered for default-initialization
(<sref ref="[dcl.init]"/>), although the distinction only matters for types with
trivial default constructors such as pointers. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
 -->
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
