<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2164" status="New">
<title>What are the semantics of <tt>vector.emplace(vector.begin(), vector.back())</tt>?</title>
<section><sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>, <sref ref="[container.requirements]"/></section>
<submitter>Howard Hinnant</submitter>
<date>7 Jul 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
Nikolay Ivchenkov recently brought the following example on the
<a href="https://groups.google.com/a/isocpp.org/d/topic/std-discussion/dhy23mDFXj4/discussion">std-discussion</a> 
newsgroup, asking whether the following program well-defined:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

int main()
{
  std::vector&lt;int&gt; v;
  v.reserve(4);
  v = { 1, 2, 3 };
  v.emplace(v.begin(), v.back());
  for (int x : v)
    std::cout &lt;&lt; x &lt;&lt; std::endl;
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
Nikolay Ivchenkov:
<p/>
I think that an implementation of <tt>vector</tt>'s 'emplace' should initialize an intermediate object with 
<tt>v.back()</tt> before any shifts take place, then perform all necessary shifts and finally replace the 
value pointed to by <tt>v.begin()</tt> with the value of the intermediate object. So, I would expect the 
following output:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
3
1
2
3
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
GNU C++ 4.7.1 and GNU C++ 4.8.0 produce other results:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
2
1
2
3
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
Howard Hinnant:
<p/>
I believe Nikolay is correct that vector should initialize an intermediate object with <tt>v.back()</tt> 
before any shifts take place. As Nikolay pointed out in another email, this appears to be the only way to 
satisfy the strong exception guarantee when an exception is not thrown by <tt>T</tt>'s copy constructor, 
move constructor, copy assignment operator, or move assignment operator as specified by 
<sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/p1. I.e. if the emplace construction throws, the vector must remain unaltered.
<p/>
That leads to an implementation that tolerates objects bound to the function parameter pack of the <tt>emplace</tt> 
member function may be elements or sub-objects of elements of the container.
<p/>
My position is that the standard is correct as written, but needs a clarification in this area. Self-referencing 
<tt>emplace</tt> should be legal and give the result Nikolay expects. The proposed resolution of LWG <iref ref="760"/> 
is not correct.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
