<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="631" status="NAD">
<title>conflicting requirements for <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[algorithms]"/></section>
<submitter>James Kanze</submitter>
<date>31 Jan 2007</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The general requirements for <tt><tt>BinaryPredicate</tt></tt> (in <sref
ref="[algorithms]"/>/8) contradict the implied specific requirements for
some functions. In particular, it says that:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
[...] if an algorithm takes <tt>BinaryPredicate <i>binary_pred</i></tt>
as its argument and <tt><i>first1</i></tt> and <i>first2</i> as its
iterator arguments, it should work correctly in the construct <tt>if
(binary_pred (*<i>first1</i> , *<i>first2</i> )){...}</tt>.
<tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> always takes the first iterator type as its
first argument, that is, in those cases when <tt>T <i>value</i></tt> is
part of the signature, it should work correctly in the context of <tt>if
(binary_pred (*<i>first1</i> , <i>value</i>)){...}</tt>.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
In the description of <tt>upper_bound</tt> (<sref
ref="[upper.bound]"/>/2), however, the use is described as
"<tt>!comp(<i>value</i>, <i>e</i>)</tt>", where <tt><i>e</i></tt> is an
element of the sequence (a result of dereferencing
<tt>*<i>first</i></tt>).
</p>

<p>
In the description of <tt>lexicographical_compare</tt>, we have both
"<tt>*<i>first1</i> &lt; *<i>first2</i></tt>" and "<tt>*<i>first2</i>
&lt; *<i>first1</i></tt>" (which presumably implies "<tt>comp(
*<i>first1</i>, *<i>first2</i> )</tt>" and "<tt>comp( *<i>first2</i>,
*<i>first1</i> )</tt>".
</p>

<p>
Logically, the <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> is used as an ordering
relationship, with the semantics of "less than".  Depending on the
function, it may be used to determine equality, or any of the inequality
relationships; doing this requires being able to use it with either
parameter first.  I would thus suggest that the requirement be:
</p>

<p>
Alternatively, one could specify an order for each function. IMHO, this
would be more work for the committee, more work for the implementors,
and of no real advantage for the user: some functions, such as
<tt>lexicographical_compare</tt> or <tt>equal_range</tt>, will still require both
functions, and it seems like a much easier rule to teach that both
functions are always required, rather than to have a complicated list of
when you only need one, and which one.
</p>

<note>
Toronto:  Moved to Open.  ConceptGCC seems to get <tt>lower_bound</tt>
and <tt>upper_bound</tt> to work withoutt these changes.
</note>

<note>
2009-07-28 Reopened by Alisdair.  No longer solved by concepts.
</note>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Move to Review. The small problem with the "iterator type"
will be fixed. The cited functions (<tt>lower_bound</tt>, <tt>uppwer_bound</tt>,
<tt>equal_range</tt>) don't actually use <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> , and where it is used,
it is consistent with <sref ref="[algorithm]"/>/8, so the main complaint of the issue
is moot.
</blockquote>

<note>
2010-01-16 Beman clarified wording.
</note>

<note>
2010-01-31: Moved to Tentatively NAD after 5 positive votes on c++std-lib. 
Rationale added below.
</note>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<note>
post San Francisco:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Solved by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2759.pdf">N2759</a>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
2010-01-31: The draft standard is well specified as is, and this specification
is desired.  Issues <iref ref="556"/> and <iref ref="870"/> solve the remaining
unclearness regarding the meaning of BinaryPredicate.
</p>

</rationale>

<resolution>
<p><i>Change <sref ref="[algorithms]"/> paragraph 8 as indicated:</i></p>

<blockquote>

<p>
8 The <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> parameter is used whenever an algorithm expects a
function object that when applied to the result of dereferencing two
corresponding iterators or to dereferencing an iterator and type <tt>T</tt> when
<tt>T</tt> is part of the signature returns a value testable as true. <ins>
<tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> always takes the first iterator <tt>value_type</tt> as
one of its arguments; which argument is unspecified.</ins> <del>In other words,
if</del> <ins> If</ins> an algorithm takes <tt>BinaryPredicate binary_pred</tt>
as its argument and <tt>first1</tt> and <tt>first2</tt> as its iterator
arguments, it should work correctly <ins>both</ins> in the construct <tt>if
(binary_pred(*first1, *first2)){...}</tt> <ins>and <tt>if (binary_pred (*first2,
*first1)){...}</tt></ins>. <del><tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> always takes the first
iterator type as its first argument, that is, in</del> <ins>In</ins> those cases
when <tt>T value</tt> is part of the signature, it should work correctly in the
context of <tt> if (binary_pred(*first1, value)){...}</tt> <ins>and of <tt>if
(binary_pred (value, *first1)){...}</tt></ins>. <del> <tt>binary_pred</tt> shall
not apply any non-constant function through the dereferenced iterators.</del>
<ins>[<i>Note:</i> if the two types are not identical, and neither is
convertable to the other, this may require that the <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> be
a functional object with two overloaded <tt>operator()()</tt> functions.
&mdash; <i>end note</i>]</ins>
</p>

</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
