<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="475" status="CD1">
<title>May the function object passed to for_each modify the elements of the iterated sequence?</title>
<section><sref ref="[alg.foreach]"/></section>
<submitter>Stephan T. Lavavej, Jaakko Jarvi</submitter>
<date>9 Jul 2004</date>

<discussion>
<p>
It is not clear whether the function object passed to for_each is allowed to
modify the elements of the sequence being iterated over.
</p>

<p>
for_each is classified without explanation in [lib.alg.nonmodifying], "25.1
Non-modifying sequence operations". 'Non-modifying sequence operation' is
never defined.
</p>

<p>
25(5) says: "If an algorithm's Effects section says that a value pointed to
by any iterator passed as an argument is modified, then that algorithm has
an additional type requirement: The type of that argument shall satisfy the
requirements of a mutable iterator (24.1)."
</p>

<p>for_each's Effects section does not mention whether arguments can be
modified:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  "Effects: Applies f to the result of dereferencing every iterator in the
   range [first, last), starting from first and proceeding to last - 1."
</p></blockquote>

<p>
Every other algorithm in [lib.alg.nonmodifying] is "really" non-modifying in
the sense that neither the algorithms themselves nor the function objects
passed to the algorithms may modify the sequences or elements in any way.
This DR affects only for_each.
</p>

<p>
We suspect that for_each's classification in "non-modifying sequence
operations" means that the algorithm itself does not inherently modify the
sequence or the elements in the sequence, but that the function object
passed to it may modify the elements it operates on. 
</p>

<p>
The original STL document by Stepanov and Lee explicitly prohibited the
function object from modifying its argument.
The "obvious" implementation of for_each found in several standard library 
implementations, however, does not impose this restriction.
As a result, we suspect that the use of for_each with function objects that modify
their arguments is wide-spread. 
If the restriction was reinstated, all such code would become non-conforming.
Further, none of the other algorithms in the Standard
could serve the purpose of for_each (transform does not guarantee the order in
which its function object is called). 
</p>

<p>
We suggest that the standard be clarified to explicitly allow the function object 
passed to for_each modify its argument.</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>Add a nonnormative note to the Effects in <sref ref="[alg.foreach]"/>: If
the type of 'first' satisfies the requirements of a mutable iterator,
'f' may apply nonconstant functions through the dereferenced iterators
passed to it.
</p>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The LWG believes that nothing in the standard prohibits function
  objects that modify the sequence elements. The problem is that
  for_each is in a secion entitled "nonmutating algorithms", and the
  title may be confusing.  A nonnormative note should clarify that.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
