<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2265" status="New">
<title>29.3p9 appears to rule out some acceptable executions</title>
<section><sref ref="[atomics.order]"/></section>
<submitter>Brian Demsky</submitter>
<date>17 Jun 2013</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I believe that the following variation on IRIW should admit executions in
which <tt>c1 = d1 = 5</tt> and <tt>c2 = d2 = 0</tt>.  If this is allowed, then what is sequence of
program evaluations for <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> p9 that justifies the store to <tt>z</tt>?  It seems that
<sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> p9 should not allow this execution because one of the stores to <tt>x</tt> or <tt>y</tt> has
to appear earlier in the sequence, each of the <tt>fetch_adds</tt> reads the previous load in the thread (and thus must 
appear later in the sequence), and <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> p9 states that each load must read from the last prior 
assignment in the sequence.
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
atomic_int x;
atomic_int y;
atomic_int z;
int c1, c2, d1, d2;

static void a(void* obj)
{
  atomic_store_explicit(&amp;x, 5, memory_order_relaxed); 
}

static void b(void* obj)
{
  atomic_store_explicit(&amp;y, 5, memory_order_relaxed); 
}

static void c(void* obj)
{
  c1 = atomic_load_explicit(&amp;x, memory_order_relaxed);
  // this could also be an atomic load if the address depends on c1:
  c2 = atomic_fetch_add_explicit(&amp;y, c1, memory_order_relaxed);  
}

static void d(void* obj)
{
  d1 = atomic_load_explicit(&amp;y, memory_order_relaxed);
  d2 = atomic_fetch_add_explicit(&amp;x, d1, memory_order_relaxed); 
}

int user_main(int argc, char** argv)
{
  thrd_t t1, t2, t3, t4;

  atomic_init(&amp;x, 0);
  atomic_init(&amp;y, 0);

  printf("Main thread: creating 4 threads\n");
  thrd_create(&amp;t1, (thrd_start_t)&amp;a, NULL);
  thrd_create(&amp;t2, (thrd_start_t)&amp;b, NULL);
  thrd_create(&amp;t3, (thrd_start_t)&amp;c, NULL);
  thrd_create(&amp;t4, (thrd_start_t)&amp;d, NULL);

  thrd_join(t1);
  thrd_join(t2);
  thrd_join(t3);
  thrd_join(t4);
  printf("c1=%d c2=%d\n",c1,c2);
  printf("d1=%d d2=%d\n",d1,d2);

  // Can this store write 1000 (i.e., c1=d1=5, c2=d2=0)?
  atomic_store(&amp;z, (c1+d1)*100+c2+d2);

  printf("Main thread is finished\n");

  return 0;
}
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
It seems that the easiest fix is to allow a load in <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> p9 to read from any prior
store in the evaluation order.
<p/>
That said, I would personally advocate the following:
It seems to me that C/C++ atomics are in a bit of different situation than Java
because:
</p>
<ol>
<li><p>People are expected to use relaxed C++ atomics in potentially racy
situations, so it isn't clear that semantics as complicated as the JMM's
causality would be sane.
</p></li>
<li><p>People who use C/C++ atomics are likely to be experts and use them in a
very controlled fashion. I would be really surprised if compilers would find
any real wins by optimizing the use of atomics.
</p></li>
</ol>
<p>
Why not do something like:
<p/>
There is satisfaction DAG of all program evaluations. Each evaluation
observes the values of variables as computed by some prior assignment in
the DAG.
<p/>
There is an edge <tt>x-&gt;y</tt> between two evaluations <tt>x</tt> and <tt>y</tt> if:
</p>
<ol>
<li><p>the evaluation <tt>y</tt> observes a value computed by the evaluation <tt>x</tt> or
</p></li>
<li><p>the evaluation <tt>y</tt> is an atomic store, the evaluation <tt>x</tt> is an atomic load, and
there is a condition branch c that may depend (intrathread dependence) on <tt>x</tt>
and <tt>x-sb-&gt;c</tt> and <tt>c-sb-&gt;y</tt>.
</p></li>
</ol>
<p>
This seems to allow reordering of relaxed atomics that processors do without
extra fence instructions, allows most reorderings by the compiler, and gets
rid of satisfaction cycles.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
