<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg_issue.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp " ">
]>

<issue num="394" status="NAD">
<title>behavior of formatted output on failure</title>
<section><sref ref="[ostream.formatted.reqmts]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>27 Dec 2002</date>

<discussion>
<p>
There is a contradiction in Formatted output about what bit is
supposed to be set if the formatting fails. On sentence says it's
badbit and another that it's failbit.
</p>
<p>
27.6.2.5.1, p1 says in the Common Requirements on Formatted output
functions:
</p>
<pre>
     ... If the generation fails, then the formatted output function
     does setstate(ios::failbit), which might throw an exception.
</pre>
<p>
27.6.2.5.2, p1 goes on to say this about Arithmetic Inserters:
</p>
<p>
     ... The formatting conversion occurs as if it performed the
     following code fragment:
</p>
<pre>
     bool failed =
         use_facet&lt;num_put&lt;charT,ostreambuf_iterator&lt;charT,traits>
         > >
         (getloc()).put(*this, *this, fill(), val). failed();

     ... If failed is true then does setstate(badbit) ...
</pre>
<p>
The original intent of the text, according to Jerry Schwarz (see
c++std-lib-10500), is captured in the following paragraph:
</p>
<p>
In general "badbit" should mean that the stream is unusable because
of some underlying failure, such as disk full or socket closure;
"failbit" should mean that the requested formatting wasn't possible
because of some inconsistency such as negative widths.  So typically
if you clear badbit and try to output something else you'll fail
again, but if you clear failbit and try to output something else
you'll succeed.
</p>
<p>
In the case of the arithmetic inserters, since num_put cannot
report failure by any means other than exceptions (in response
to which the stream must set badbit, which prevents the kind of
recoverable error reporting mentioned above), the only other
detectable failure is if the iterator returned from num_put
returns true from failed().
</p>
<p>
Since that can only happen (at least with the required iostream
specializations) under such conditions as the underlying failure
referred to above (e.g., disk full), setting badbit would seem
to be the appropriate response (indeed, it is required in
27.6.2.5.2, p1). It follows that failbit can never be directly
set by the arithmetic (it can only be set by the sentry object
under some unspecified conditions).
</p>
<p>
The situation is different for other formatted output functions
which can fail as a result of the streambuf functions failing
(they may do so by means other than exceptions), and which are
then required to set failbit.
</p>
<p>
The contradiction, then, is that ostream::operator&lt;&lt;(int) will
set badbit if the disk is full, while operator&lt;&lt;(ostream&amp;,
char) will set failbit under the same conditions. To make the behavior
consistent, the Common requirements sections for the Formatted output
functions should be changed as proposed below.
</p>
<note>Kona: There's agreement that this is a real issue.  What we
  decided at Kona: 1. An error from the buffer (which can be detected
  either directly from streambuf's member functions or by examining a
  streambuf_iterator) should always result in badbit getting set.
  2. There should never be a circumstance where failbit gets set.
  That represents a formatting error, and there are no circumstances
  under which the output facets are specified as signaling a
  formatting error. (Even more so for string output that for numeric
  because there's nothing to format.)  If we ever decide to make it
  possible for formatting errors to exist then the facets can signal
  the error directly, and that should go in clause 22, not clause 27.
  3. The phrase "if generation fails" is unclear and should be
  eliminated.  It's not clear whether it's intended to mean a buffer
  error (e.g. a full disk), a formatting error, or something else.
  Most people thought it was supposed to refer to buffer errors; if
  so, we should say so.  Martin will provide wording.</note>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote><p>
NAD. This issue is already fixed.
</p></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

<rationale>

</rationale>

</issue>
