<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="203" status="NAD">
<title>basic_istream::sentry::sentry() is uninstantiable with ctype&lt;user-defined type&gt;</title>
<section><sref ref="[istream::sentry]"/></section>
<submitter>Matt McClure and Dietmar K&uuml;hl</submitter>
<date>1 Jan 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>27.6.1.1.2 Paragraph 4 states:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>To decide if the character c is a whitespace character, the constructor      
     performs ''as if'' it executes the following code fragment:&nbsp;</p>
  <pre>const ctype&lt;charT&gt;&amp; ctype = use_facet&lt;ctype&lt;charT&gt; &gt;(is.getloc());
if (ctype.is(ctype.space,c)!=0)
// c is a whitespace character.</pre>
</blockquote>

<p> But Table 51 in 22.1.1.1.1 only requires an implementation to
provide specializations for ctype&lt;char&gt; and
ctype&lt;wchar_t&gt;.  If sentry's constructor is implemented using
ctype, it will be uninstantiable for a user-defined character type
charT, unless the implementation has provided non-working (since it
would be impossible to define a correct ctype&lt;charT&gt; specialization
for an arbitrary charT) definitions of ctype's virtual member
functions.</p>

<p>
It seems the intent the standard is that sentry should behave, in
every respect, not just during execution, as if it were implemented
using ctype, with the burden of providing a ctype specialization
falling on the user.  But as it is written, nothing requires the
translation of sentry's constructor to behave as if it used the above
code, and it would seem therefore, that sentry's constructor should be
instantiable for all character types.
</p>

<p> 
Note: If I have misinterpreted the intent of the standard with
respect to sentry's constructor's instantiability, then a note should
be added to the following effect:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
An implementation is forbidden from using the above code if it renders
the constructor uninstantiable for an otherwise valid character
type.
</p></blockquote>

<p>In any event, some clarification is needed.</p>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>It is possible but not easy to instantiate on types other than char
or wchar_t; many things have to be done first. That is by intention
and is not a defect.</p>
</rationale>
</issue>
