<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1211" status="NAD Editorial">
<title>move iterators should be restricted as input iterators</title>
<section><sref ref="[move.iterator]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>18 Sep 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I contend that while we can support both bidirectional and random access
traversal, the category of a move iterator should never be better than
<tt>input_iterator_tag</tt>.
</p>

<p>
The contentious point is that you cannot truly have a multipass property
when values are moved from a range.  This is contentious if you view a
moved-from object as still holding a valid value within the range.  
</p>

<p>
The second reason comes from the Forward Iterator requirements table:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
Forward iterators <sref ref="[forward.iterators]"/>
</p>

<p>
Table 102 -- Forward iterator requirements
</p>

<blockquote>
For expression <tt>*a</tt> the return type is:
"<tt>T&amp;</tt> if <tt>X</tt> is mutable, otherwise <tt>const T&amp;</tt>"
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>
There is a similar constraint on <tt>a-&gt;m</tt>.
</p>

<p>
There is no support for rvalue references, nor do I believe their should
be.  Again, opinions may vary but either this table or the definition of
<tt>move_iterator</tt> need updating.
</p>

<p>
Note: this requirement probably need updating anyway if we wish to
support proxy iterators but I am waiting to see a new working paper
before filing that issue.
</p>

<note>
2009-10 post-Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Move to Open. Howard to put his rationale mentioned above into the issue
as a note.
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10-26 Howard adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
<tt>vector::insert(pos, iter, iter)</tt> is significantly more effcient when
<tt>iter</tt> is a random access iterator, as compared to when it is an
input iterator.
</p>

<p>
When <tt>iter</tt> is an input iterator, the best algorithm
is to append the inserted range to the end of the <tt>vector</tt> using
<tt>push_back</tt>.  This may involve several reallocations before the input
range is exhausted.  After the append, then one can use <tt>std::rotate</tt>
to place the inserted range into the correct position in the vector.
</p>

<p>
But when <tt>iter</tt> is a random access iterator, the best algorithm
is to first compute the size of the range to be inserted (<tt>last - first</tt>),
do a buffer reallocation if necessary, scoot existing elements in the <tt>vector</tt>
down to make the "hole", and then insert the new elements directly to their correct
place.
</p>

<blockquote><b>
The insert-with-random-access-iterators algorithm is considerably more efficient
than the insert-with-input-iterators algorithm
</b></blockquote>

<p>
Now consider:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
vector&lt;A&gt; v;
<font color="#C80000">//  ... build up a large vector of A ...</font>
vector&lt;A&gt; temp;
<font color="#C80000">//  ... build up a large temporary vector of A to later be inserted ...</font>
typedef move_iterator&lt;vector&lt;A&gt;::iterator&gt; MI;
<font color="#C80000">//  Now insert the temporary elements:</font>
v.insert(v.begin() + N, MI(temp.begin()), MI(temp.end()));
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
A major motivation for using <tt>move_iterator</tt> in the above example is the
expectation that <tt>A</tt> is cheap to move but expensive to copy.  I.e. the
customer is looking for <em>high performance</em>.  If we allow <tt>vector::insert</tt>
to subtract two <tt>MI</tt>'s to get the distance between them, the customer enjoys
substantially better performance, compared to if we say that <tt>vector::insert</tt>
can not subtract two <tt>MI</tt>'s.
</p>

<p>
I can find no rationale for not giving this performance boost to our customers.
Therefore I am strongly against restricting <tt>move_iterator</tt> to the
<tt>input_iterator_tag</tt> category.
</p>

<p>
I believe that the requirement that forward
iterators have a dereference that returns an lvalue reference to cause unacceptable
pessimization.  For example <tt>vector&lt;bool&gt;::iterator</tt> also does not return
a <tt>bool&amp;</tt> on dereference.  Yet I am not aware of a single vendor that
is willing to ship <tt>vector&lt;bool&gt;::iterator</tt> as an input iterator.
Everyone classifies it as a random access iterator.  Not only does this not
cause any problems, it prevents significant performance problems.
</p>

</blockquote>

<note>
2010 Pittsburgh:  Moved to NAD Editorial.  Rationale added below.
</note>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>
Solved by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2010/n3066.html">N3066</a>.
</p>
</rationale>

<resolution>
<p>
Class template move_iterator <sref ref="[move.iterator]"/>
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
namespace std {
template &lt;class Iterator&gt;
class move_iterator {
public:
 ...
 typedef <del>typename iterator_traits&lt;Iterator&gt;::iterator_category</del> <ins>input_iterator_tag</ins> iterator_category;
</pre></blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
