<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1169" status="Review">
<title><tt>num_get</tt> not fully compatible with <tt>strto*</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[facet.num.get.virtuals]"/></section>
<submitter>Cosmin Truta</submitter>
<date>4 Jul 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
As specified in the latest draft,
<a 
href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2914.pdf">N2914</a>,
<code>num_get</code> is still not fully compatible with the following C
functions: <code>strtoul</code>, <code>strtoull</code>, 
<code>strtof</code> and
<code>strtod</code>.
</p>
<p>
In C, when conversion of a string to an unsigned integer type falls 
outside the
representable range, <code>strtoul</code> and <code>strtoull</code> return
<code>ULONG_MAX</code> and <code>ULLONG_MAX</code>, respectively, 
regardless
whether the input field represents a positive or a negative value.
On the other hand, the result of <code>num_get</code> conversion of 
negative
values to unsigned integer types is zero. This raises a compatibility 
issue.
</p>
<p>
Moreover, in C, when conversion of a string to a floating-point type falls
outside the representable range, <code>strtof</code>, <code>strtod</code> 
and
<code>strtold</code> return <code>&#xB1HUGE_VALF</code>,
<code>&#xB1HUGE_VAL</code> and <code>&#xB1HUGE_VALL</code>, respectively.
On the other hand, the result of <code>num_get</code> conversion of such
out-of-range floating-point values results in the most positive/negative
representable value.
Although many C library implementations do implement <code>HUGE_VAL</code>
(etc.) as the highest representable (which is, usually, the infinity), 
this isn't required by the C standard. The C library specification makes no
statement regarding the value of <code>HUGE_VAL</code> and friends, which
potentially raises the same compatibility issue as in the above case of
unsigned integers.
In addition, neither C nor C++ define symbolic constants for the maximum
representable floating-point values (they only do so only for the maximum
representable <i>finite</i> floating-point values), which raises a 
usability
issue (it would be hard for the programmer to check the result of
<code>num_get</code> against overflow).
</p>
<p>
As such, we propose to adjust the specification of <code>num_get</code> to
closely follow the behavior of all of its underlying C functions.
</p>



<note>
2010 Rapperswil:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
Some concern that this is changing the specification for an existing C++03 function, but it was 
pointed out that this was underspecified as resolved by issue 23.  This is clean-up for that 
issue in turn. Some concern that we are trying to solve the same problem in both clause 22 and 27.
</p>
<p>
Bill: There's a change here as to whether val is stored to in an error case.
</p>
<p>
Pablo: Don't think this changes whether val is stored to or not, but changes the value that is stored.
</p>
<p>
Bill: Remembers having skirmishes with customers and testers as to whether val is stored to, and the resolution was not to store in error cases.
</p>
<p>
Howard: Believes since C++03 we made a change to always store in overflow.
</p>
<p>
Everyone took some time to review the issue.
</p>
<p>
Pablo: C++98 definitely did not store any value during an error condition.
</p>
<p>
Dietmar: Depends on the question of what is considered an error, and whether overflow is an error or not, which was the crux of LWG 23.
</p>
<p>
Pablo: Yes, but given the "zero, if the conversion function fails to convert the entire field", we are requiring every error condition to store.
</p>
<p>
Bill: When did this happen?
</p>
<p>
Alisdair: One of the last two or three meetings.
</p>
<p>
Dietmar: To store a value in case of failure is a very bad idea.
</p>
<p>
Move to Open, needs more study.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>2011-03-24 Madrid meeting</note>

<p>Move to deferred</p>

<note>
2011 Bloomington
</note>

<p>
The proposed wording looks good, no-one sure why this was held back before.  Move to Review.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>
Change <sref ref="[facet.num.get.virtuals]"/> as follows:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<b>Stage 3:</b>
The sequence of <code>char</code>s accumulated in stage 2 (the field) is
converted to a numeric value by the rules of one of the functions declared in
the header <code>&lt;cstdlib&gt;</code>:
</p>
<ul>
<li>For a signed integer value, the function <code>strtoll</code>.</li>
<li>For an unsigned integer value, the function <code>strtoull</code>.</li>
<li><ins>For a <code>float</code> value, the function
    <code>strtof</code>.</ins></li>
<li><ins>For a <code>double</code> value, the function
    <code>strtod</code>.</ins></li>
<li>For a <del>floating-point</del> <ins><code>long double</code></ins>
    value, the function <code>strtold</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The numeric value to be stored can be one of:
</p>
<ul>
<li>zero, if the conversion function fails to convert the entire field.
    <del><code>ios_base::failbit</code> is assigned to <code>err</code>.</del></li>
<li>the most positive <ins>(or negative)</ins> representable value, if
    the field <ins>to be converted to a signed integer type</ins> represents a
    value too large positive <ins>(or negative)</ins> to be represented in
    <code>val</code>.
    <del><code>ios_base::failbit</code> is assigned to <code>err</code>.</del></li>
<li><del>the most negative representable value or zero for an unsigned integer
    type, if the field represents a value too large negative to be represented
    in <code>val</code>.
    <code>ios_base::failbit</code> is assigned to <code>err</code>.</del></li>
<li><ins>the most positive representable value, if the field to be converted to
    an unsigned integer type represents a value that cannot be represented in
    <code>val</code>.</ins></li>
<li>the converted value, otherwise.</li>
</ul>
<p>
The resultant numeric value is stored in <code>val</code>.
<ins>If the conversion function fails to convert the entire field, or if the
field represents a value outside the range of representable values,
<code>ios_base::failbit</code> is assigned to <code>err</code>.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
