<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="404" status="CD1">
<title>May a replacement allocation function be declared inline?</title>
<section><sref ref="[replacement.functions]"/> <sref ref="[new.delete]"/></section>
<submitter>Matt Austern</submitter>
<date>24 Apr 2003</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The eight basic dynamic memory allocation functions (single-object
and array versions of ::operator new and ::operator delete, in the
ordinary and nothrow forms) are replaceable.  A C++ program may
provide an alternative definition for any of them, which will be used
in preference to the implementation's definition.  
</p>

<p>
Three different parts of the standard mention requirements on
replacement functions: <sref ref="[replacement.functions]"/>, <sref ref="[new.delete.single]"/>
and <sref ref="[new.delete.array]"/>, and <sref ref="[basic.stc.auto]"/>.
</p>

<p>None of these three places say whether a replacement function may
  be declared inline.  <sref ref="[new.delete.single]"/> paragraph 2 specifies a
  signature for the replacement function, but that's not enough:
  the <tt>inline</tt> specifier is not part of a function's signature.
  One might also reason from <sref ref="[dcl.fct.spec]"/> paragraph 2, which
  requires that "an inline function shall be defined in every
  translation unit in which it is used," but this may not be quite
  specific enough either.  We should either explicitly allow or
  explicitly forbid inline replacement memory allocation
  functions.</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Add a new sentence to the end of <sref ref="[replacement.functions]"/> paragraph 3:
"The program's definitions shall not be specified as <tt>inline</tt>.
No diagnostic is required."
</p>

<note>Kona: added "no diagnostic is required"</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>
The fact that <tt>inline</tt> isn't mentioned appears to have been
nothing more than an oversight.  Existing implementations do not
permit inline functions as replacement memory allocation functions.
Providing this functionality would be difficult in some cases, and is
believed to be of limited value.
</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
