<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2232" status="NAD Future">
<title>[CD] The <tt>char_traits</tt> specializations should declare their <tt>length()</tt>, <tt>compare()</tt>, and 
<tt>find()</tt> members constexpr</title>
<section><sref ref="[char.traits.specializations]"/></section>
<submitter>Jeffrey Yasskin</submitter>
<date>24 Dec 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p><b>Addresses ES 14, US 19</b></p>

<p>
These functions have easy recursive constexpr implementations that, unfortunately, aren't efficient at runtime. 
EWG is still figuring out how to solve this problem in general (e.g., 
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2012/n3444.html">N3444</a> isn't sufficient to avoid 
stack overflows in debug builds or to get the optimal assembly-based implementations at runtime), so users can't 
portably solve this problem for themselves, but implementations can use compiler-specific techniques to choose 
the right implementation inside their standard libraries.
</p>

<p>
The LWG is still undecided about whether individual implementations can add constexpr to these functions, so we 
need to add <tt>constexpr</tt> to the standard here for implementations to be able to improve this.
</p>

<note>2013-03-15 Issues Teleconference</note>
<p>
Moved to Open.
</p>
<p>
There are a number of people who have a strong interest in this issue not available for the telecon.
</p>
<p>
It also plays at the heart of a discussion about library freedoms for <tt>constexpr</tt> and specifying
a library that may depend on unspecified compiler intrinsics to be implementable.
</p>

<note>2013-09 Chicago</note>
<p>
Moved to NAD Future.
</p>
<p>
While it is clear that this feature can be implemented using only C++14 <tt>constexpr</tt> features,
there is real concern that we cannot call the efficient, highly optimized, C implementations of these
functions under a C++14 <tt>constexpr</tt> implentation, nor implement similar ourselves as this
typically involves use of inline <tt>asm</tt> instructions.
</p>
<p>
Clang and libc++ have some experience of using intrinsics to try to address the perfomance issue, but
the current intrinsics are not general enough to support <tt>char_traits</tt>.  The intrinsics support
only operations on character string literals, and the string literal is no longer visible <i>as</i> a
literal after passing as a <tt>const char *</tt> to the <tt>char_traits</tt> functions.
</p>
<p>
Additional concern was raised that these operations are unlikely to be useful anyway, as the only client
is <tt>basic_string</tt> which relies on dynamic memory allocation, and so cannot effectively be made a
literal type.  Jeffrey then pointed out the pending <tt>string_view</tt> library that will also use
<tt>char_traits</tt> and would most certainly benefit from being a literal type.
</p>

<p>
Given the choice of giving up performance on a critical library component, or requiring a compiler
intrisic with only unsuccessful implementation experience, the consensus is to not reject this, unless
compelling implementation experience is demonstrated.  NAD Future seems the appropriate resolution.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3691.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>In <sref ref="[char.traits.specializations.char]"/>, <sref ref="[char.traits.specializations.char16_t]"/>, 
<sref ref="[char.traits.specializations.char32_t]"/>, and <sref ref="[char.traits.specializations.wchar.t]"/>:</p>
<blockquote><pre>
static <ins>constexpr</ins> int compare(const char_type* s1, const char_type* s2, size_t n);
static <ins>constexpr</ins> size_t length(const char_type* s);
static <ins>constexpr</ins> const char_type* find(const char_type* s, size_t n, const char_type&amp; a);
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
