<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2198" status="New">
<title><tt>max_load_factor(z)</tt> makes no strong guatantees, but bans useful behavior</title>
<section><sref ref="[unord.req]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>09 Oct 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
The user cannot specify a <tt>max_load_factor</tt> for their unordered container
at construction, it must be supplied after the event, when the container is
potentially not empty.  The contract for this method is deliberately vague, not
guaranteeing to use the value supplied by the user, and any value actually used
will be used as a ceiling that the container will <i>attempt</i> to respect.
</p>
<p>
The only guarantee we have is that, if user requests a <tt>max_load_factor</tt>
that is less than the current <tt>load_factor</tt>, then the operation will take
constant time, thus outlawing an implementation that chooses to rehash and so
preserve as a class invariant that <tt>load_factor &lt; max_load_factor</tt>.
</p>
<p>
Reasonable options conforming to the standard include ignoring the user's request
if the requested value is too low, or deferring the rehash to the next <tt>insert</tt>
operation and allowing the container to have a strange state (wrt <tt>max_load_factor</tt>)
until then - and there is still the question of rehashing if the next <tt>insert</tt>
is for a duplicate key in a unique container.
</p>
<p>
Given the deliberate vagueness of the current wording, to support a range of reasonable
(but not <i>perfect</i>) behaviors, it is not clear why the equally reasonable rehash
to restore the constraint should be outlawed.  It is not thought that this is a performance
critical operation, where users will be repeatedly setting low load factors on populated
containers, in a tight or (less unlikely) an instant response scenario.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>

</resolution>

</issue>
