<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="471" status="WP">
<title>result of what() implementation-defined</title>
<section><sref ref="[exception]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>28 Jun 2004</date>

<discussion>

<p>[lib.exception] specifies the following:</p>
<pre>
    exception (const exception&amp;) throw();
    exception&amp; operator= (const exception&amp;) throw();

    -4- Effects: Copies an exception object.
    -5- Notes: The effects of calling what() after assignment
        are implementation-defined.
</pre>

<p>
First, does the Note only apply to the assignment operator? If so,
what are the effects of calling what() on a copy of an object? Is
the returned pointer supposed to point to an identical copy of
the NTBS returned by what() called on the original object or not?
</p>

<p>
Second, is this Note intended to extend to all the derived classes
in section 19? I.e., does the standard provide any guarantee for
the effects of what() called on a copy of any of the derived class
described in section 19?
</p>

<p>
Finally, if the answer to the first question is no, I believe it
constitutes a defect since throwing an exception object typically
implies invoking the copy ctor on the object. If the answer is yes,
then I believe the standard ought to be clarified to spell out
exactly what the effects are on the copy (i.e., after the copy
ctor was called).
</p>

<note>Redmond: Yes, this is fuzzy.  The issue of derived classes is
  fuzzy too.</note>

<note>
Batavia: Howard provided wording.
</note>

<note>
Bellevue:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Eric concerned this is unimplementable, due to nothrow guarantees.
Suggested implementation would involve reference counting.
</p>
<p>
Is the implied reference counting subtle enough to call out a note on
implementation? Probably not.
</p>
<p>
If reference counting required, could we tighten specification further
to require same pointer value? Probably an overspecification, especially
if exception classes defer evalutation of final string to calls to
what().
</p>
<p>
Remember issue moved open and not resolved at Batavia, but cannot
remember who objected to canvas a disenting opinion - please speak up if
you disagree while reading these minutes!
</p>
<p>
Move to Ready as we are accepting words unmodified.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
Sophia Antipolis:
</note>

<blockquote>
The issue was pulled from Ready.  It needs to make clear that only homogenous copying
is intended to be supported, not coping from a derived to a base.
</blockquote>

<note>
Batavia (2009-05):
</note>
<blockquote>
<p>
Howard supplied the following replacement wording
for paragraph 7 of the proposed resolution:
</p>
<blockquote>
<ins>-7- <i>Postcondition:</i> <tt>what()</tt> shall return the same NTBS
  as would be obtained by using <tt>static_cast</tt>
  to cast the rhs to the same types as the lhs
  and then calling <tt>what()</tt> on that possibly sliced object.</ins>
</blockquote>
<p>
Pete asks what "the same NTBS" means.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07-30 Niels adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
Further discussion in the thread starting with c++std-lib-24512.
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-09-24 Niels provided updated wording:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
I think the resolution should at least guarantee
that the result of <tt>what()</tt> is independent of whether the compiler does
copy-elision. And for any class derived from <tt>std::excepion</tt> that has a
constructor that allows specifying a <tt>what_arg</tt>, it should make sure that
the text of a user-provided <tt>what_arg</tt> is preserved, when the object is
copied. Note that all the implementations I've tested already appear to
satisfy the proposed resolution, including MSVC 2008 SP1, Apache
stdcxx-4.2.1, GCC 4.1.2, GCC 4.3.2, and CodeGear C++ 6.13.
</p>
<p>
The proposed resolution was updated with help from Daniel Kr&uuml;gler;
the update aims to clarify that the proposed postcondition only
applies to homogeneous copying.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Moved to Ready after inserting "publicly accessible" in two places.
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>
Change <sref ref="[exception]"/> to:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-1- The class <tt>exception</tt> defines the base class for the types of
objects thrown as exceptions by C++ standard library components, and
certain expressions, to report errors detected during program execution.
</p>
<p><ins>
Each standard library class <tt>T</tt> that derives from class
<tt>exception</tt> shall have a publicly accessible copy constructor and a publicly accessible copy assignment
operator that do not exit with an exception. These member functions
shall preserve the following postcondition: If two objects <i>lhs</i>
and <i>rhs</i> both have dynamic type <tt>T</tt>, and <i>lhs</i> is a
copy of <i>rhs</i>, then <tt>strcmp(<i>lhs</i>.what(),
<i>rhs</i>.what()) == 0</tt>.
</ins></p>
<p>
 ...
</p>

<pre>exception(const exception&amp; <ins>rhs</ins>) throw();
exception&amp; operator=(const exception&amp; <ins>rhs</ins>) throw();</pre>

<blockquote>
<p>
-4- <i>Effects:</i> Copies an exception object.
</p>
<p>
<del> -5- <i>Remarks:</i> The effects of calling <tt>what()</tt> after assignment
are implementation-defined.</del>
</p>
<p>
<ins>-5- <i>Postcondition:</i>
	If <tt>*this</tt>
	and <i>rhs</i> both have dynamic type <tt>exception</tt>
	then <tt>strcmp(what(), <i>rhs</i>.what()) == 0</tt>.</ins>
</p>

</blockquote>

</blockquote>

</resolution>
</issue>
