<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp " ">
] >

<issue num="340" status="CD1">
<title>interpretation of <tt>has_facet&lt;Facet&gt;(loc)</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[locale.category]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>18 Sep 2001</date>

<discussion>
<p>
It's unclear whether 22.1.1.1.1, p3 says that
<tt>has_facet&lt;Facet&gt;(loc)</tt> returns true for any <tt>Facet</tt>
from Table 51 or whether it includes Table 52 as well:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
For any locale <tt>loc</tt> either constructed, or returned by
locale::classic(), and any facet <tt>Facet</tt> that is a member of a
standard category, <tt>has_facet&lt;Facet&gt;(loc)</tt> is true. Each
locale member function which takes a <tt>locale::category</tt>
argument operates on the corresponding set of facets.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
It seems that it comes down to which facets are considered to be members of a
standard category. Intuitively, I would classify all the facets in Table 52 as
members of their respective standard categories, but there are an unbounded set
of them...
</p>

<p>
The paragraph implies that, for instance, <tt>has_facet&lt;num_put&lt;C,
OutputIterator&gt; &gt;(loc)</tt> must always return true. I don't think that's
possible. If it were, then <tt>use_facet&lt;num_put&lt;C, OutputIterator&gt;
&gt;(loc)</tt> would have to return a reference to a distinct object for each
valid specialization of <tt>num_put&lt;C, OutputIteratory&gt;</tt>, which is
clearly impossible.
</p>

<p>
On the other hand, if none of the facets in Table 52 is a member of a standard
category then none of the locale member functions that operate on entire
categories of facets will work properly.
</p>

<p>
It seems that what p3 should mention that it's required (permitted?)
to hold only for specializations of <tt>Facet</tt> from Table 52 on
<tt>C</tt> from the set { <tt>char</tt>, <tt>wchar_t</tt> }, and
<tt>InputIterator</tt> and <tt>OutputIterator</tt> from the set of
{
{i,o}<tt>streambuf_iterator</tt>&lt;{<tt>char</tt>,<tt>wchar_t</tt>}<tt>&gt;</tt>
}.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>In <sref ref="[locale.category]"/>, paragraph 3, change
"that is a member of a standard category" to "shown in Table 51".</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The facets in Table 52 are an unbounded set.  Locales should not be
required to contain an infinite number of facets.</p> 

<p>It's not necessary to talk about which values of InputIterator and
OutputIterator must be supported.  Table 51 already contains a
complete list of the ones we need.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>

