<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1330" status="New">
<title>Move container requirements into requirements tables</title>
<section><sref ref="[container.requirements]"/></section>
<submitter>Nicolai Josuttis</submitter>
<date>10 Mar 2010</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Abstract:
</p>
<p>
In general, it seems that in a couple of places container behavior is
not described in requirement tables although it is a general behavior.
</p>

<p>
History:
</p>

<p>
Issue <iref ref="676"/> added move semantics to unordered containers.
For the added insert functions the Editor requested to put their
semantic description into a requirements table rather than describing
them for each container individually. The text however was taken from
the associative containers, where we also have the semantics for each
container described. Also, <iref ref="1034"/> is to some extend
requesting a clarification of the requirement tables and it turned out
that in other places we have the same problem (e.g. we have no general
requirement for type pointer and const_pointer although each container
has them with issue <iref ref="1306"/>).
</p>

<p>
From my personal list of functions in requirement tables
and containers, the following types/functions are missing in
requirement tables:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<tt>pointer</tt>, <tt>const_pointer</tt> in Table 91 (container requirements)
</li>
<li>
<p>
all copy constructors, copy constructors with allocator,
 assignment operators, and insert operators
 with move semantics for associative and unordered containers
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
ContType c1(c2&amp;&amp;)
ContType c1(c2&amp;&amp;,alloc)
c1 = c2&amp;&amp;
c.insert(val&amp;&amp;)
c.insert(pos,val&amp;&amp;)
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
As a special case, we lack the following requirements for all sequence
containers BUT array (so special wording or a new container category is
required):
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>
constructor with only a size argument
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
ContType c(num)
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>
copy constructor with allocator and move semantics
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
ContType c1(c2&amp;&amp;,alloc)
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>
all constructors that insert multiple elements with additional allocator
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
ContType c(num, val,alloc)
ContType c(beg, end,alloc)
ContType c(initlist,alloc)
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>
all resize functiuons:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
c.resize(num)
c.resize(num,val)
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Note that we also might have to add additional requirements on other
places for sequence containers because having an allocator requires
additional statements for the treatment of the allocators. E.g. swap for
containers with allocators is not specified in any requirement table.
</p>

<p>
And finally, if we have the requirements in the requirements tables, we
can remove the corresponding descriptions for the individual container.
However, note that sequence container requirements have NO complexity
column, so that we still need container specific descriptions for the
functions listed there.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
