<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1046" status="Resolved">
<title>Response to UK 329</title>
<section><sref ref="[futures]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>12 Mar 2009</date>

<discussion>

<p><b>Addresses UK 329</b></p>

<p>
<tt>future</tt>, <tt>promise</tt> and <tt>packaged_task</tt> provide a
framework for creating future values, but a simple function to tie all
three components together is missing. Note that we only need a *simple*
facility for C++0x. Advanced thread pools are to be left for TR2.
</p>

<p>
Simple Proposal:
</p>

<p>
Provide a simple function along the lines of: 
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt; typename F, typename ... Args &gt;
  requires Callable&lt; F, Args... &gt;
    future&lt; Callable::result_type &gt; async( F&amp;&amp; f, Args &amp;&amp; ... ); 
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
Semantics are similar to creating a <tt>thread</tt> object with a <tt>packaged_task</tt>
invoking <tt>f</tt> with <tt>forward&lt;Args&gt;(args...)</tt>
but details are left unspecified to allow different scheduling and thread
spawning implementations. 
</p>
<p>
It is unspecified whether a task submitted to async is run on its own thread
or a thread previously used for another async task. If a call to <tt>async</tt>
succeeds, it shall be safe to wait for it from any thread. 
</p>
<p>
The state of <tt>thread_local</tt> variables shall be preserved during <tt>async</tt> calls. 
</p>
<p>
No two incomplete async tasks shall see the same value of
<tt>this_thread::get_id()</tt>. 
</p>
<p>
[<i>Note:</i> this effectively forces new tasks to be run on a new thread, or a
fixed-size pool with no queue. If the 
library is unable to spawn a new thread or there are no free worker threads
then the <tt>async</tt> call should fail. <i>--end note</i>] 
</p>

<note>
Summit:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
The concurrency subgroup has revisited this issue and decided that it
could be considered a defect according to the Kona compromise. A task
group was formed lead by Lawrence Crowl and Bjarne Stroustrup to write a
paper for Frankfort proposing a simple asynchronous launch facility
returning a <tt>future</tt>. It was agreed that the callable must be run on a
separate thread from the caller, but not necessarily a brand-new thread.
The proposal might or might not allow for an implementation that uses
fixed-size or unlimited thread pools.
</p>
<p>
Bjarne in c++std-lib-23121: I think that what we agreed was that to
avoid deadlock <tt>async()</tt> would almost certainly be specified to  launch in
a different thread from the thread that executed <tt>async()</tt>, but I don't
think it was a specific design constraint.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Proposed resolution: see
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2996.htm">N2996</a>
(Herb's and Lawrence's paper on Async). Move state to <del>NAD editorial</del><ins>Resolved</ins>.
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
