<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="226" status="CD1">
<title>User supplied specializations or overloads of namespace std function templates</title>
<section><sref ref="[reserved.names]"/></section>
<submitter>Dave Abrahams</submitter>
<date>01 Apr 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>The issues are:&nbsp;</p>
<p>1. How can a 3rd party library implementor (lib1) write a version of a standard
algorithm which is specialized to work with his own class template?&nbsp;</p>
<p>2. How can another library implementor (lib2) write a generic algorithm which 
will take advantage of the specialized algorithm in lib1?</p>
<p>This appears to be the only viable answer under current language rules:</p>
<blockquote>
  <pre>namespace lib1
{
    // arbitrary-precision numbers using T as a basic unit
    template &lt;class T&gt;
    class big_num { //...
    };
    </pre>
  <pre>    // defining this in namespace std is illegal (it would be an
    // overload), so we hope users will rely on Koenig lookup
    template &lt;class T&gt;
    void swap(big_int&lt;T&gt;&amp;, big_int&lt;T&gt;&amp;);
}</pre>
  <pre>#include &lt;algorithm&gt;
namespace lib2
{
    template &lt;class T&gt;
    void generic_sort(T* start, T* end)
    {
            ...
        // using-declaration required so we can work on built-in types
        using std::swap;
        // use Koenig lookup to find specialized algorithm if available
        swap(*x, *y);
    }
}</pre>
</blockquote>
<p>This answer has some drawbacks. First of all, it makes writing lib2 difficult
and somewhat slippery. The implementor needs to remember to write the
using-declaration, or generic_sort will fail to compile when T is a built-in
type. The second drawback is that the use of this style in lib2 effectively
&quot;reserves&quot; names in any namespace which defines types which may
eventually be used with lib2. This may seem innocuous at first when applied to
names like swap, but consider more ambiguous names like unique_copy() instead.
It is easy to imagine the user wanting to define these names differently in his
own namespace. A definition with semantics incompatible with the standard
library could cause serious problems (see issue <iref ref="225"/>).</p>
<p>Why, you may ask, can't we just partially specialize std::swap()? It's
because the language doesn't allow for partial specialization of function
templates. If you write:</p>
<blockquote>
  <pre>namespace std
{
    template &lt;class T&gt;
    void swap(lib1::big_int&lt;T&gt;&amp;, lib1::big_int&lt;T&gt;&amp;);
}</pre>
</blockquote>
<p>You have just overloaded std::swap, which is illegal under the current
language rules. On the other hand, the following full specialization is legal:</p>
<blockquote>
  <pre>namespace std
{
    template &lt;&gt;
    void swap(lib1::other_type&amp;, lib1::other_type&amp;);
}</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>This issue reflects concerns raised by the &quot;Namespace issue
with specialized swap&quot; thread on comp.lang.c++.moderated. A
similar set of concerns was earlier raised on the boost.org mailing
list and the ACCU-general mailing list.  Also see library reflector
message c++std-lib-7354.</p>

<p>
J. C. van Winkel points out (in c++std-lib-9565) another unexpected
fact: it's impossible to output a container of std::pair's using copy
and an ostream_iterator, as long as both pair-members are built-in or
std:: types.  That's because a user-defined operator&lt;&lt; for (for
example) std::pair&lt;const std::string, int&gt; will not be found:
lookup for operator&lt;&lt; will be performed only in namespace std.
Opinions differed on whether or not this was a defect, and, if so,
whether the defect is that something is wrong with user-defined
functionality and std, or whether it's that the standard library does
not provide an operator&lt;&lt; for std::pair&lt;&gt;.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>Adopt the wording proposed in Howard Hinnant's paper
  N1523=03-0106, "Proposed Resolution To LWG issues 225, 226, 229".</p>


<note>Tokyo: Summary, &quot;There is no conforming way to extend
std::swap for user defined templates.&quot;&nbsp; The LWG agrees that
there is a problem.  Would like more information before
proceeding. This may be a core issue.  Core issue 229 has been opened
to discuss the core aspects of this problem. It was also noted that
submissions regarding this issue have been received from several
sources, but too late to be integrated into the issues list.
</note>

<note>Post-Tokyo: A paper with several proposed resolutions,
J16/00-0029==WG21/N1252, &quot;Shades of namespace std functions
&quot; by Alan Griffiths, is in the Post-Tokyo mailing. It
should be considered a part of this issue.</note>

<note>Toronto: Dave Abrahams and Peter Dimov have proposed a
resolution that involves core changes: it would add partial
specialization of function template.  The Core Working Group is
reluctant to add partial specialization of function templates.  It is
viewed as a large change, CWG believes that proposal presented leaves
some syntactic issues unanswered; if the CWG does add partial
specialization of function templates, it wishes to develop its own
proposal.  The LWG continues to believe that there is a serious
problem: there is no good way for users to force the library to use
user specializations of generic standard library functions, and in
certain cases (e.g. transcendental functions called by
<tt>valarray</tt> and <tt>complex</tt>) this is important.  Koenig
lookup isn't adequate, since names within the library must be
qualified with <tt>std</tt> (see issue 225), specialization doesn't
work (we don't have partial specialization of function templates), and
users aren't permitted to add overloads within namespace std.
</note>

<note>Copenhagen: Discussed at length, with no consensus.  Relevant
papers in the pre-Copenhagen mailing: N1289, N1295, N1296.  Discussion
focused on four options. (1) Relax restrictions on overloads within
namespace std. (2) Mandate that the standard library use unqualified
calls for <tt>swap</tt> and possibly other functions.  (3) Introduce
helper class templates for <tt>swap</tt> and possibly other functions.
(4) Introduce partial specialization of function templates.  Every
option had both support and opposition.  Straw poll (first number is
support, second is strongly opposed): (1) 6, 4; (2) 6, 7; (3) 3, 8;
(4) 4, 4.</note>

<note>Redmond: Discussed, again no consensus.  Herb presented an
argument that a user who is defining a type <tt>T</tt> with an
associated <tt>swap</tt> should not be expected to put that
<tt>swap</tt> in namespace std, either by overloading or by partial
specialization.  The argument is that <tt>swap</tt> is part of
<tt>T</tt>'s interface, and thus should to in the same namespace as
<tt>T</tt> and only in that namespace.  If we accept this argument,
the consequence is that standard library functions should use
unqualified call of <tt>swap</tt>.  (And which other functions? Any?)
A small group (Nathan, Howard, Jeremy, Dave, Matt, Walter, Marc) will
try to put together a proposal before the next meeting.</note>

<note>Cura&ccedil;ao: An LWG-subgroup spent an afternoon working on issues
225, 226, and 229.  Their conclusion was that the issues should be
separated into an LWG portion (Howard's paper, N1387=02-0045), and a
EWG portion (Dave will write a proposal). The LWG and EWG had
(separate) discussions of this plan the next day.  The proposed
resolution is the one proposed by Howard.</note>

<note>Santa Cruz: the LWG agreed with the general direction of
  Howard's paper, N1387.  (Roughly: Koenig lookup is disabled unless
  we say otherwise; this issue is about when we do say otherwise.)
  However, there were concerns about wording.  Howard will provide new
  wording.  Bill and Jeremy will review it.</note>

<note>Kona: Howard proposed the new wording.  The LWG accepted his
  proposed resolution.</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>Informally: introduce a Swappable concept, and specify that the
  value types of the iterators passed to certain standard algorithms
  (such as iter_swap, swap_ranges, reverse, rotate, and sort) conform
  to that concept.  The Swappable concept will make it clear that
  these algorithms use unqualified lookup for the calls
  to <tt>swap</tt>.  Also, in <sref ref="[valarray.transcend]"/> paragraph 1,
  state that the valarray transcendentals use unqualified lookup.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
