<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="246" status="Dup">
<title><tt>a.insert(p,t)</tt> is incorrectly specified</title>
<section><sref ref="[associative.reqmts]"/></section>
<submitter>Mark Rodgers</submitter>
<date>19 May 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>Closed issue 192 raised several problems with the specification of
this function, but was rejected as Not A Defect because it was too big
a change with unacceptable impacts on existing implementations.
However, issues remain that could be addressed with a smaller change
and with little or no consequent impact.</p>

<ol>
   <li><p> The specification is inconsistent with the original
   proposal and with several implementations.</p>

   <p>The initial implementation by Hewlett Packard only ever looked
   immediately <i>before</i> p, and I do not believe there was any
   intention to standardize anything other than this behavior.
   Consequently, current implementations by several leading
   implementors also look immediately before p, and will only insert
   after p in logarithmic time.  I am only aware of one implementation
   that does actually look after p, and it looks before p as well.  It
   is therefore doubtful that existing code would be relying on the
   behavior defined in the standard, and it would seem that fixing
   this defect as proposed below would standardize existing
   practice.</p></li>

   <li><p>
   The specification is inconsistent with insertion for sequence
   containers.</p>

   <p>This is difficult and confusing to teach to newcomers.  All
   insert operations that specify an iterator as an insertion location
   should have a consistent meaning for the location represented by
   that iterator.</p></li>

   <li><p> As specified, there is no way to hint that the insertion
   should occur at the beginning of the container, and the way to hint
   that it should occur at the end is long winded and unnatural.</p>

   <p>For a container containing n elements, there are n+1 possible
   insertion locations and n+1 valid iterators.  For there to be a
   one-to-one mapping between iterators and insertion locations, the
   iterator must represent an insertion location immediately before
   the iterator.</p></li>

   <li><p> When appending sorted ranges using insert_iterators,
   insertions are guaranteed to be sub-optimal.</p>

   <p>In such a situation, the optimum location for insertion is
   always immediately after the element previously inserted.  The
   mechanics of the insert iterator guarantee that it will try and
   insert after the element after that, which will never be correct.
   However, if the container first tried to insert before the hint,
   all insertions would be performed in amortized constant
   time.</p></li>
</ol>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>In 23.1.2 [lib.associative.reqmts] paragraph 7, table 69, make
the following changes in the row for a.insert(p,t):</p>

<p><i>assertion/note pre/post condition:</i>
<br/>Change the last sentence from</p>
     <blockquote><p>
     &quot;iterator p is a hint pointing to where the insert should
     start to search.&quot;
     </p></blockquote>
<p>to</p>
     <blockquote><p>
     &quot;iterator p is a hint indicating that immediately before p
     may be a correct location where the insertion could occur.&quot;
     </p></blockquote>

<p><i>complexity:</i><br/>
Change the words "right after" to "immediately before".</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<duplicate><iref ref="233"/></duplicate>
</rationale>
</issue>
