<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="751" status="NAD">
<title>change pass-by-reference members of <tt>vector&lt;bool&gt;</tt> to pass-by-value?</title>
<section><sref ref="[vector.bool]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>10 Oct 2007</date>

<discussion>
<p>
A number of vector&lt;bool&gt; members take const bool&amp; as arguments.
Is there any chance we could change them to pass-by-value or would I 
be wasting everyone's time if wrote up an issue?
</p>

<note>
post Bellevue:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
As we understand it, the original requester (Martin Sebor) would like
for implementations to be permitted to pass-by-value. Alisdair suggests
that if this is to be resolved, it should be resolved more generally,
e.g. in other containers as well.
</p>
<p>
We note that this would break ABI. However, we also suspect that this
might be covered under the "as-if" rule in section 1.9.
</p>
<p>
Many in the group feel that for vector&lt;bool&gt;, this is a "don't care",
and that at this point in the process it's not worth the bandwidth.
</p>
<p>
Issue <iref ref="679"/> -- which was in ready status pre-Bellevue and is
now in the working paper -- is related to this, though not a duplicate.
</p>
<p>
Moving to Open with a task for Alisdair to craft a informative note to
be put whereever appropriate in the WP. This note would clarify places
where pass-by-const-ref can be transformed to pass-by-value under the
as-if rule.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
San Francisco:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
This is really a clause 17 issue, rather than something specific to vector&lt;bool&gt;.
</p>
<p>
Move to Open. Alisdair to provide a resolution. Alternately, Howard can
close this as NAD and then open a new issue to handle the general issue
(rather than the vector&lt;bool&gt; one).
</p>
<p>
Howard:  Haven't yet opened new issue.  Lacking wording for it.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt:
</note>

<blockquote>
NAD.  Insufficient motivation to make any changes.
</blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
