<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2259" status="New">
<title>Issues in 17.6.5.5 rules for member functions</title>
<section><sref ref="[member.functions]"/></section>
<submitter>Richard Smith</submitter>
<date>12 May 2013</date>

<discussion>
<p>
<sref ref="[member.functions]"/> p2 says:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
&quot;An implementation may declare additional non-virtual member function signatures within a class:
</p>
<ul>
<p>by adding arguments with default values to a member function signature; [Footnote: Hence, the address of a member 
function of a class in the C++ standard library has an unspecified type.] [<i>Note</i>: An implementation
may not add arguments with default values to virtual, global, or non-member functions. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]</p>
<p>by replacing a member function signature with default values by two or more member function signatures
with equivalent behavior; and</p>
<p>by adding a member function signature for a member function name.&quot;</p>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li>
<p>
This wording is not using the correct terminology. "by adding arguments with default values" presumably means 
"by adding parameters with default arguments", and likewise throughout.
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
This paragraph only allows an implementation to declare "additional" signatures, but the first bullet is talking 
about replacing a standard signature with one with additional parameters.
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
None of these bullets allows a member function with no <i>ref</i>-qualifier to be replaced by signatures with <i>ref</i>-qualifiers 
(a situation which was just discussed on std-proposals), and likewise for <i>cv</i>-qualifiers. Presumably that is 
not intentional, and such changes should be permissible.
</p>
</li>
</ol>

<p>
I think the first two items are probably editorial, since the intent is clear.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
