<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="317" status="CD1">
<title>Instantiation vs. specialization of facets</title>
<section><sref ref="[localization]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>4 May 2001</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The localization section of the standard refers to specializations of
the facet templates as instantiations even though the required facets
are typically specialized rather than explicitly (or implicitly)
instantiated. In the case of ctype&lt;char&gt; and
ctype_byname&lt;char&gt; (and the wchar_t versions), these facets are
actually required to be specialized. The terminology should be
corrected to make it clear that the standard doesn't mandate explicit
instantiation (the term specialization encompasses both explicit
instantiations and specializations).
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
In the following paragraphs, replace all occurrences of the word
instantiation or instantiations with specialization or specializations,
respectively:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
22.1.1.1.1, p4, Table 52, 22.2.1.1, p2, 22.2.1.5, p3, 22.2.1.5.1, p5,
22.2.1.5.2, p10, 22.2.2, p2, 22.2.3.1, p1, 22.2.3.1.2, p1, p2 and p3, 
22.2.4.1, p1, 22.2.4.1.2, p1, 22,2,5, p1, 22,2,6, p2, 22.2.6.3.2, p7, and
Footnote 242.
</p></blockquote>

<p>And change the text in 22.1.1.1.1, p4 from</p>

<blockquote><p>
    An implementation is required to provide those instantiations
    for facet templates identified as members of a category, and
    for those shown in Table 52:
</p></blockquote>

<p>to</p>

<blockquote><p>
    An implementation is required to provide those specializations...
</p></blockquote>

<note>Nathan will review these changes, and will look for places where
explicit specialization is necessary.</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>This is a simple matter of outdated language.  The language to
describe templates was clarified during the standardization process,
but the wording in clause 22 was never updated to reflect that
change.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>


