<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp " ">
]>

<issue num="358" status="CD1">
<title>interpreting <tt>thousands_sep</tt> after a <tt>decimal_point</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[facet.num.get.virtuals]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>12 Mar 2002</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I don't think <tt>thousands_sep</tt> is being treated correctly after
decimal_point has been seen. Since grouping applies only to the
integral part of the number, the first such occurrence should, IMO,
terminate Stage 2. (If it does not terminate it, then 22.2.2.1.2, p12
and 22.2.3.1.2, p3 need to explain how <tt>thousands_sep</tt> is to be
interpreted in the fractional part of a number.)
</p>

<p>
The easiest change I can think of that resolves this issue would be
something like below.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Change the first sentence of 22.2.2.1.2, p9 from
</p>

<blockquote><p>
    If discard is true then the position of the character is
    remembered, but the character is otherwise ignored. If it is not
    discarded, then a check is made to determine if c is allowed as
    the next character of an input field of the conversion specifier
    returned by stage 1. If so it is accumulated.
</p></blockquote>

<p>to</p>

<blockquote><p>
    If <tt>discard</tt> is true, then if <tt>'.'</tt> has not yet been
    accumulated, then the position of the character is remembered, but
    the character is otherwise ignored. Otherwise, if <tt>'.'</tt> has
    already been accumulated, the character is discarded and Stage 2
     terminates. ...
</p></blockquote>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>We believe this reflects the intent of the Standard.  Thousands sep
  characters after the decimal point are not useful in any locale.
  Some formatting conventions do group digits that follow the decimal
  point, but they usually introduce a different grouping character
  instead of reusing the thousand sep character.  If we want to add
  support for such conventions, we need to do so explicitly.</p>

</rationale>

</issue>
