<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2334" status="New">
<title><tt>atomic</tt>'s default constructor requires "uninitialized" state even for types with non-trivial default-constructor</title>
<section><sref ref="[atomics.types.operations.req]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>3 Oct 2013</date>

<discussion>
<p>
According to <sref ref="[atomics.types.operations.req]"/> p4,
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
A ::A () noexcept = default;
</pre><blockquote>
<p>
<i>Effects:</i> leaves the atomic object in an uninitialized state. [<i>Note:</i> These semantics ensure compatibility
with <tt>C</tt>. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
<p>
This implementation requirement is OK for POD types, like <tt>int</tt>, but <sref ref="[atomics.types.generic]"/> p1
intentionally allows template arguments of <tt>atomic</tt> with a non-trivial default constructor ("The type of the template argument 
<tt>T</tt> shall be trivially copyable (3.9)"), so this wording can be read in a way that makes the behaviour of the following code
undefined:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;atomic&gt;
#include &lt;iostream&gt;

struct S {
  S() noexcept : v(42) {}
  int v;
};

int main() {
  std::atomic&lt;S&gt; as; // Default-initialization
  std::cout &lt;&lt; as.load().v &lt;&lt; std::endl; // ?
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
For a user-defined emulation of <tt>atomic</tt> the expected outcome would be defined and the program would output "42",
but existing implementations differ and the result value is a "random number" for at least one implementation. This seems
very surprising to me.
<p/>
To realize that seemingly existing requirement, an implementation is either required to violate normal language rules internally
or to perform specific bit-randomization-techniques after the normal default-initialization that called the default constructor
of <tt>S</tt>.
<p/>
According to my understanding, the non-normative note in <sref ref="[atomics.types.operations.req]"/> p4 is intended to
refer to types that are valid <tt>C</tt>-types, but the example type <tt>S</tt> is not such a type.
<p/>
To make the mental model of <tt>atomic</tt>'s default constructor more intuitive for user-code, I suggest to clarify the wording
to have the effects of default-initialization instead. The current state seems more like an unintended effect of imprecise
language used here and has some similarities to wording that was incorrectly used to specify <tt>atomic_flag</tt> initialization 
as described by LWG <iref ref="2159"/>.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3691.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[atomics.types.operations.req]"/> p4 as indicated: <em>[Editorial note: There is no exposition-only
member in <tt>atomic</tt>, which makes it a bit hard to specify what actually is initialized, but the usage of the term "value" 
seems consistent with similar wording used to specify the effects of the atomic <tt>load</tt> functions]</em></p>

<blockquote><pre>
A ::A () noexcept = default;
</pre><blockquote>
<p>
-4- <i>Effects:</i> <del>leaves the atomic object in an uninitialized state</del><ins>The value of the atomic object
is default-initialized (<sref ref="[dcl.init]"/>)</ins>. [<i>Note:</i> These semantics ensure compatibility
with <tt>C</tt>. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
