<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="270" status="CD1">
<title>Binary search requirements overly strict</title>
<section><sref ref="[alg.binary.search]"/></section>
<submitter>Matt Austern</submitter>
<date>18 Oct 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Each of the four binary search algorithms (lower_bound, upper_bound,
equal_range, binary_search) has a form that allows the user to pass a
comparison function object.  According to 25.3, paragraph 2, that
comparison function object has to be a strict weak ordering.
</p>

<p>
This requirement is slightly too strict.  Suppose we are searching
through a sequence containing objects of type X, where X is some
large record with an integer key.  We might reasonably want to look
up a record by key, in which case we would want to write something
like this:
</p>
<pre>
    struct key_comp {
      bool operator()(const X&amp; x, int n) const {
        return x.key() &lt; n;
      }
    }

    std::lower_bound(first, last, 47, key_comp());
</pre>

<p>
key_comp is not a strict weak ordering, but there is no reason to
prohibit its use in lower_bound.
</p>

<p>
There's no difficulty in implementing lower_bound so that it allows
the use of something like key_comp.  (It will probably work unless an
implementor takes special pains to forbid it.)  What's difficult is
formulating language in the standard to specify what kind of
comparison function is acceptable.  We need a notion that's slightly
more general than that of a strict weak ordering, one that can encompass
a comparison function that involves different types.  Expressing that
notion may be complicated.
</p>

<p><i>Additional questions raised at the Toronto meeting:</i></p>
<ul>
<li> Do we really want to specify what ordering the implementor must
     use when calling the function object?  The standard gives 
     specific expressions when describing these algorithms, but it also
     says that other expressions (with different argument order) are
     equivalent.</li>
<li> If we are specifying ordering, note that the standard uses both
     orderings when describing <tt>equal_range</tt>.</li>
<li> Are we talking about requiring these algorithms to work properly
     when passed a binary function object whose two argument types
     are not the same, or are we talking about requirements when
     they are passed a binary function object with several overloaded
     versions of <tt>operator()</tt>?</li>
<li> The definition of a strict weak ordering does not appear to give
     any guidance on issues of overloading; it only discusses expressions,
     and all of the values in these expressions are of the same type.
     Some clarification would seem to be in order.</li>
</ul>

<p><i>Additional discussion from Copenhagen:</i></p>
<ul>
<li>It was generally agreed that there is a real defect here: if
the predicate is merely required to be a Strict Weak Ordering, then
it's possible to pass in a function object with an overloaded
operator(), where the version that's actually called does something
completely inappropriate.  (Such as returning a random value.)</li>

<li>An alternative formulation was presented in a paper distributed by
David Abrahams at the meeting, "Binary Search with Heterogeneous
Comparison", J16-01/0027 = WG21 N1313: Instead of viewing the
predicate as a Strict Weak Ordering acting on a sorted sequence, view
the predicate/value pair as something that partitions a sequence.
This is almost equivalent to saying that we should view binary search
as if we are given a unary predicate and a sequence, such that f(*p)
is true for all p below a specific point and false for all p above it.
The proposed resolution is based on that alternative formulation.</li>
</ul>
</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>Change 25.3 [lib.alg.sorting] paragraph 3 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  3 For all algorithms that take Compare, there is a version that uses
  operator&lt; instead. That is, comp(*i, *j) != false defaults to *i &lt;
  *j != false. For the algorithms to work correctly, comp has to
  induce a strict weak ordering on the values.
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  3 For all algorithms that take Compare, there is a version that uses
  operator&lt; instead. That is, comp(*i, *j) != false defaults to *i
  &lt; *j != false. For algorithms other than those described in
  lib.alg.binary.search (25.3.3) to work correctly, comp has to induce
  a strict weak ordering on the values.
</p></blockquote>

<p>Add the following paragraph after 25.3 [lib.alg.sorting] paragraph 5:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  -6- A sequence [start, finish) is partitioned with respect to an
  expression f(e) if there exists an integer n such that
  for all 0 &lt;= i &lt; distance(start, finish), f(*(begin+i)) is true if
  and only if i &lt; n.
</p></blockquote>

<p>Change 25.3.3 [lib.alg.binary.search] paragraph 1 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  -1- All of the algorithms in this section are versions of binary
   search and assume that the sequence being searched is in order
   according to the implied or explicit comparison function. They work
   on non-random access iterators minimizing the number of
   comparisons, which will be logarithmic for all types of
   iterators. They are especially appropriate for random access
   iterators, because these algorithms do a logarithmic number of
   steps through the data structure. For non-random access iterators
   they execute a linear number of steps.
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- All of the algorithms in this section are versions of binary
    search and assume that the sequence being searched is partitioned
    with respect to an expression formed by binding the search key to
    an argument of the implied or explicit comparison function. They
    work on non-random access iterators minimizing the number of
    comparisons, which will be logarithmic for all types of
    iterators. They are especially appropriate for random access
    iterators, because these algorithms do a logarithmic number of
    steps through the data structure. For non-random access iterators
    they execute a linear number of steps.
</p></blockquote>

<p>Change 25.3.3.1 [lib.lower.bound] paragraph 1 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: Type T is LessThanComparable
    (lib.lessthancomparable). 
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: The elements e of [first, last) are partitioned with
   respect to the expression e &lt; value or comp(e, value)
</p></blockquote>


<p>Remove 25.3.3.1 [lib.lower.bound] paragraph 2:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -2- Effects: Finds the first position into which value can be
    inserted without violating the ordering. 
</p></blockquote>

<p>Change 25.3.3.2 [lib.upper.bound] paragraph 1 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  -1- Requires: Type T is LessThanComparable (lib.lessthancomparable).
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: The elements e of [first, last) are partitioned with
   respect to the expression !(value &lt; e) or !comp(value, e)
</p></blockquote>

<p>Remove 25.3.3.2 [lib.upper.bound] paragraph 2:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -2- Effects: Finds the furthermost position into which value can be
    inserted without violating the ordering.
</p></blockquote>

<p>Change 25.3.3.3 [lib.equal.range] paragraph 1 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: Type T is LessThanComparable
    (lib.lessthancomparable).
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: The elements e of [first, last) are partitioned with
   respect to the expressions e &lt; value and !(value &lt; e) or
   comp(e, value) and !comp(value, e).  Also, for all elements e of
   [first, last), e &lt; value implies !(value &lt; e) or comp(e,
   value) implies !comp(value, e)
</p></blockquote>

<p>Change 25.3.3.3 [lib.equal.range] paragraph 2 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -2- Effects: Finds the largest subrange [i, j) such that the value
    can be inserted at any iterator k in it without violating the
    ordering. k satisfies the corresponding conditions: !(*k &lt; value)
    &amp;&amp; !(value &lt; *k) or comp(*k, value) == false &amp;&amp; comp(value, *k) ==
    false.
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<pre>
   -2- Returns: 
         make_pair(lower_bound(first, last, value),
                   upper_bound(first, last, value))
       or
         make_pair(lower_bound(first, last, value, comp),
                   upper_bound(first, last, value, comp))
</pre>

<p>Change 25.3.3.3 [lib.binary.search] paragraph 1 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: Type T is LessThanComparable
    (lib.lessthancomparable).
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
   -1- Requires: The elements e of [first, last) are partitioned with
   respect to the expressions e &lt; value and !(value &lt; e) or comp(e,
   value) and !comp(value, e). Also, for all elements e of [first,
   last), e &lt; value implies !(value &lt; e) or comp(e, value) implies
   !comp(value, e)
</p></blockquote>

<note>Copenhagen: Dave Abrahams provided this wording</note>

<note>Redmond: Minor changes in wording.  (Removed "non-negative", and
changed the "other than those described in" wording.) Also, the LWG
decided to accept the "optional" part.</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The proposed resolution reinterprets binary search. Instead of
thinking about searching for a value in a sorted range, we view that
as an important special case of a more general algorithm: searching
for the partition point in a partitioned range.</p>

<p>We also add a guarantee that the old wording did not: we ensure
that the upper bound is no earlier than the lower bound, that
the pair returned by equal_range is a valid range, and that the first
part of that pair is the lower bound.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
