<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2114" status="Open">
<title>Incorrect "<em>contextually</em> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>" requirements</title>
<section><sref ref="[nullablepointer.requirements]"/>,<sref ref="[input.iterators]"/>,<sref ref="[random.access.iterators]"/>,
<sref ref="[algorithms.general]"/>, <sref ref="[alg.sorting]"/>, <sref ref="[thread.req.paramname]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>9 Dec 2011</date>

<discussion>

<p>
As of <sref ref="[utility.arg.requirements]"/> Table 17&#47;18, the return types of the expressions
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
a == b
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
or
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
a &lt; b
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
for types satisfying the <tt>EqualityComparable</tt> or <tt>LessThanComparable</tt>
types, respectively, are required to be "convertible to <tt>bool</tt>" which corresponds to
a copy-initialization context. But several newer parts of the library that refer to 
such contexts have lowered the requirements taking  advantage of the new terminology of 
"<em>contextually</em> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>" instead, which corresponds to a 
direct-initialization context (In addition to "normal" direct-initialization constructions, 
operands of logical operations as well as <tt>if</tt> or <tt>switch</tt> conditions also 
belong to this special context).
<p/>
One example for these new requirements are input iterators which satisfy <tt>EqualityComparable</tt> 
but also specify that the expression
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
a != b
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
shall be just "<strong>contextually</strong> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>". The same discrepancy 
exists for requirement set <tt>NullablePointer</tt> in regard to several equality-related expressions.
<p/>
For random access iterators we have
</p>
<blockquote><p>
<tt>a &lt; b</tt>      contextually convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
as well as for all derived comparison functions, so strictly speaking we could have a random access 
iterator that does not satisfy the <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> requirements, which looks like an
artifact to me.
<p/>
Even if we keep with the existing requirements based on <tt>LessThanComparable</tt> or
<tt>EqualityComparable</tt> we still would have the problem that some current specifications 
are actually  based on the assumption of implicit convertibility instead of "explicit convertibility", e.g. 
<sref ref="[unique.ptr.special]"/> p3:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class T1, class D1, class T2, class D2&gt;
bool operator!=(const unique_ptr&lt;T1, D1&gt;&amp; x, const unique_ptr&lt;T2, D2&gt;&amp; y);
</pre>
<blockquote>
<p>
-3- <i>Returns</i>: <tt>x.get() != y.get()</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
<p>
Similar examples exist in <sref ref="[unique.ptr.single.dtor]"/> p2, <sref ref="[unique.ptr.single.asgn]"/> p9,
<sref ref="[unique.ptr.single.observers]"/> p1+3+8, etc.
<p/>
In all these places the expressions involving comparison functions (but <em>not</em> those of the conversion 
of a <tt>NullablePointer</tt> to <tt>bool</tt>!) assume to be "convertible to <tt>bool</tt>". I think this
is a very natural assumption and all delegations of the comparison functions of some type <tt>X</tt> to some
other API type <tt>Y</tt> in third-party code does so assuming that copy-initialization semantics will
just work.
<p/>
The actual reason for using the newer terminology can be rooted back to LWG <iref ref="556"/>. My hypotheses 
is that the resolution of that issue also needs a slight correction. Why so?
<p/>
The reason for opening that issue were worries based on the previous "convertible to <tt>bool</tt>"
wording. An expressions like "<tt>!pred(a, b)</tt>" might not be well-formed in those situations, because
<tt>operator!</tt> might not be accessible or might have an unusual semantics (and similarly for other logical
operations). This can indeed happen with unusual proxy return types, so the idea was that the evaluation of 
<tt>Predicate</tt>, <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> (<sref ref="[algorithms.general]"/> p8+9), and <tt>Compare</tt> 
(<sref ref="[alg.sorting]"/> p2) should be defined based on contextual conversion to <tt>bool</tt>. 
Unfortunately this <em>alone</em> is not sufficient: In addition, I think, we <em>also</em> want the predicates 
to be (implicitly) convertible to <tt>bool</tt>! Without this wording, several conditions are plain wrong, 
e.g. <sref ref="[alg.find]"/> p2, which talks about "<tt>pred(*i) != false</tt>" (<tt>find_if</tt>) and 
"<tt>pred(*i) == false</tt>" (<tt>find_if_not</tt>). These expressions are not within a boolean context! 
<p/>
While we could simply fix all these places by proper wording to be considered in a "contextual conversion to
<tt>bool</tt>", I think that this is not the correct solution: Many third-party libraries already refer to
the previous C++03 <tt>Predicate</tt> definition &mdash; it actually predates C++98 and is as old as the 
<a href="http://www.sgi.com/tech/stl/Predicate.html">SGI specification</a>. It seems to be a high price to
pay to switch to direct initialization here instead of fixing a completely different specification problem.
<p/>
A final observation is that we have another definition for a <tt>Predicate</tt> in <sref ref="[thread.req.paramname]"/> p2:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
If a parameter is <tt>Predicate</tt>, <tt>operator()</tt> applied to the actual template argument shall return a value that
is convertible to <tt>bool</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The problem here is not that we have two different definitions of <tt>Predicate</tt> in the standard &mdash; this 
is confusing, but this fact alone is not a defect. The first (minor) problem is that this definition does not properly 
apply to function objects that are function pointers, because <tt>operator()</tt> is not defined in a strict sense. 
But the actually worse second problem is that this wording has the very <tt>same</tt> problem that has originally lead to
LWG <iref ref="556"/>! We only need to look at <sref ref="[thread.condition.condvar]"/> p15 to recognice this:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
while (!pred())
  wait(lock);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
The negation expression here looks very familiar to the example provided in LWG <iref ref="556"/> and is sensitive
to the same "unusual proxy" problem. Changing the <sref ref="[thread.req.paramname]"/> wording to a corresponding
"contextual conversion to <tt>bool</tt>" wouldn't work either, because existing specifications rely on "convertible
to <tt>bool</tt>", e.g. <sref ref="[thread.condition.condvar]"/> p32+33+42 or <sref ref="[thread.condition.condvarany]"/> 
p25+26+32+33.
<p/>
To summarize: I believe that LWG <iref ref="556"/> was not completely resolved. A pessimistic interpretation is,
that even with the current wording based on "contextually convertible to <tt>bool</tt>" the actual problem of that 
issue has <em>not</em> been fixed. What actually needs to be required here is some normative wording that basically
expresses something along the lines of:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The semantics of <em>any</em> contextual conversion to <tt>bool</tt> shall be equivalent to the semantics of 
any implicit conversion to <tt>bool</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
This is still not complete without having concepts, but it seems to be a better approximation. Another way of solving
this issue would be to define a minimum requirements table with equivalent semantics. The proposed wording is a bit
simpler but attempts to express the same thing.
</p>

<note>2012, Kona</note>
<p>
Agree with Daniel that we potentially broke some C++03 user code, accept the changes striking
"contextually" from tables.  Stefan to provide revised wording for section 25, and figure out
changes to section 30.
</p>
<p>
Move to open, and then to Review when updated wording from Stefan is available.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to the FDIS.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Change Table 25 &mdash; "<tt>NullablePointer</tt> requirements" in <sref ref="[nullablepointer.requirements]"/>
as indicated:</p>

<table border="1">
<caption>Table 25 &mdash; <tt>NullablePointer</tt> requirements</caption>
<tr align="center">
<th>Expression</th>
<th>Return type</th>
<th>Operational semantics</th>
</tr> 

<tr>
<td colspan="3" align="center">
<tt>[&hellip;]</tt>
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a != b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>!(a == b)</tt>
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a == np<br/>
np == a</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>a == P()</tt>
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a != np<br/>
np != a</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>!(a == np)</tt>
</td>
</tr>

</table>
 
</li>

<li><p>Change Table 107 &mdash; "Input iterator requirements" in <sref ref="[input.iterators]"/>
as indicated:</p>

<table border="1">
<caption>Table 107 &mdash; Input iterator requirements (in addition to Iterator)</caption>
<tr align="center">
<th>Expression</th>
<th>Return type</th>
<th>Operational semantics</th>
<th>Assertion&#47;note<br/>pre-&#47;post-condition</th>
</tr> 

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a != b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>!(a == b)</tt>
</td>
<td>
pre: <tt>(a, b)</tt> is in the domain of <tt>==</tt>.
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td colspan="4" align="center">
<tt>[&hellip;]</tt>
</td>
</tr>

</table>
 
</li>

<li><p>Change Table 111 &mdash; "Random access iterator requirements" in <sref ref="[random.access.iterators]"/>
as indicated:</p>

<table border="1">
<caption>Table 111 &mdash; Random access iterator requirements (in addition to bidirectional iterator)</caption>
<tr align="center">
<th>Expression</th>
<th>Return type</th>
<th>Operational semantics</th>
<th>Assertion&#47;note<br/>pre-&#47;post-condition</th>
</tr> 

<tr>
<td colspan="4" align="center">
<tt>[&hellip;]</tt>
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a &lt; b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>b - a &gt; 0</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>&lt;</tt> is a total ordering relation
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a &gt; b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>b &lt; a</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>&gt;</tt> is a total ordering relation opposite to <tt>&lt;</tt>.
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a &gt;= b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>!(a &lt; b)</tt>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>
<tt>a &lt;= b</tt>
</td>
<td>
<del>contextually</del> convertible to <tt>bool</tt>
</td>
<td>
<tt>!(a &gt; b)</tt>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>

</table>
 
</li>

<li><p>Change <sref ref="[algorithms.general]"/> p8+9 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-8- The <tt>Predicate</tt> parameter is used whenever an algorithm expects a function object 
(<sref ref="[function.objects]"/>) that, when applied to the result of dereferencing the corresponding iterator, 
returns a value testable as <tt>true</tt>. In other words, if an algorithm takes <tt>Predicate pred</tt> 
as its argument and first as its iterator argument, it should work correctly in the construct 
<tt>pred(*first)</tt> <ins>implicitly or</ins> contextually converted to <tt>bool</tt> (Clause <sref ref="[conv]"/>). 
The function object <tt>pred</tt> shall not apply any non-constant function through the dereferenced iterator.
<p/>
-9- The <tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> parameter is used whenever an algorithm expects a function object that when applied
to the result of dereferencing two corresponding iterators or to dereferencing an iterator and type
<tt>T</tt> when <tt>T</tt> is part of the signature returns a value testable as <tt>true</tt>. In other words, if an algorithm takes
<tt>BinaryPredicate binary_pred</tt> as its argument and <tt>first1</tt> and <tt>first2</tt> as its iterator arguments, it should
work correctly in the construct <tt>binary_pred(*first1, *first2)</tt> <ins>implicitly or</ins> contextually converted to 
<tt>bool</tt> (Clause <sref ref="[conv]"/>).
<tt>BinaryPredicate</tt> always takes the first iterator's <tt>value_type</tt> as its first argument, that is, in those cases
when <tt>T</tt> value is part of the signature, it should work correctly in the construct <tt>binary_pred(*first1, value)</tt> 
<ins>implicitly or</ins> contextually converted to <tt>bool</tt> (Clause <sref ref="[conv]"/>). <tt>binary_pred</tt> shall 
not apply any non-constant function through the dereferenced iterators.
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Change <sref ref="[alg.sorting]"/> p2 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-2- <tt>Compare</tt> is a function object type (<sref ref="[function.objects]"/>). The return value of the function 
call operation applied to an object of type <tt>Compare</tt>, when <ins>implicitly or</ins> contextually converted 
to <tt>bool</tt> (<sref ref="[conv]"/>), yields <tt>true</tt> if the first argument of the call is less than the second, and 
<tt>false</tt> otherwise. <tt>Compare comp</tt> is used throughout for algorithms assuming an ordering relation. It is assumed 
that <tt>comp</tt> will not apply any non-constant function through the dereferenced iterator.
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Change <sref ref="[thread.req.paramname]"/> p2 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-2- <del>If a parameter is <tt>Predicate</tt>, operator() applied to the actual template argument shall return a value that
is convertible to <tt>bool</tt></del><ins><tt>Predicate</tt> is a function object type (<sref ref="[function.objects]"/>).
The return value of the function call operation applied to an object of type <tt>Predicate</tt>, when implicitly or 
contextually converted to <tt>bool</tt> (<sref ref="[conv]"/>), yields <tt>true</tt> if the corresponding test condition is
satisfied, and <tt>false</tt> otherwise</ins>.
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
