<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="461" status="CD1">
<title>time_get hard or impossible to implement</title>
<section><sref ref="[locale.time.get.virtuals]"/></section>
<submitter>Bill Plauger</submitter>
<date>23 Mar 2004</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Template time_get currently contains difficult, if not impossible,
requirements for do_date_order, do_get_time, and do_get_date. All require
the implementation to scan a field generated by the %x or %X conversion
specifier in strftime. Yes, do_date_order can always return no_order, but
that doesn't help the other functions. The problem is that %x can be
nearly anything, and it can vary widely with locales. It's horribly
onerous to have to parse "third sunday after Michaelmas in the year of
our Lord two thousand and three," but that's what we currently ask of
do_get_date. More practically, it leads some people to think that if
%x produces 10.2.04, we should know to look for dots as separators. Still
not easy.
</p>

<p>
Note that this is the <i>opposite</i> effect from the intent stated in the
footnote earlier in this subclause:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
"In other words, user confirmation is required for reliable parsing of
user-entered dates and times, but machine-generated formats can be
parsed reliably. This allows parsers to be aggressive about interpreting
user variations on standard formats."
</p></blockquote>

<p>
We should give both implementers and users an easier and more reliable
alternative: provide a (short) list of alternative delimiters and say
what the default date order is for no_order. For backward compatibility,
and maximum latitude, we can permit an implementation to parse whatever
%x or %X generates, but we shouldn't require it.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>

<p><b>In the description:</b></p>
<pre>
iter_type do_get_time(iter_type s, iter_type end, ios_base&amp; str,
        ios_base::iostate&amp; err, tm* t) const;
</pre>

<p>
2 Effects: Reads characters starting at suntil it has extracted those
struct tm members, and remaining format characters, used by
time_put&lt;&gt;::put to produce the format specified by 'X', or until it
encounters an error or end of sequence.
</p>

<p><b>change:</b> 'X'</p>

<p><b>to:</b> "%H:%M:%S"</p>


<p>Change</p>
<pre>
iter_type do_get_date(iter_type s, iter_type end, ios_base&amp; str,
        ios_base::iostate&amp; err, tm* t) const;

4 Effects: Reads characters starting at s until it has extracted those
struct tm members, and remaining format characters, used by
time_put&lt;>::put to produce the format specified by 'x', or until it
encounters an error.
</pre>

<p>to</p>
<pre>
iter_type do_get_date(iter_type s, iter_type end, ios_base&amp; str,
        ios_base::iostate&amp; err, tm* t) const;
</pre>

<p>
4 Effects: Reads characters starting at s until it has extracted those
struct tm members, and remaining format characters, used by
time_put&lt;>::put to produce one of the following formats, or until it
encounters an error. The format depends on the value returned by
date_order() as follows:
</p>

<pre>
        date_order()  format

        no_order      "%m/%d/%y"
        dmy           "%d/%m/%y"
        mdy           "%m/%d/%y"
        ymd           "%y/%m/%d"
        ydm           "%y/%d/%m"
</pre>
<p>
An implementation may also accept additional implementation-defined formats.
</p>

<note>Redmond: agreed that this is a real problem.  The solution is
  probably to match C99's parsing rules.  Bill provided wording.
</note>

</resolution>

</issue>
