<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2120" status="WP">
<title>What should <tt>async</tt> do if neither '<tt>async</tt>' nor '<tt>deferred</tt>' is set in policy?</title>
<section><sref ref="[futures.async]"/></section>
<submitter>Jonathan Wakely</submitter>
<date>1 Jan 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
Implementations already disagree, one returns an invalid future with
no shared state, one chooses <tt>policy == async</tt> and one chooses <tt>policy ==
deferred</tt>, see c++std-lib-30839, c++std-lib-30840 and c++std-lib-30844.
It's not clear if returning an invalid future is allowed by the current wording.
</p>
<p>
If the intention is to allow an empty future to be returned, then
<sref ref="[futures.async]"/> p3 and p4 should be adjusted to clarify that a
shared state might not be created and an invalid future might be returned.
</p>
<p>
If the intention is that a valid future is always returned, p3 should
say something about the case where none of the conditions applies.
</p>

<note>2012, Portland: move to Review</note>
<p>
We could make it undefined if no launch policy is defined.
</p>
<p>
Hans: If no launch policy is specified the behaviour is undefined
</p>
<p>
Artur: or implementation defined?
</p>
<p>
Hans: no: we don't want people to do this
</p>
<note>Proposed wording</note>
<p>
This wording is relative to N3376
</p>
<p>
Add a third bullet to the end of the list in 30.6.8p3
</p>
<blockquote>
"if no valid launch policy is provided the behaviour is undefined"
</blockquote>
<p>
Moved to review
</p>

<note>2013-04-19, Bristol</note> 

<p>Detlef provides new wording</p>

<p>Previous wording:</p>

<blockquote class="note">  
<note>This wording is relative to N3376</note>
<p>
Add a third bullet to the end of the list in <sref ref="[futures.async]"/>p3
</p>
<blockquote>
<ins>&ndash; if no valid launch policy is provided the behaviour is undefined</ins>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<note>2013-09 Chicago</note>
<p>
If no policy is given, it should be undefined, so moved to Immediate.
</p>
<p>
Accept for Working Paper
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<note>This wording is relative to N3485</note>
<p>
Add a third bullet to the end of the list in <sref ref="[futures.async]"/>p3
</p>
<blockquote>
<ins>&ndash; If no value is set in the launch policy, or a value is set that is
neither specified in this International Standard or by the implementation, the behaviour 
is undefined.</ins>
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
