<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2086" status="Pending WP">
<title>Overly generic type support for math functions</title>
<section><sref ref="[c.math]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>22 Sep 2011</date>

<discussion>

<p>
<sref ref="[c.math]"/> ends with a description of a rule set for "sufficient overloads"
in p11:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Moreover, there shall be additional overloads sufficient to ensure:</p>
<ol>
<li>
If any argument corresponding to a <tt>double</tt> parameter has type <tt>long double</tt>, then all arguments
corresponding to <tt>double</tt> parameters are effectively cast to <tt>long double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, if any argument corresponding to a <tt>double</tt> parameter has type <tt>double</tt> or an integer type,
then all arguments corresponding to <tt>double</tt> parameters are effectively cast to <tt>double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, all arguments corresponding to <tt>double</tt> parameters are effectively cast to <tt>float</tt>.
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>
My impression is that this rule set is probably more generic as intended, my assumption is that it is written 
to mimic the C99&#47;C1x rule set in 7.25 p2+3 in the "C++" way:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-2- Of the <tt>&lt;math.h&gt;</tt> and <tt>&lt;complex.h&gt;</tt> functions without an 
<tt>f</tt> (<tt>float</tt>) or <tt>l</tt> (<tt>long double</tt>) suffix, several have 
one or more parameters whose corresponding real type is <tt>double</tt>. For each such 
function, except <tt>modf</tt>, there is a corresponding type-generic macro. (footnote 313) 
The parameters whose corresponding real type is <tt>double</tt> in the function
synopsis are generic parameters. Use of the macro invokes a function whose
corresponding real type and type domain are determined by the arguments for the generic
parameters. (footnote 314)
<p/>
-3- Use of the macro invokes a function whose generic parameters have the corresponding 
real type determined as follows:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
First, if any argument for generic parameters has type <tt>long double</tt>, the type
determined is <tt>long double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, if any argument for generic parameters has type <tt>double</tt> or is of integer
type, the type determined is <tt>double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, the type determined is <tt>float</tt>.
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>
where footnote 314 clarifies the intent:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
If the type of the argument is not compatible with the type of the parameter for the selected function,
the behavior is undefined.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
The combination of the usage of the unspecific term "cast" with otherwise no further constraints 
(note that C constraints the valid set to types that C++ describes as arithmetic types, but see below 
for one important difference) has the effect that it requires the following examples to be well-formed 
and well-defined:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;cmath&gt;

enum class Ec { };

struct S { explicit operator long double(); };

void test(Ec e, S s) {
 std::sqrt(e); // OK, behaves like std::sqrt((float) e);
 std::sqrt(s); // OK, behaves like std::sqrt((float) s);
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
GCC 4.7 does not accept any of these examples.
<p/>
I found another example where the C++ rule differs from the C set, 
but in this case I'm not so sure, which direction C++ should follow. 
The difference is located in the fact, that in C enumerated types are 
<em>integer types</em> as described in 6.2.5 p17 (see e.g. n1569 or n1256):
<p/>
"The type char, the signed and unsigned integer types, and
the enumerated types are collectively called integer types. The
integer and real floating types are collectively called real types."
<p/>
This indicates that in C the following code
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;math.h&gt;

enum E { e };

void test(void) {
  sqrt(e); // OK, behaves like sqrt((double) e);
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
seems to be well-defined and <tt>e</tt> is cast to <tt>double</tt>, but in C++
referring to
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
#include &lt;cmath&gt;

enum E { e };

void test() {
  std::sqrt(e); // OK, behaves like sqrt((float) e);
}
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
is also well-defined (because of our lack of constraints) but we
must skip bullet 2 (because E is not an integer type) and effectively
cast <tt>e</tt> to <tt>float</tt>. Accepting this, we would introduce 
a silent, but observable runtime difference for C and C++.
<p/>
GCC 4.7 does not accept this example, but causes an ambiguity
error among the three floating point overloads of sqrt.
<p/>
My current suggestion to fix these problems would be to constrain the 
valid argument types of these functions to arithmetic types.
</p>

<blockquote><p>
Howard provided wording to solve the issue.
</p></blockquote>

<note>2012, Kona</note>
<p>
Moved to Ready.  The proposed wording reflects both original intent from
TR1, and current implementations.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to the FDIS.</p>

<p>Change <sref ref="[c.math]"/> p11 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Moreover, there shall be additional overloads sufficient to ensure:</p>
<ol>
<li>
If any <ins>arithmetic</ins> argument corresponding to a <tt>double</tt> parameter has 
type <tt>long double</tt>, then all <ins>arithmetic</ins> arguments corresponding to 
<tt>double</tt> parameters are effectively cast to <tt>long double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, if any <ins>arithmetic</ins> argument corresponding to a <tt>double</tt> 
parameter has type <tt>double</tt> or an integer type, then all <ins>arithmetic</ins> 
arguments corresponding to <tt>double</tt> parameters are effectively cast to <tt>double</tt>.
</li>
<li>
Otherwise, all <ins>arithmetic</ins> arguments corresponding to <tt>double</tt> parameters 
<del>are effectively cast to</del><ins>have type</ins> <tt>float</tt>.
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
