<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="617" status="NAD">
<title><tt>std::array</tt> is a sequence that doesn't satisfy the sequence requirements?</title>
<section><sref ref="[array]"/></section>
<submitter>Bo Persson</submitter>
<date>30 Dec 2006</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The <tt>&lt;array&gt;</tt> header is given under <sref ref="[sequences]"/>.
<sref ref="[array]"/>/paragraph 3 says:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"Unless otherwise specified, all array operations are as described in
<sref ref="[container.requirements]"/>".
</p></blockquote>
<p>
However, <tt>array</tt> isn't mentioned at all in section <sref ref="[container.requirements]"/>.
In particular, Table 82 "Sequence requirements" lists several operations (insert, erase, clear) 
that <tt>std::array</tt> does not have in <sref ref="[array]"/>.
</p>
<p>
Also, Table 83 "Optional sequence operations" lists several operations that 
<tt>std::array</tt> does have, but array isn't mentioned.
</p>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
The real issue seems to be different than what is described here.
Non-normative text says that <tt>std::array</tt> is a sequence container, but
there is disagreement about what that really means. There are two
possible interpretations:
</p>
<ol>
<li>
a sequence container is one that satisfies all sequence container requirements
</li>
<li>
a sequence container is one that satisfies some of the sequence
container requirements. Any operation that the container supports is
specified by one or more sequence container requirements, unless that
operation is specifically singled out and defined alongside the
description of the container itself.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
Move to Tentatively NAD.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07-15 Lo&iuml;c Joly adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
The section <sref ref="[sequence.reqmts]"/>/1 states that array is a sequence. <sref ref="[sequence.reqmts]"/>/3
introduces table 83, named Sequence container requirements. This seems
to me to be defining the requirements for all sequences. However, array
does not follow all of this requirements (this can be read in the array
specific section, for the standard is currently inconsistent).
</p>

<p>
Proposed resolution 1 (minimal change): 
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
Say that array is a container, that in addition follows only some of the
sequence requirements, as described in the array section:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
The library provides <del>five</del> <ins>three</ins> basic kinds of sequence containers: <del><tt>array</tt></del>,
<tt>vector</tt>, 
<del><tt>forward_list</tt></del>, <tt>list</tt>, and <tt>deque</tt>. <ins>In addition, <tt>array</tt>
and <tt>forward_list</tt> follows some of the requirements 
of sequences, as described in their respective sections.</ins>
</p></blockquote>

</blockquote>

<p>
Proposed resolution 2 (most descriptive description, no full wording provided): 
</p>
<blockquote><p>
Introduce the notion of a Fixed Size Sequence, with it requirement table
that would be a subset of the current Sequence container. array would be
the only Fixed Size Sequence (but dynarray is in the queue for TR2).
Sequence requirements would now be requirements in addition to Fixed
Size Sequence requirements (it is currently in addition to container).
</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
Move to NAD Editorial
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2009 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
This will require a lot of reorganization. Editor doesn't think this is really
an issue, since the description of array can be considered as overriding
what's specified about sequences. Move to NAD.
</p></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
