<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="247" status="CD1">
<title><tt>vector</tt>, <tt>deque::insert</tt> complexity</title>
<section><sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/></section>
<submitter>Lisa Lippincott</submitter>
<date>06 Jun 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>Paragraph 2 of <sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/> describes the complexity
of <tt>vector::insert</tt>:</p>

   <blockquote><p>
   Complexity: If first and last are forward iterators, bidirectional
   iterators, or random access iterators, the complexity is linear in
   the number of elements in the range [first, last) plus the distance
   to the end of the vector. If they are input iterators, the complexity
   is proportional to the number of elements in the range [first, last)
   times the distance to the end of the vector.
   </p></blockquote>

<p>First, this fails to address the non-iterator forms of
<tt>insert</tt>.</p>

<p>Second, the complexity for input iterators misses an edge case --
it requires that an arbitrary number of elements can be added at
the end of a <tt>vector</tt> in constant time.</p>

<p>I looked to see if <tt>deque</tt> had a similar problem, and was
surprised to find that <tt>deque</tt> places no requirement on the
complexity of inserting multiple elements (<sref ref="[deque.modifiers]"/>,
paragraph 3):</p>

   <blockquote><p>
   Complexity: In the worst case, inserting a single element into a
   deque takes time linear in the minimum of the distance from the
   insertion point to the beginning of the deque and the distance
   from the insertion point to the end of the deque. Inserting a
   single element either at the beginning or end of a deque always
   takes constant time and causes a single call to the copy constructor
   of T.
   </p></blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>Change Paragraph 2 of <sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/> to</p>
   <blockquote><p>
   Complexity: The complexity is linear in the number of elements 
   inserted plus the distance to the end of the vector.
   </p></blockquote>

   <note>For input iterators, one may achieve this complexity by first
   inserting at the end of the <tt>vector</tt>, and then using
   <tt>rotate</tt>.</note>

<p>Change <sref ref="[deque.modifiers]"/>, paragraph 3, to:</p>

   <blockquote><p>
   Complexity: The complexity is linear in the number of elements 
   inserted plus the shorter of the distances to the beginning and
   end of the deque.  Inserting a single element at either the
   beginning or the end of a deque causes a single call to the copy
   constructor of T.
   </p></blockquote>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>This is a real defect, and proposed resolution fixes it: some
  complexities aren't specified that should be.  This proposed
  resolution does constrain deque implementations (it rules out the
  most naive possible implementations), but the LWG doesn't see a
  reason to permit that implementation.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
