<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2130" status="New">
<title>Missing ordering constraints</title>
<section><sref ref="[atomics.order]"/></section>
<submitter>Mark Batty</submitter>
<date>22 Feb 2012</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>C11 issue 407</b></p>

<p>
It seems that both C11 and C++11 are missing the following two derivatives of this 
rule:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
  For atomic modifications <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> of an atomic object <tt>M</tt>, if there is
  a <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fence <tt>X</tt> such that <tt>A</tt> is sequenced before <tt>X</tt>,
  and <tt>X</tt> precedes <tt>B</tt> in <tt>S</tt>, then <tt>B</tt> occurs later than <tt>A</tt> in the
  modification order of <tt>M</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>
  For atomic modifications <tt>A</tt> and <tt>B</tt> of an atomic object <tt>M</tt>, if there is
  a <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fence <tt>Y</tt> such that <tt>Y</tt> is sequenced before <tt>B</tt>,
  and <tt>A</tt> precedes <tt>Y</tt> in <tt>S</tt>, then <tt>B</tt> occurs later than <tt>A</tt> in the
  modification order of <tt>M</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Above wording has been suggested for the Technical Corrigendum of C11 via issue 407, details can be found 
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg14/www/docs/n1584.pdf">here</a>.
</p>

<note>2012-03-19: Daniel proposes a slightly condensed form to reduce wording duplications</note>

<note>2012-03-20: Hans comments</note>
<p>
The usage of the term <em>atomic operations</em> in <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> p7 is actually
incorrect and should better be replaced by <em>atomic modifications</em> as used in the C11
407 wording.
<p/>
There seems to be a similar wording incorrectness used in <sref ref="[intro.multithread]"/> p17
which should be corrected as well.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3376.</p>

<ol>
<li><p><em>[Drafting note: The project editor is kindly asked to consider to replace in <sref ref="[intro.multithread]"/> p17
the phrase <em>"before an operation <i>B</i> on <i>M</i>"</em> by <em>"before a modification <i>B</i> of <i>M</i>"</em>.]</em></p>
</li>
<li><p>Change <sref ref="[atomics.order]"/> paragraph 7 as indicated: <em>[Drafting note: Note that the
wording change intentionally does also replace the term <em>atomic operation</em> by <em>atomic modification</em>]</em>
</p>

<p>
-7- <del>For atomic operations <i>A</i> and <i>B</i> on an atomic object <i>M</i>, if there are 
<tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences <i>X</i> and <i>Y</i> such that <i>A</i> is sequenced before <i>X</i>, 
<i>Y</i> is sequenced before <i>B</i>, and <i>X</i> precedes <i>Y</i> in <i>S</i>, then <i>B</i> 
occurs later than <i>A</i> in the modification order of <i>M</i>.</del>
<ins>For atomic modifications <i>A</i> and <i>B</i> of an atomic object <i>M</i>, <i>B</i> occurs
later than <i>A</i> in the modification order of <i>M</i> if:</ins>
<ul>
<li><ins>there is a <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fence <i>X</i> such that <i>A</i> is sequenced before <i>X</i>, 
and <i>X</i> precedes <i>B</i> in <i>S</i>, or</ins>
</li>
<li><ins>there is a <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fence <i>Y</i> such that <i>Y</i> is sequenced before <i>B</i>,
and <i>A</i> precedes <i>Y</i> in <i>S</i>, or</ins>
</li>
<li><ins>there are <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences <i>X</i> and <i>Y</i> such that <i>A</i> is sequenced 
before <i>X</i>, <i>Y</i> is sequenced before <i>B</i>, and <i>X</i> precedes <i>Y</i> in <i>S</i>.</ins>
</li>
</ul>
<p/>
-8- [ <i>Note</i>: <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> ensures sequential consistency only for a program that is free of data races
and uses exclusively <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> operations. Any use of weaker ordering will invalidate this
guarantee unless extreme care is used. In particular, <tt>memory_order_seq_cst</tt> fences ensure a total order
only for the fences themselves. Fences cannot, in general, be used to restore sequential consistency for atomic
operations with weaker ordering specifications. &mdash; <i>end note</i> ]
</p>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
