<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1369" status="NAD">
<title>[FCD] <tt>rethrow_exception</tt> may introduce data races</title>
<section><sref ref="[propagation]"/></section>
<submitter>BSI</submitter>
<date>25 Aug 2010</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses GB-74</b></p>
<p>
One idea for the <tt>exception_ptr</tt> type was that a reference-counted
implementation could simply 'reactivate' the same
exception object in the context of a call to
<tt>rethrow_exception</tt>. Such an implementation would allow
the same exception object to be active in multiple threads
(such as when multiple threads join on a <tt>shared_future</tt>)
and introduce potential data races in any exception
handler that catches exceptions by reference - notably
existing library code written before this capability was
added. <tt>rethrow_exception</tt> should <em>always</em> make a copy
of the target exception object.
</p>

<note>Resolution suggested by NB comment</note>

<p>
Add the following to 18.8.5, [propogation]
</p>
<blockquote><p><ins>
<i>Throws</i>: a copy of the exception object to which <tt>p</tt> refers.
</ins></p></blockquote>

<note>2011-03-15: Anthony drafts wording</note>

<note>2011-03-23 Madrid meeting</note>

<p>No consensus for a change</p>

</discussion>

<rationale><p>It would break too many existing implementations</p></rationale>

<resolution>

<ol>
<li><p>Alter <sref ref="[except.throw]"/> p. 5 as follows:</p>

<blockquote><p>
5 When the thrown object is a class object, the copy/move constructor and the destructor shall be accessible,
even if the copy/move operation is elided (<sref ref="[class.copy]"/>). <ins>The copy constructor shall be
accessible, and is odr-used (<sref ref="[basic.def.odr]"/>), even if the copy operation is elided, 
or a move constructor used to construct the exception object.</ins>
</p></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Alter <sref ref="[propagation]"/> p. 7 as follows:</p>

<blockquote><pre>
exception_ptr current_exception() noexcept;
</pre><blockquote>
<p>
7 <i>Returns</i>: An <tt>exception_ptr</tt> object that refers to <del>the currently handled exception 
(<sref ref="[except.handle]"/>) or</del> a copy of the currently handled exception, or a null <tt>exception_ptr</tt> 
object if no exception is being handled. The referenced object shall remain valid at least as long as there 
is an <tt>exception_ptr</tt> object that refers to it. If the function needs to allocate memory and the 
attempt fails, it returns an <tt>exception_ptr</tt> object that refers to an instance of <tt>bad_alloc</tt>. 
It is unspecified whether the return values of two successive calls to <tt>current_exception</tt> refer to 
the same exception object. [ <i>Note</i>: That is, it is unspecified whether <tt>current_exception</tt> 
creates a new copy each time it is called. &mdash; <i>end note</i> ] If the attempt to copy the current 
exception object throws an exception,<ins> or is otherwise not possible,</ins> the function returns an 
<tt>exception_ptr</tt> object that refers to the thrown exception <ins>if any</ins> or, <del>if this is not possible,</del> 
to an instance of <tt>bad_exception</tt>. [ <i>Note</i>: The copy constructor of the thrown exception 
may also fail, so the implementation is allowed to substitute a <tt>bad_exception</tt> object to avoid 
infinite recursion. &mdash; <i>end note</i> ]
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Alter <sref ref="[propagation]"/> p. 9 and add a new paragraph after p. 9 as follows:</p>

<blockquote><pre>
[[noreturn]] void rethrow_exception(exception_ptr p);
</pre><blockquote>
<p>
8 <i>Requires</i>: <tt>p</tt> shall not be a null pointer.
<p/>
9 <i>Throws</i>: <ins>a copy of</ins> the exception object to which <tt>p</tt> refers<ins>, or any exception 
thrown by the attempt to copy the exception object to which <tt>p</tt> refers</ins>.
<p/>
<ins>? <i>Synchronization</i>: Calls to <tt>rethrow_exception</tt> on <tt>exception_ptr</tt> objects
that refer to the same exception object shall appear to occur in a single total order. The completion 
of each call shall synchronize with (<sref ref="[intro.multithread]"/>) the next call in that total order.</ins>
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
</li>
</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
