<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2336" status="New">
<title><tt>is_trivially_constructible/is_trivially_assignable</tt> traits are always false</title>
<section><sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>1 Oct 2013</date>

<discussion>
<p>
In <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/> we have traits to allow testing for triviality of specific operations, such as
<tt>is_trivially_constructible</tt> and <tt>is_trivially_assignable</tt> (and their derived forms), which are specified
in terms of the following initialization and assignment, respectively:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
T t(create&lt;Args&gt;()...);

declval&lt;T&gt;() = declval&lt;U&gt;()
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
The wording that describes the way how triviality is deduced, is in both cases of the same form:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[&hellip; ] and the variable definition/assignment, as defined by <tt>is_constructible/is_assignable</tt>, is known
to call no operation that is not trivial (3.9, 12).
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The problematic part of this wording is that both definitions are specified in terms of an "object construction" function
<tt>create</tt> or <tt>declval</tt>, respectively, (The former being a conceptual function, the latter being a library function), 
but for none of these functions we can assume that they could be considered as trivial &mdash; only special member functions can 
have this property and none of these is one. This problem became obvious, when the similar issue LWG <iref ref="2298"/> 
in regard to <tt>is_nothrow_constructible</tt> was opened.
<p/>
A possible approach to solve this specification problem is to make a blanket statement for sub-clause <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/>
that these helper functions are considered trivial for the purpose of defining these traits.
<p/>
Using this kind of wording technique can also be used to get rid of the additional helper function template <tt>create</tt>, which
is currently needed for the <tt>is_convertible</tt> and the <tt>is_constructible</tt> traits, because both traits are specified in
terms of contexts where technically the corresponding "object construction" function would be considered as odr-used. This is problematic,
because these traits are defined in terms of well-formed code and odr-using <tt>declval</tt> would make the program ill-formed (see
<sref ref="[declval]"/>). So extending above blanket statement to consider <tt>std::declval&lt;T&gt;()</tt> as not odr-used
in the context of the corresponding trait definition would allow for replacing <tt>create</tt> by <tt>declval</tt>.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3691.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Add a new paragraph after <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/> p3 as indicated: <em>[Editorial note: The first change in
<sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/> p3 is recommended, because technically a Clause is always a "main chapter" &mdash; such as
Clause 20 &mdash; but every child of a Clause or sub-clause is a sub-clause]</em></p>

<blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
-3- For all of the class templates <tt>X</tt> declared in this <del>Clause</del><ins>sub-clause</ins>, instantiating that 
template with a template-argument that is a class template specialization may result in the implicit instantiation of the 
template argument if and only if the semantics of <tt>X</tt> require that the argument must be a complete type.
<p/>
<ins>-?- For the purpose of defining the templates in this sub-clause, a function call expression 
<tt>declval&lt;T&gt;()</tt> for any type <tt>T</tt> is considered to be a trivial (<sref ref="[basic.types]"/>, <sref ref="[special]"/>) 
function call that is not an odr-use (<sref ref="[basic.def.odr]"/>) of <tt>declval</tt> in the context of the corresponding definition 
notwithstanding the restrictions of <sref ref="[declval]"/>.</ins>
<p/>
[&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/> p6 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-6- <del>Given the following function prototype:</del>
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
<del>template &lt;class T&gt;
  typename add_rvalue_reference&lt;T&gt;::type create();</del>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
<del>t</del><ins>T</ins>he predicate condition for a template specialization <tt>is_constructible&lt;T, Args...&gt;</tt> 
shall be satisfied if and only if the following variable definition would be well-formed for some invented variable <tt>t</tt>:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
T t(<del>create</del><ins>declval</ins>&lt;Args&gt;()...);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Add a new paragraph after <sref ref="[meta.rel]"/> p2 as indicated: <em>[Editorial note: Technically we don't need
the guarantee of "a trivial function call" for the type relationship predicates at the very moment, but it seems more robust and
consistent to have the exact same guarantee here as well]</em>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
<p/>
-2- [&hellip;]
<p/>
<ins>-?- For the purpose of defining the templates in this sub-clause, a function call expression 
<tt>declval&lt;T&gt;()</tt> for any type <tt>T</tt> is considered to be a trivial (<sref ref="[basic.types]"/>, <sref ref="[special]"/>) 
function call that is not an odr-use (<sref ref="[basic.def.odr]"/>) of <tt>declval</tt> in the context of the corresponding definition 
notwithstanding the restrictions of <sref ref="[declval]"/>.</ins>
<p/>
[&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[meta.rel]"/> p4 as indicated:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
-4- <del>Given the following function prototype:</del>
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
<del>template &lt;class T&gt;
  typename add_rvalue_reference&lt;T&gt;::type create();</del>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
<del>t</del><ins>T</ins>he predicate condition for a template specialization <tt>is_convertible&lt;From, To&gt;</tt> 
shall be satisfied if and only if the return expression in the following code would be well-formed, including any implicit 
conversions to the return type of the function:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
To test() {
  return <del>create</del><ins>declval</ins>&lt;From&gt;();
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
[&hellip;]
</p>
</blockquote>
</li>

</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
