<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="653" status="NAD">
<title>Library reserved names</title>
<section><sref ref="[intro.refs]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>8 Mar 2007</date>

<discussion>
<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
<sref ref="[intro.refs]"/> Normative references
</p>

<p>
The following standards contain provisions which, through reference in
this text, constitute provisions of this Interna- tional Standard. At
the time of publication, the editions indicated were valid. All
standards are subject to revision, and parties to agreements based on
this International Standard are encouraged to investigate the
possibility of applying the most recent editions of the standards
indicated below. Members of IEC and ISO maintain registers of currently
valid International Standards.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Ecma International, ECMAScript Language Specification, Standard
Ecma-262, third edition, 1999.</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 2382 (all parts), Information technology - Vocabulary</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9899:1990, Programming languages - C</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9899/Amd.1:1995, Programming languages - C, AMENDMENT 1: C
Integrity</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9899:1999, Programming languages - C</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9899:1999/Cor.1:2001 Programming languages - C</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9899:1999/Cor.2:2004 Programming languages - C</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 9945:2003, Information Technology-Portable Operating System
Interface (POSIX)</li>
<li>ISO/IEC 10646-1:1993 Information technology - Universal Multiple-Octet
Coded Character Set (UCS) - Part 1: Architecture and Basic Multilingual
Plane</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>
I'm not sure how many of those reserve naming patterns that might affect
us, but I am equally sure I don't own a copy of any of these to check!
</p>
<p>
The point is to list the reserved naming patterns, rather than the
individual names themselves - although we may want to list C keywords
that are valid identifiers in C++ but likely to cause trouble in shared
headers (e.g. restrict)
</p>

<note>
Kona (2007): Recommend NAD.  No one has identified a specific defect, just the possibility of one.
</note>

<note>
Post-Kona: Alisdair request Open. A good example of the problem was a
discussion of the system error proposal, where it was pointed out an all-caps
identifier starting with a capital E conflicted with reserved macro names for
both Posix and C.  I had absolutely no idea of this rule, and suspect I was
not the only one in the room.<br/>
<br/>
Resolution will require someone with access to all the listed documents to
research their respective name reservation rules, or people with access to
specific documents add their rules to this issue until the list is complete.
</note>

<note>
Bellevue: Wording is aleady present in various standards, and no-one has come forward with wording.
Suggest a formal paper rather than a defect report is the correct way to proceed.
</note>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
