<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="731" status="NAD">
<title>proposal for a customizable <tt>seed_seq</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[rand.util.seedseq]"/></section>
<submitter>Stephan Tolksdorf</submitter>
<date>21 Sep 2007</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The proper way to seed random number engines seems to be the most frequently 
discussed issue of the <sref ref="[rand]"/> proposal. While the new <tt>seed_seq</tt> approach is already rather 
general and probably sufficient for most situations, it is unlikely to be optimal in every case (one 
problem was pointed out in point T5 above). In some situations it might, for instance, be better to 
seed the state with a cryptographic generator. 
</p>
<p>
In my opinion this is a pretty strong argument for extending the standard with a simple facility to 
customize the seeding procedure. This could, for example, be done with the following minimal 
changes:
</p>

<p>
<b>Possible resolution:</b>
</p>

<ol style="list-style-type:lower-alpha">
<li>
Turn the interface specification of <sref ref="[rand.util.seedseq]"/>/2 into a "SeedSeq" requirement, where the 
exact behaviour of the constructors and the randomize method are left unspecified and where the
const qualification for randomize is removed. Classes implementing this interface are additionally 
required to specialize the traits class in c).
</li>
<li>
Provide the class <tt>seed_seq</tt> as a default implementation of the SeedSeq interface.
</li>
<li>
<p>
Supplement the <tt>seed_seq</tt> with a traits class
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;typename T&gt; 
struct is_seed_seq { static const bool value = false; }
</pre></blockquote>
<p>and the specialization</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;&gt; 
struct is_seed_seq&lt;seed_seq&gt; { static const bool value = true; }
</pre></blockquote>
<p>which users can supplement with further specializations.</p>
</li>
<li>
Change <sref ref="[rand.req.eng]"/>/1 d) to "q is an lvalue of a type that fulfils the SeedSeq requirements", and 
modify the constructors and seed methods in <sref ref="[rand.eng]"/> appropriately (the actual implementation 
could be done using the SFINAE technique).
</li>
</ol>

<note>
Bellevue:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
See N2424. Close NAD but note that "conceptizing" the library may cause
this problem to be solved by that route.
</p></blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
See <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2007/n2424.pdf">N2424</a>
for the proposed resolution.
</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
