<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2033" status="Pending WP">
<title>Preconditions of <tt>reserve</tt>, <tt>shrink_to_fit</tt>, and <tt>resize</tt> functions</title>
<section><sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/> <sref ref="[deque.capacity]"/></section>
<submitter>Nikolay Ivchenkov</submitter>
<date>20 Feb 2011</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I have several questions with regard to the working paper N3225 (C++0x working draft):
</p>
<ol>
<li><p>
Where the working draft specifies preconditions for <tt>shrink_to_fit</tt>
member function of <tt>std::vector</tt> and <tt>std::deque</tt>?
</p></li>
<li><p>
Where the working draft specifies preconditions for '<tt>void reserve(size_type n)</tt>' 
member function of <tt>std::vector</tt>?
</p></li>
<li><p>
Does a call to '<tt>void resize(size_type sz)</tt>' of <tt>std::vector</tt> require
the element type to be <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt>? If yes, why such
requirement is not listed in the <i>Requires</i> paragraph?
</p></li>
<li><p>
Does a call to '<tt>void resize(size_type sz)</tt>' of <tt>std::vector</tt> require
the element type to be <tt>MoveAssignable</tt> because the call <tt>erase(begin() + sz, end())</tt> 
mentioned in the <i>Effects</i> paragraph would require the element type to be <tt>MoveAssignable</tt>?
</p></li>
<li><p>
Why <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> requirement is used for '<tt>void resize(size_type sz)</tt>' of <tt>std::vector</tt> 
instead of <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> requirement?
</p></li>
</ol>

<note>2011-06-12: Daniel comments and provides wording</note>
<p>According to my understanding of the mental model of vector (and to some parts for deque) the 
some requirements are missing in the standard as response to above questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>The preconditions of <tt>shrink_to_fit</tt> for both <tt>std::vector</tt> and <tt>std::deque</tt>
should impose the <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> requirements. The reason for this is, that these containers
can host move-only types. For a container type <tt>X</tt> the C++03 idiom <tt>X(*this).swap(*this)</tt>
imposes the <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> requirements which would make the function call ill-formed,
which looks like an unacceptable restriction to me. Assuming the committee decides to support the
move-only case, further wording has to be added for the situation where such a move-only type could
throw an exception, because this can leave the object in an unspecified state. This seems consistent
with the requirements of <tt>reserve</tt>, which seems like a very similar function to me (for
<tt>vector</tt>). And this brings us smoothly to the following bullet:
</li>

<li><p>I agree that we are currently missing to specify the preconditions of the <tt>reserve</tt> function.
My interpretation of the mental model of this function is that it should work for move-only types, which
seems to be supported by the wording used in <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/> p2:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[&hellip;] If an exception is thrown other than by the move constructor of a non-CopyInsertable type, 
there are no effects.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Given this statement, the appropriate requirement is <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into the <tt>vector</tt>.
</p>
</li>

<li>I agree that <tt>vector::resize(size_type)</tt> misses to list the <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt>
requirements.
</li>

<li>Unfortunately the current specification in terms of <tt>erase</tt> implies the <tt>MoveAssignable</tt>
requirements. I don't think that this implication is intended. This function requires "append" and 
"pop-back" effects, respectively, where the former can be realized in terms of <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> 
requirements. The same fix in regard to using <tt>pop_back</tt> instead of <tt>erase</tt> is necessary 
for the two argument overload of <tt>resize</tt> as well (no <tt>MoveAssignable</tt> is required).
</li>

<li>The <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> requirement is incorrect and should be <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> instead.</li>
</ol>

<p>In addition to above mentioned items, the proposed resolution adds a linear complexity bound for 
<tt>shrink_to_fit</tt> and attempts to resolve the related issue <iref ref="2066"/>.</p>

<note>
2011 Bloomington
</note>

<p>
Move to Ready.
</p>

<p>
Note for editor: we do not normally refer to 'linear <i>time</i>' for complexity requirements, but there
is agreement that any clean-up of such wording is editorial.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to the FDIS.</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Edit <sref ref="[deque.capacity]"/> as indicated [Remark: The suggested change of p4 is
not redundant, because <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> is not necessarily a refinement of <tt>MoveInsertable</tt>
in contrast to the fact that <tt>CopyConstructible</tt> is a refinement of <tt>MoveConstructible</tt>]:</p>

<blockquote><pre>
void resize(size_type sz);
</pre><blockquote><p>
-1- <i>Effects</i>: If <tt>sz &lt;= size()</tt>, equivalent to <del><tt>erase(begin() + sz, 
end());</tt></del><ins>calling <tt>pop_back()</tt> <tt>size() - sz</tt> times</ins>. If 
<tt>size() &lt; sz</tt>, appends <tt>sz - size()</tt> value-initialized elements to the sequence.
<p/>
-2- Requires: <tt>T</tt> shall be <ins><tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt> and</ins> <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt>.
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<blockquote><pre>
void resize(size_type sz, const T&amp; c);
</pre><blockquote><p>
-3- <i>Effects</i>: <ins>If <tt>sz &lt;= size()</tt>, equivalent to calling <tt>pop_back()</tt> 
<tt>size() - sz</tt> times. If <tt>size() &lt; sz</tt>, appends <tt>sz - size()</tt> copies of <tt>c</tt> 
to the sequence.</ins>
</p><blockquote><pre>
<del>if (sz &gt; size())
  insert(end(), sz-size(), c);
else if (sz &lt; size())
  erase(begin()+sz, end());
else
  ; <i>// do nothing</i></del>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
-4- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <ins><tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt> and</ins> 
<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt>.
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<blockquote><pre>
void shrink_to_fit();
</pre><blockquote><p>
<ins>-?- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
<ins>-?- <i>Complexity</i>: Takes at most linear time in the size of the sequence.</ins>
<p/>
-5- <i>Remarks</i>: <tt>shrink_to_fit</tt> is a non-binding request to reduce memory use <ins>but does
not change the size of the sequence</ins>. [ <i>Note</i>: The request is non-binding to allow latitude 
for implementation-specific optimizations. &mdash; <i>end note</i> ]
</p></blockquote></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Edit <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/> as indicated including edits that also resolve <iref ref="2066"/> 
[Remark: The combined listing of <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> and <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> before p12 is not redundant, 
because <tt>CopyInsertable</tt> is not necessarily a refinement of <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> in contrast to the 
fact that <tt>CopyConstructible</tt> is a refinement of <tt>MoveConstructible</tt>]:</p>

<p>[&hellip;]</p>

<blockquote><pre>
void reserve(size_type n);
</pre><blockquote><p>
<ins>-?- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
-2- <i>Effects</i>: A directive that informs a vector of a planned change in size, so that it can manage the storage
allocation accordingly. After <tt>reserve()</tt>, <tt>capacity()</tt> is greater or equal to the argument of reserve if
reallocation happens; and equal to the previous value of <tt>capacity()</tt> otherwise. Reallocation happens
at this point if and only if the current capacity is less than the argument of <tt>reserve()</tt>. If an exception
is thrown other than by the move constructor of a non-<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> type, there are no effects.
<p/>
-3- <i>Complexity</i>: It does not change the size of the sequence and takes at most linear time in the size of
the sequence.
<p/>
-4- <i>Throws</i>: <tt>length_error</tt> if <tt>n &gt; max_size()</tt>.[footnote 266]
<p/>
-5- <i>Remarks</i>: Reallocation invalidates all the references, pointers, and iterators referring to the elements
in the sequence. It is guaranteed that no reallocation takes place during insertions that happen after
a call to <tt>reserve()</tt> until the time when an insertion would make the size of the vector greater than
the value of <tt>capacity()</tt>.
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<blockquote><pre>
void shrink_to_fit();
</pre><blockquote><p>
<ins>-?- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
<ins>-?- <i>Complexity</i>: Takes at most linear time in the size of the sequence.</ins>
<p/>
-6- <i>Remarks</i>: <tt>shrink_to_fit</tt> is a non-binding request to reduce <tt>capacity()</tt> to <tt>size()</tt>. 
[ <i>Note</i>: The request is non-binding to allow latitude for implementation-specific optimizations. &mdash; <i>end note</i> ]
<ins>If an exception is thrown other than by the move constructor of a non-<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> <tt>T</tt> there 
are no effects.</ins>
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>[&hellip;]</p>

<blockquote><pre>
void resize(size_type sz);
</pre><blockquote><p>
-9- <i>Effects</i>: If <tt>sz &lt;= size()</tt>, equivalent to <del><tt>erase(begin() + sz, end());</tt></del><ins>calling 
<tt>pop_back()</tt> <tt>size() - sz</tt> times</ins>. If <tt>size() &lt; sz</tt>, appends <tt>sz - size()</tt> 
value-initialized elements to the sequence.
<p/>
-10- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <tt><del>Copy</del><ins>Move</ins>Insertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt> 
<ins>and <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt></ins>.
<p/>
<ins>-??- <i>Remarks</i>: If an exception is thrown other than by the move constructor of a non-<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> 
<tt>T</tt> there are no effects.</ins>
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<blockquote><pre>
void resize(size_type sz, const T&amp; c);
</pre><blockquote><p>
-11- <i>Effects</i>: <ins>If <tt>sz &lt;= size()</tt>, equivalent to calling <tt>pop_back()</tt> 
<tt>size() - sz</tt> times. If <tt>size() &lt; sz</tt>, appends <tt>sz - size()</tt> copies of <tt>c</tt> 
to the sequence.</ins>
</p><blockquote><pre>
<del>if (sz &gt; size())
  insert(end(), sz-size(), c);
else if (sz &lt; size())
  erase(begin()+sz, end());
else
  ; <i>// do nothing</i></del>
</pre></blockquote><p>
<ins>-??- <i>Requires</i>: <tt>T</tt> shall be <tt>MoveInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt> and 
<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> into <tt>*this</tt>.</ins>
<p/>
-12- <i><del>Requires</del><ins>Remarks</ins></i>: If an exception is thrown other than by the move constructor of a 
non-<tt>CopyInsertable</tt> <tt>T</tt> there are no effects.
</p></blockquote></blockquote>

</li>

</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
