<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2358" status="New">
<title>Apparently-bogus definition of <tt>is_empty</tt> type trait</title>
<section><sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/></section>
<submitter>Richard Smith</submitter>
<date>1 Feb 2014</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The 'Condition' for <tt>std::is_empty</tt> is listed as:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"<tt>T</tt> is a class type, but not a union type, with no non-static data members other than bit-fields of length 0, 
no virtual member functions, no virtual base classes, and no base class <tt>B</tt> for which <tt>is_empty&lt;B&gt;::value</tt> 
is false."
</p></blockquote>
<p>
This is incorrect: there is no such thing as a non-static data member that is a bit-field of length 0, since bit-fields of 
length 0 must be unnamed, and unnamed bit-fields are not members (see <sref ref="[class.bit]"/> p2).
<p/>
It also means that classes such as:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
struct S {
 int : 3;
};
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
are empty (because they have no non-static data members). There's implementation divergence on the value of 
<tt>is_empty&lt;S&gt;::value</tt>.
<p/>
I'm not sure what the purpose of <tt>is_empty</tt> is (or how it could be useful), but if it's desirable for the above type to 
not be treated as empty, something like this could work:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"<tt>T</tt> is a class type, but not a union type, with no non-static data members <del>other than</del><ins>, no unnamed</ins> 
bit-fields of <ins>non-zero</ins> length <del>0</del>, no virtual member functions, no virtual base classes, and no base class 
<tt>B</tt> for which <tt>is_empty&lt;B&gt;::value</tt> is false."
</p></blockquote>
<p>
and if the above type <em>should</em> be treated as empty, then this might be appropriate:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
"<tt>T</tt> is a class type, but not a union type, with no <ins>(named)</ins> non-static data members <del>other than bit-fields of 
length 0</del>, no virtual member functions, no virtual base classes, and no base class <tt>B</tt> for which 
<tt>is_empty&lt;B&gt;::value</tt> is false."
</p></blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
