<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1059" status="NAD Concepts">
<title>Usage of no longer existing FunctionType concept</title>
<section><sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>13 Mar 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Due to a deliberate core language decision, the earlier called
"foundation" concept <tt>std::FunctionType</tt> had been removed in
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2773.pdf">N2773</a>
shortly
before the first "conceptualized" version of the WP
(<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2798.pdf">N2798</a>)
had been
prepared. This caused a break of the library, which already used this
concept in the adapted definition of <tt>std::function</tt>
(<sref ref="[function.objects]"/>/2, header <tt>&lt;functional&gt;</tt> synopsis and
<sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/>).
</p>
<p>
A simple fix would be to either (a) make <tt>std::function</tt>'s primary template
unconstrained or to (b) add constraints based on existing (support) concepts.
A more advanced fix would (c) introduce a new library concept.
</p>
<p>
The big disadvantage of (a) is, that users can define templates which
cause compiler errors during instantiation time because of under-constrainedness
and would thus violate the basic advantage of constrained
code.
</p>
<p>
For (b), the ideal constraints for <tt>std::function</tt>'s template parameter would
be one which excludes everything else but the single provided partial
specialization that matches every "free function" type (i.e. any function
type w/o cv-qualifier-seq and w/o ref-qualifier).
Expressing such a type as as single requirement would be written as
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;typename T&gt;
requires ReferentType&lt;T&gt; // Eliminate cv void and function types with cv-qual-seq
                         //   or ref-qual (depending on core issue #749)
      &amp;&amp; PointeeType&lt;T&gt;  // Eliminate reference types
      &amp;&amp; !ObjectType&lt;T&gt;  // Eliminate object types
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
Just for completeness approach (c), which would make sense, if the
library has more reasons to constrain for free function types:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
auto concept FreeFunctionType&lt;typename T&gt;
  : ReferentType&lt;T&gt;, PointeeType&lt;T&gt;, MemberPointeeType&lt;T&gt;
{
  requires !ObjectType&lt;T&gt;;
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
I mention that approach because I expect that free function types belong
to the most natural type categories for every days coders. Potential
candidates in the library are <tt>addressof</tt> and class template <tt>packaged_task</tt>.
</p>

<note>
Batavia (2009-05):
</note>
<blockquote>
<p>
Alisdair would prefer to have a core-supported <tt>FunctionType</tt> concept
in order that any future changes be automatically correct
without need for a library solution to catch up;
he points to type traits as a precedent.
Further, he believes that a published concept can't in the future
be changed.
</p>
<p>
Bill feels this category of entity would change sufficiently slowly
that he would be willing to take the risk.
</p>
<p>
Of the discussed solutions, we tend toward option (c).
We like the idea of having a complete taxonomy of native types,
and perhaps erred in trimming the set.
</p>
<p>
We would like to have this issue reviewed by Core and would like
their feedback.  Move to Open.
</p>
</blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<ol>
<li>
<p>
Change in <sref ref="[function.objects]"/>/2, Header <tt>&lt;functional&gt;</tt> synopsis:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
// 20.6.16 polymorphic function wrappers:
class bad_function_call;
template&lt;<del>FunctionType</del><ins>ReferentType F</ins>&gt;
<ins>requires PointeeType&lt;F&gt; &amp;&amp; !ObjectType&lt;F&gt;</ins>
class function; // undefined
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>
Change in <sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/>:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
namespace std {
template&lt;<del>FunctionType</del><ins>ReferentType F</ins>&gt;
<ins>requires PointeeType&lt;F&gt; &amp;&amp; !ObjectType&lt;F&gt;</ins>
class function; // undefined
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
