<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="310" status="CD1">
<title>Is errno a macro?</title>
<section><sref ref="[headers]"/><sref ref="[errno]"/></section>
<submitter>Steve Clamage</submitter>
<date>21 Mar 2001</date>

<discussion>
  <p>
  Exactly how should errno be declared in a conforming C++ header?
  </p>

  <p>
  The C standard says in 7.1.4 that it is unspecified whether errno is a
  macro or an identifier with external linkage.  In some implementations
  it can be either, depending on compile-time options.  (E.g., on
  Solaris in multi-threading mode, errno is a macro that expands to a
  function call, but is an extern int otherwise.  "Unspecified" allows
  such variability.)
  </p>

  <p>The C++ standard:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>17.4.1.2 says in a note that errno must be macro in C. (false)</li>
  <li>17.4.3.1.3 footnote 166 says errno is reserved as an external 
      name (true), and implies that it is an identifier.</li>
  <li>19.3 simply lists errno as a macro (by what reasoning?) and goes
      on to say that the contents of of C++ &lt;errno.h&gt; are the
      same as in C, begging the question.</li>
  <li>C.2, table 95 lists errno as a macro, without comment.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>I find no other references to errno.</p>

  <p>We should either explicitly say that errno must be a macro, even
  though it need not be a macro in C, or else explicitly leave it
  unspecified.  We also need to say something about namespace std. 
  A user who includes &lt;cerrno&gt; needs to know whether to write
  <tt>errno</tt>, or <tt>::errno</tt>, or <tt>std::errno</tt>, or
  else &lt;cerrno&gt; is useless.</p>

  <p>Two acceptable fixes:</p>
  <ul>
    <li><p>errno must be a macro. This is trivially satisfied by adding<br/>
        &nbsp;&nbsp;#define errno (::std::errno)<br/>
        to the headers if errno is not already a macro. You then always
        write errno without any scope qualification, and it always expands
        to a correct reference. Since it is always a macro, you know to
        avoid using errno as a local identifer.</p></li>
    <li><p>errno is in the global namespace. This fix is inferior, because
        ::errno is not guaranteed to be well-formed.</p></li>
  </ul>

  <note>
    This issue was first raised in 1999, but it slipped through 
    the cracks.
  </note>
</discussion>

<resolution>
  <p>Change the Note in section 17.4.1.2p5 from</p>

    <blockquote><p>
    Note: the names defined as macros in C include the following:
    assert, errno, offsetof, setjmp, va_arg, va_end, and va_start.
    </p></blockquote>

  <p>to</p>

    <blockquote><p>
    Note: the names defined as macros in C include the following:
    assert, offsetof, setjmp, va_arg, va_end, and va_start.
    </p></blockquote>

  <p>In section 19.3, change paragraph 2 from</p>

    <blockquote><p>
    The contents are the same as the Standard C library header
    &lt;errno.h&gt;.
    </p></blockquote>

  <p>to</p>

    <blockquote><p>
    The contents are the same as the Standard C library header 
    &lt;errno.h&gt;, except that errno shall be defined as a macro.
    </p></blockquote>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>C++ must not leave it up to the implementation to decide whether or
not a name is a macro; it must explicitly specify exactly which names
are required to be macros.  The only one that really works is for it
to be a macro.</p>

<note>Cura&ccedil;ao: additional rationale added.</note>

</rationale>

</issue>
