<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1459" status="Open">
<title>[FCD] Overlapping evaluations are allowed</title>
<section><sref ref="[atomics.order]"/></section>
<submitter>Canada</submitter>
<date>25 Aug 2010</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses CA-21</b></p>

<sref ref="[atomics.lockfree]"/> p.8 states:
<p><blockquote>
An atomic store shall only store a value that has
been computed from constants and program input values
by a finite sequence of program evaluations, such
that each evaluation observes the values of variables
as computed by the last prior assignment in the
sequence.
</blockquote></p>
<p>
... but <sref ref="[intro.execution]"/> p.13 states:
</p>
<p><blockquote>
If A is not sequenced before B and B is not
sequenced before A, then A and B are unsequenced.
[ <em>Note</em>: The execution of unsequenced
evaluations can overlap. &mdash; <em>end note</em> ]
</blockquote></p>
<p>
Overlapping executions can make it impossible to
construct the sequence described in <sref ref="[atomics.lockfree]"/> p.8. We are not
sure of the intention here and do not offer a suggestion for
change, but note that <sref ref="[atomics.lockfree]"/> p.8 is the condition that prevents
out-of-thin-air reads.
</p>
<p>
For an example, suppose we have a function invocation
f(e1,e2). The evaluations of e1 and e2 can overlap.
Suppose that the evaluation of e1 writes y and reads x
whereas the evaluation of e2 reads y and writes x, with
reads-from edges as below (all this is within a single
thread).
<PRE>
 e1           e2
Wrlx y--   --Wrlx x
      rf\ /rf
         X
        / \
Rrlx x&lt;-   -&gt;Rrlx y
</PRE>
This seems like it should be allowed, but there seems to
be no way to produce a sequence of evaluations with the
property above.
</p>
In more detail, here the two evaluations, e1 and e2, are
being executed as the arguments of a function and are
consequently not sequenced-before each other. In
practice we'd expect that they could overlap (as allowed
by <sref ref="[intro.execution]"/> p.13), with the two writes taking effect before the two
reads. However, if we have to construct a linear order of
evaluations, as in <sref ref="[atomics.lockfree]"/> p.8, then the execution above is not
permited. Is that really intended?

<note>
Resolution proposed by ballot comment
</note>
<p>
Please clarify.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
