<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1015" status="NAD Concepts">
<title>C++ programs - but not users - need to provide support <tt>concept_map</tt>s</title>
<section><sref ref="[concept.transform]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>11 Mar 2009</date>

<discussion>

<p><b>Addresses UK 199</b></p>

<p>
The requirement that programs do not supply <tt>concept_maps</tt> should
probably be users do not supply their own <tt>concept_map</tt>
specializations. The program will almost certainly supply
<tt>concept_maps</tt> - the standard itself supplies a specialization
for <tt>RvalueOf</tt> references. Note that the term <i>program</i> is
defined in <sref ref="[basic.link]"/>p1 and makes no account of the
standard library being treated differently to user written code.
</p>

<note>
2009-05-09 Alisdair adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
The same problem is present in the words added for the
<tt>LvalueReference/RvalueReference</tt> concepts last meeting.
</p>
<p>
With three subsections requiring the same constraint, I'm wondering if there
is a better way to organise this section.
Possible 20.2.1 -&gt; 20.2.3 belong in the fundamental concepts clause in
<sref ref="[concept.support]"/>?  While they can be implemented purely as a
library feature without additional compiler support, they are pretty
fundamental and we want the same restriction on user-concept maps as is
mandated there.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
Batavia (2009-05):
</note>
<blockquote><p>
We agree with the issue,
but believe the wording needs further improvement.
We want to investigate current definitions for nomenclature such as
"user" and "program."
Move to Open pending the recommended investigation.
</p></blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Change <sref ref="[concept.transform]"/> p2:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
-2- A <del>program</del> <ins>user</ins> shall not provide concept maps for
any concept in 20.1.1.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
Change <sref ref="[concept.true]"/> p2:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
-2- <i>Requires:</i> a <del>program</del> <ins>user</ins> shall not
provide a concept map for the <tt>True</tt> concept.
</p></blockquote>

<p>
Change <sref ref="[concept.classify]"/> p2:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
-2- <i>Requires:</i> a <del>program</del><ins>user</ins> shall not provide concept
maps for any concept in this section.
</p></blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
