<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1236" status="NAD">
<title>reserved identifiers in programs not using the library</title>
<section><sref ref="[library]"/></section>
<submitter>Sean Hunt</submitter>
<date>13 Oct 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I wasn't sure whether to consider this a library or a language issue,
because the issue is I think it's incorrectly categorized as being part
of the library, so I thought I'd send a message to both of you and let
you sort it out.
</p>

<p>
Most reserved identifiers are treated as unilaterally available to the
implementation, such as to implement language extensions, or provide
macros documenting its functionality. However, the requirements for
reserved identifers are in <sref ref="[reserved.names]"/>, which are a
subsection of <sref ref="[constraints]"/>. <sref
ref="[constraints.overview]"/> appears only to apply to "C++ programs
that use the facilities of the C++ standard library", meaning that, in
theory, all implementations are erroneous in having any non-standard
identifiers predefined for programs that do not, at some point, include
a standard library header.
</p>

<p>
Furthermore, it's unclear whether the use of certain identifiers is UB
or results in an ill-formed program. In particular, <sref
ref="[macro.names]"/> uses a "shall not", where <sref
ref="[global.names]"/> says that names are "reserved to the
implementation". <sref ref="[reserved.names]"/> seems only to cover the
instance of a name being described as "reserved", so are implementations
required to diagnose a program that performs, as an example, "<tt>#undef
get</tt>"?
</p>

<note>
2009 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Move to NAD. There may in theory be multiple interpretations possible,
but there's no evidence that this causes any genuine problems or
uncertainty about what implementations are allowed to do. We do not
believe this rises to the level of a defect.
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
