<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="887" status="NAD">
<title>issue with condition::wait_...</title>
<section><sref ref="[thread.condition.condvar]"/></section>
<submitter>Lawrence Crowl</submitter>
<date>15 Sep 2008</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The Posix/C++ working group has identified an inconsistency between
Posix and the C++ working draft in that Posix requires the clock to be
identified at creation, whereas C++ permits identifying the clock at the
call to wait.  The latter cannot be implemented with the former.
</p>

<note>
San Francisco:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Howard recommends NAD with the following explanation:
</p>

<p>
The intent of the current wording is for the <tt>condtion_variable::wait_until</tt>
be able to handle user-defined clocks as well as clocks the system knows about.
This can be done by providing overloads for the known clocks, and another
overload for unknown clocks which synchs to a known clock before waiting.
For example:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class Duration&gt;
bool
condition_variable::wait_until(unique_lock&lt;mutex&gt;&amp; lock,
                               const chrono::time_point&lt;chrono::system_clock, Duration&gt;&amp; abs_time)
{
    using namespace chrono;
    nanoseconds d = __round_up&lt;nanoseconds&gt;(abs_time.time_since_epoch());
    __do_timed_wait(lock.mutex()-&gt;native_handle(), time_point&lt;system_clock, nanoseconds&gt;(d));
    return system_clock::now() &lt; abs_time;
}

template &lt;class Clock, class Duration&gt;
bool
condition_variable::wait_until(unique_lock&lt;mutex&gt;&amp; lock,
                               const chrono::time_point&lt;Clock, Duration&gt;&amp; abs_time)
{
    using namespace chrono;
    system_clock::time_point    s_entry = system_clock::now();
    typename Clock::time_point  c_entry = Clock::now();
    nanoseconds dn = __round_up&lt;nanoseconds&gt;(abs_time.time_since_epoch() -
                                              c_entry.time_since_epoch());
    __do_timed_wait(lock.mutex()-&gt;native_handle(), s_entry + dn);
    return Clock::now() &lt; abs_time;
}
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
In the above example, <tt>system_clock</tt> is the only clock which the underlying
condition variable knows how to deal with.  One overload just passes that clock
through.  The second overload (approximately) converts the unknown clock into
a <tt>system_clock  time_point</tt> prior to passing it down to the native
condition variable.
</p>

<p>
On Posix systems vendors are free to add implementation defined constructors which
take a clock.  That clock can be stored in the condition_variable, and converted
to (or not as necessary) as shown above.
</p>

<p>
If an implementation defined constructor takes a clock (for example), then part
of the semantics for that implementation defined ctor might include that a
<tt>wait_until</tt> using a clock other than the one constructed with results
in an error (exceptional condition) instead of a conversion to the stored clock.
Such a design is up to the vendor as once an implementation defined ctor is used,
the vendor is free to specifiy the behavior of waits and/or notifies however
he pleases (when the cv is constructed in an implementation defined manner).
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
Post Summit:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
"POSIX people will review the proposed NAD resolution at their upcoming NY
meeting.
</p>

<p>
See the minutes at: <a href="http://wiki.dinkumware.com/twiki/bin/view/Posix/POSIX-CppBindingWorkingGroupNewYork2009">http://wiki.dinkumware.com/twiki/bin/view/Posix/POSIX-CppBindingWorkingGroupNewYork2009</a>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
Move to NAD.
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07-18 Detlef reopens the issue:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
On Friday afternoon in Frankfurt is was decided that 887 is NAD.
This decision was mainly based on a sample implementation presented
by Howard that implemented one clock on top of another.
Unfortunately this implementation doesn't work for the probably most
important case where a system has a monotonic clock and a real-time
clock (or "wall time" clock):
</p>
<p>
If the underlying "system_clock" is a monotonic clock, and
the program waits on the real-time clock, and the real-time clock
is set forward, the wait will unblock too late.
</p>

<p>
If the underlying "system_clock" is a real-time clock, and the
program waits on the monotonic clock, and the real-time clock
is set back, the wait again will unblock too late.
</p>

<p>
Sorry that I didn't remember this on Friday, but it was Friday
afternoon after a busy week...
</p>

<p>
So as the decision was made on a wrong asumption, I propose to re-open
the issue.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-07-26 Howard adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Detlef correctly argues that <tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt> could
return "too late" in the context of clocks being adjusted during the wait.  I agree
with his logic.  But I disagree that this makes this interface unimplementable
on POSIX.
</p>

<p>
The POSIX spec also does not guarantee that <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt> does
not return "too late" when clocks are readjusted during the wait.  Indeed, the
POSIX specification lacks any requirements at all concerning how soon
<tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt> returns after a time out.  This is evidently a
QOI issue by the POSIX standard.  Here is a quote of the most relevant normative
text concerning <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt> found
<a href="http://www.unix.org/single_unix_specification/">here</a>.
</p>

<blockquote>
The <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait()</tt> function shall be equivalent to
<tt>pthread_cond_wait()</tt>, except that an error is returned if the absolute
time specified by <tt>abstime</tt> passes (that is, system time equals or exceeds
<tt>abstime</tt>) before the condition <tt>cond</tt> is signaled or broadcasted, or if the
absolute time specified by <tt>abstime</tt> has already been passed at the time
of the call.
</blockquote>

<p>
I.e. the POSIX specification speaks of the error code returned in case of a time
out, but not on the timeliness of that return.
</p>

<p>
Might this simply be an oversight, or minor defect in the POSIX specification?
</p>

<p>
I do not believe so.  This same section goes on to say in <em>non-normative</em>
text:
</p>

<blockquote>
For cases when the system clock is advanced discontinuously by an
operator, it is expected that implementations process any timed wait
expiring at an intervening time as if that time had actually occurred.
</blockquote>

<p>
Here is non-normative wording encouraging the implementation to ignore an advancing
underlying clock and subsequently causing an early (spurious) return.  There is
no wording at all which addresses Detlef's example of a "late return".  With
<tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt> this would be caused by setting the system clock
backwards.  It seems reasonable to assume, based on the wording that is already
in the POSIX spec, that again, the discontinuously changed clock would be ignored
by <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt>. 
</p>

<p>
A noteworthy difference between <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt> and
<tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt> is that the POSIX spec appears to
say that <tt>ETIMEDOUT</tt> should be returned if <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt>
returns because of timeout signal, whether or not the system clock was discontinuously
advanced during the wait.  In contrast <tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt>
always returns:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
<tt>Clock::now() &lt; abs_time</tt>
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
That is, the C++ spec requires that the clock be rechecked (detecting discontinuous
adjustments during the wait) at the time of return.  <tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt>
may indeed return early or late.  But regardless it will return a value
reflecting timeout status at the time of return (even if clocks have been adjusted).
Of course the clock may be adjusted after the return value is computed but before the client has
a chance to read the result of the return.  Thus there are no iron-clad guarantees
here.
</p>

<p>
<tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt> (and <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait</tt>)
is little more than a convenience function for making sure
<tt>condition_variable::wait</tt> doesn't hang for an unreasonable amount of
time (where the client gets to define "unreasonable").  I do not think it
is in anyone's interest to try to make it into anything more than that.
</p>

<p>
I maintain that this is a useful and flexible specification in the spirit of
C++, and is implementable on POSIX.  The implementation technique described above
is a reasonable approach.  There may also be higher quality approaches.  This
specification, like the POSIX specification, gives a wide latitude for QOI.
</p>

<p>
I continue to recommend NAD, but would not object to a clarifying note regarding
the behavior of <tt>condition_variable::wait_until</tt>.  At the moment, I do
not have good wording for such a note, but welcome suggestions.
</p>

</blockquote>

<note>
2009-09-30: See <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2969.html">N2969</a>.
</note>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
The LWG is in favor of Detlef to supply revision which adopts Option 2 from
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2969.html">N2969</a>
but is modified by saying that <tt>system_clock</tt> must be available for <tt>wait_until</tt>.
</blockquote>

<note>
2010-02-11 Anthony provided wording.
</note>

<note>
2010-02-22 Anthony adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
I am strongly against
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2999.html">N2999</a>.
</p>

<p>
Firstly, I think that the most appropriate use of a timed wait on a condition
variable is with a monotonic clock, so it ought to be guaranteed to be available
on systems that support such a clock. Also, making the set of supported clocks
implementation defined essentially kills portability around the use of
user-defined clocks.
</p>

<p>
I also think that <tt>wait_for</tt> is potentially useful, and trivially
implementable given a working templated <tt>wait_until</tt> and a monotonic
clock.
</p>

<p>
I also disagree with many of Detlef's points in the rationale. In a system with
hard latency limits there is likely to be a monotonic clock, otherwise you have
no way of measuring against these latency limits since the <tt>system_clock</tt>
may change arbitrarily. In such systems, you <em>want</em> to be able to use
<tt>wait_for</tt>, or <tt>wait_until</tt> with a monotonic clock.
</p>

<p>
I disagree that the <tt>wait_*</tt> functions cannot be implemented correctly on
top of POSIX: I have done so. The only guarantee in the working draft is that
when the function returns certain properties are true; there is no guarantee
that the function will return <em>immediately</em> that the properties are true.
My resolution to issue 887 makes this clear. How small the latency is is QoI.
</p>

<p>
On systems without a monotonic clock, you cannot measure the problem since the
system clock can change arbitrarily so any timing calculations you make may be
wrong due to clock changes.
</p>

<p>
On systems with a monotonic clock, you can choose to use it for your condition
variables. If you are waiting against a <tt>system_clock::time_point</tt> then
you can check the clock when waking, and either return as a timeout or spurious
wake depending on whether <tt>system_clock::now()</tt> is before or after the
specified <tt>time_point</tt>.
</p>

<p>
Windows <em>does</em> provide condition variables from Vista onwards. I choose
not to use them, but they are there. If people are concerned about
implementation difficulty, the Boost implementation can be used for most
purposes; the Boost license is pretty liberal in that regard.
</p>

<p>
My preferred resolution to issue 887 is currently the PR in the issues list.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2010 Pittsburgh:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
There is no consensus for moving the related paper
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2999.html">N2999</a>
into the WP.
</p>
<p>
There was support for moving this issue as proposed to Ready, but the support
was insufficient to call a consensus.
</p>
<p>
There was consensus for moving this issue to NAD as opposed to leaving it open.
Rationale added.
</p>
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>
The standard as written is sufficiently implementable and self consistent.
</p>
</rationale>

<resolution>
<p>
Add a new paragraph after <sref ref="[thread.req.timing]"/>p3:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
3 The resolution of timing provided by an implementation depends on both
operating system and hardware. The finest resolution provided by an
implementation is called the <i>native resolution</i>.
</p>

<p><ins>
If a function in this clause takes a timeout argument, and the time point or
elapsed time specified passes before the function returns, the latency between
the timeout occurring and the function returning is unspecified [<i>Note:</i>
Implementations should strive to keep such latency as small as possible, but
portable code should not rely on any specific upper limits &mdash; <i>end
note</i>]
</ins></p>
</blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
