<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
    <!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY nbsp " ">
     ]
>
<issue num="422" status="CD1">
<title>explicit specializations of member functions of class templates</title>
<section><sref ref="[reserved.names]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>18 Sep 2003</date>

<discussion>
<p>
It has been suggested that 17.4.3.1, p1 may or may not allow programs to
explicitly specialize members of standard templates on user-defined types.
The answer to the question might have an impact where library requirements
are given using the "as if" rule. I.e., if programs are allowed to specialize
member functions they will be able to detect an implementation's strict
conformance to Effects clauses that describe the behavior of the function
in terms of the other member function (the one explicitly specialized by
the program) by relying on the "as if" rule.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>

<p>
  Add the following sentence to <sref ref="[reserved.names]"/>, p1:
</p>

<blockquote><p>
It is undefined for a C++ program to add declarations or definitions to
namespace std or namespaces within namespace <tt>std</tt> unless otherwise specified. A
program may add template specializations for any standard library template to
namespace <tt>std</tt>. Such a specialization (complete or partial) of a standard library
template results in undefined behavior unless the declaration depends on a
user-defined type of external linkage and unless the specialization meets the
standard library requirements for the original template.<sup>168)</sup>
<ins>A program has undefined behavior if it declares</ins>
</p>
<ul>
<li><ins>an explicit specialization of any member function of a standard
            library class template, or</ins></li>
<li><ins>an explicit specialization of any member function template of a
            standard library class or class template, or</ins></li>
<li><ins>an explicit or partial specialization of any member class
            template of a standard library class or class template.</ins></li>
</ul>
<p>
A program may explicitly instantiate any templates in the standard library only
if the declaration depends on the name of a user-defined type of external
linkage and the instantiation meets the standard library requirements for the
original template.
</p></blockquote>

<note>Kona: straw poll was 6-1 that user programs should not be
  allowed to specialize individual member functions of standard
  library class templates, and that doing so invokes undefined
  behavior. Post-Kona: Martin provided wording.</note>

<note>Sydney: The LWG agrees that the standard shouldn't permit users
to specialize individual member functions unless they specialize the
whole class, but we're not sure these words say what we want them to;
they could be read as prohibiting the specialization of any standard
library class templates. We need to consult with CWG to make sure we
use the right wording.</note>

</resolution>
</issue>
