<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="128" status="NAD">
<title>Need open_mode() function for file stream, string streams, file buffers, and string&nbsp; buffers</title>
<section><sref ref="[string.streams]"/> <sref ref="[file.streams]"/></section>
<submitter>Angelika Langer</submitter>
<date>22 Feb 1999</date>

<discussion>
<p>The following question came from Thorsten Herlemann:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can set a mode when constructing or opening a file-stream or
  filebuf, e.g.  ios::in, ios::out, ios::binary, ... But how can I get
  that mode later on, e.g. in my own operator &lt;&lt; or operator
  &gt;&gt; or when I want to check whether a file-stream or
  file-buffer object passed as parameter is opened for input or output
  or binary? Is there no possibility? Is this a design-error in the
  standard C++ library? </p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is indeed impossible to find out what a stream's or stream
buffer's open mode is, and without that knowledge you don't know
how certain operations behave. Just think of the append mode. </p>

<p>Both streams and stream buffers should have a <tt>mode()</tt> function that returns the
current open mode setting. </p>

<note>
post Bellevue:  Alisdair requested to re-Open.
</note>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Neither Howard nor Bill has received a customer request for this.
</p>
<p>
No consensus for change. The programmer can save this information to the side.
</p>
<p>
Moved to NAD.
</p>
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>For stream buffers, add a function to the base class as a non-virtual function
qualified as const to <sref ref="[streambuf]"/>:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<tt>openmode mode() const</tt>;</p>

<p><b>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Returns</b> the current open mode.</p>

<p>With streams, I'm not sure what to suggest. In principle, the mode
could already be returned by <tt>ios_base</tt>, but the mode is only
initialized for file and string stream objects, unless I'm overlooking
anything. For this reason it should be added to the most derived
stream classes. Alternatively, it could be added to <tt>basic_ios</tt>
and would be default initialized in <tt>basic_ios&lt;&gt;::init()</tt>.</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>This might be an interesting extension for some future, but it is
not a defect in the current standard. The Proposed Resolution is
retained for future reference.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
