<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="573" status="NAD">
<title>C++0x file positioning should handle modern file sizes</title>
<section><sref ref="[fpos]"/></section>
<submitter>Beman Dawes</submitter>
<date>12 Apr 2006</date>

<discussion>
<p>
There are two deficiencies related to file sizes:
</p>
<ol>
<li>It doesn't appear that the Standard Library is specified in
      a way that handles modern file sizes, which are often too
      large to be represented by an unsigned long.</li>

<li>The <tt>std::fpos</tt> class does not currently have the ability to
      set/get file positions.</li>
</ol>
<p>
The Dinkumware implementation of the Standard Library as shipped with the Microsoft compiler copes with these issues by:
</p>
<ol style="list-style-type:upper-alpha">
<li>Defining <tt>fpos_t</tt> be <tt>long long</tt>, which is large enough to
      represent any file position likely in the foreseeable future.</li>

<li>Adding member functions to class <tt>fpos</tt>. For example,
<blockquote><pre>
fpos_t seekpos() const;
</pre></blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
Because there are so many types relating to file positions and offsets (<tt>fpos_t</tt>,
<tt>fpos</tt>, <tt>pos_type</tt>, <tt>off_type</tt>, <tt>streamoff</tt>, <tt>streamsize</tt>, 
<tt>streampos</tt>, <tt>wstreampos</tt>, and perhaps more), it is difficult to know if 
the Dinkumware extensions are sufficient. But they seem a useful starting place for 
discussions, and they do represent existing practice.
</p>

<note>
Kona (2007): We need a paper. It would be nice if someone proposed
clarifications to the definitions of <tt>pos_type</tt> and <tt>off_type</tt>. Currently
these definitions are horrible. Proposed Disposition: Open
</note>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
This is the subject of paper N2926.
</p>
<p>
If we choose to take any action, we will move the paper, so the issue can be closed.
</p>
<p>
Move to NAD.
</p>
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
</p>
</resolution>

</issue>
