<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1102" status="NAD">
<title><tt>std::vector</tt>'s reallocation policy still unclear</title>
<section><sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>20 Apr 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
I have the impression that even the wording of current draft
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2009/n2857.pdf">N2857</a>
does insufficiently express the intent of <tt>vector</tt>'s
reallocation strategy. This has produced not too old library
implementations which release memory in the <tt>clear()</tt> function
and even modern articles about C++ programming cultivate
the belief that <tt>clear</tt> is allowed to do exactly this. A typical
example is something like this:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
const int buf_size = ...;
std::vector&lt;T&gt; buf(buf_size);
for (int i = 0; i &lt; some_condition; ++i) {
  buf.resize(buf_size);
  write_or_read_data(buf.data());
  buf.clear(); // Ensure that the next round get's 'zeroed' elements
}
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
where still the myth is ubiquitous that <tt>buf</tt> might be
allowed to reallocate it's memory *inside* the <tt>for</tt> loop.
</p>
<p>
IMO the problem is due to the fact, that
</p>

<ol type="a">
<li>
the actual memory-reallocation stability of <tt>std::vector</tt>
is explained in <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/>/3 and /6 which
are describing just the effects of the <tt>reserve</tt>
function, but in many examples (like above) there
is no explicit call to <tt>reserve</tt> involved. Further-more
<sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/>/6 does only mention <em>insertions</em>
and never mentions the consequences of erasing
elements.
</li>
<li>
<p>
the effects clause of <tt>std::vector</tt>'s <tt>erase</tt> overloads in
<sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/4 is silent about capacity changes. This
easily causes a misunderstanding, because the counter
parting insert functions described in <sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/2
explicitly say, that
</p>
<blockquote>
Causes reallocation if the new size is greater than the
old capacity. If no reallocation happens, all the iterators
and references before the insertion point remain valid.
</blockquote>
<p>
It requires a complex argumentation chain about four
different places in the standard to provide the - possibly
weak - proof that calling <tt>clear()</tt> also does <em>never</em> change
the capacity of the <tt>std::vector</tt> container. Since <tt>std::vector</tt>
is the de-facto replacement of C99's dynamic arrays this
type is near to a built-in type and it's specification should
be clear enough that usual programmers can trust their
own reading.
</p>
</li>
</ol>

<note>
Batavia (2009-05):
</note>
<blockquote>
<p>
Bill believes paragraph 1 of the proposed resolution is unnecessary
because it is already implied (even if tortuously) by the current wording.
</p>
<p>
Move to Review.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Mark as NAD. Rationale: there is no consensus to clarify the standard,
general consensus that the standard is correct as written.
</blockquote>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<note>
This is a minimum version. I also
suggest that the wording explaining the allocation strategy
of <tt>std::vector</tt> in <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/>/3 and /6 is moved into
a separate sub paragraph of <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/> <em>before</em>
any of the prototype's are discussed, but I cannot provide
reasonable wording changes now
</note>

<ol>
<li>
<p>
Change <sref ref="[vector.capacity]"/>/6 as follows:
</p>
<blockquote>
It is guaranteed that no reallocation takes place during
insertions <ins>or erasures</ins> that happen after a call
to <tt>reserve()</tt> until the time when an insertion would make
the size of the vector greater than the value of <tt>capacity()</tt>.
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>
Change <sref ref="[vector.modifiers]"/>/4 as follows:
</p>
<blockquote>
<i>Effects:</i> <ins>The capacity shall remain unchanged and no reallocation shall
happen.</ins>
Invalidates iterators and references at or after the point
of the erase.
</blockquote>
</li>
</ol>
</resolution>

</issue>
