<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="489" status="NAD">
<title>std::remove / std::remove_if wrongly specified</title>
<section><sref ref="[alg.remove]"/></section>
<submitter>Thomas Mang</submitter>
<date>12 Dec 2004</date>

<discussion>
<p>In Section 25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraphs 1 to 5 describe the
behavior of the mutating sequence operations std::remove and
std::remove_if. However, the wording does not reflect the intended
behavior [Note: See definition of intended behavior below] of these
algorithms, as it is known to the C++ community [1].
</p>



<p>1) Analysis of current wording:</p>


<p>25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 2:</p>

<p>Current wording says:
"Effects: Eliminates all the elements referred to by iterator i in the
range [first, last) for which the following corresponding conditions
hold: *i == value, pred(*i) != false."</p>

<p>
This sentences expresses specifically that all elements denoted by the
(original) range [first, last) for which the corresponding condition
hold will be eliminated. Since there is no formal definition of the term
"eliminate" provided, the meaning of "eliminate" in everyday language
implies that as postcondition, no element in the range denoted by
[first, last) will hold the corresponding condition on reiteration over
the range [first, last).
</p>

<p>
However, this is neither the intent [Note: See definition of intended
behavior below] nor a general possible approach. It can be easily proven
that if all elements of the original range[first, last) will hold the
condition, it is not possible to substitute them by an element for which
the condition will not hold.
</p>


<p>25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 3:</p>

<p>
Current wording says:
"Returns: The end of the resulting range."
</p>

<p>
The resulting range is not specified. In combination with 25.2.7
[lib.alg.remove], paragraph 2, the only reasonable interpretation of
this so-called resulting range is the range [first,last) - thus
returning always the ForwardIterator 'last' parameter.
</p>


<p>
25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 4:
</p>

<p>
Current wording says:
"Notes: Stable: the relative order of the elements that are not removed
is the same as their relative order in the original range"
</p>

<p>
This sentences makes use of the term "removed", which is neither
specified, nor used in a previous paragraph (which uses the term
"eliminate"), nor unamgiuously separated from the name of the algorithm.
</p>


<p>2) Description of intended behavior:</p>

<p>
For the rest of this Defect Report, it is assumed that the intended
behavior was that all elements of the range [first, last) which do not
hold the condition *i == value (std::remove) or  pred(*i) != false
(std::remove_if)], call them s-elements [Note: s...stay], will be placed
into a contiguous subrange of [first, last), denoted by the iterators
[first, return value). The number of elements in the resulting range
[first, return value) shall be equal to the number of s-elements in the
original range [first, last). The relative order of the elements in the
resulting subrange[first, return value) shall be the same as the
relative order of the corresponding elements in the original range. It
is undefined whether any elements in the resulting subrange [return
value, last) will hold the corresponding condition, or not.
</p>

<p>
All implementations known to the author of this Defect Report comply
with this intent. Since the intent  of the behavior (contrary to the
current wording) is also described in various utility references serving
the C++ community [1], it is not expected that fixing the paragraphs
will influence current code - unless the code relies on the behavior as
it is described by current wording and the implementation indeed
reflects the current wording, and not the intent.
</p>



<p>3) Proposed fixes:</p>


<p>Change 25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 2 to:</p>

<p>
"Effect: Places all the elements referred to by iterator i in the range
[first, last) for which the following corresponding conditions hold :
!(*i == value), pred(*i) == false into the subrange [first, k) of the
original range, where k shall denote a value of type ForwardIterator. It
is undefined whether any elements in the resulting subrange [k, last)
will hold the corresponding condition, or not."
</p>

<p>Comments to the new wording:</p>

<p>
a) "Places" has no special meaning, and the everyday language meaning
should fit.
b) The corresponding conditions were negated compared to the current
wording, becaue the new wording requires it.
c) The wording "of the original range" might be redundant, since any
subrange starting at 'first' and containing no more elements than the
original range is implicitly a subrange of the original range [first,
last).
d) The iterator k was introduced instead of "return value" in order to
avoid a cyclic dependency on 25.2.7/3. The wording ", where k shall
denote a value of type ForwardIterator" might be redundant, because it
follows implicitly by 25.2.7/3.
e) "Places" does, in the author's opinion, explicitly forbid duplicating
any element holding the corresponding condition in the original range
[first, last) within the resulting range [first, k). If there is doubt
this term might be not unambiguous regarding this, it is suggested that
k is specified more closely by the following wording: "k shall denote a
value of type ForwardIterator [Note: see d)] so that k - first is equal
to the number of elements in the original range [first, last) for which
the corresponding condition did hold". This could also be expressed as a
separate paragraph "Postcondition:"
f) The senctence "It is undefined whether any elements in the resulting
subrange [k, last) will hold the corresponding condition, or not." was
added consciously so the term "Places" does not imply if the original
range [first, last) contains n elements holding the corresponding
condition, the identical range[first, last) will also contain exactly n
elements holding the corresponding condition after application of the
algorithm.
</p>

<p>
Change 25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 3 to:

"Returns: The iterator k."
</p>

<p>
Change 25.2.7 [lib.alg.remove], paragraph 4 to:

"Notes: Stable: the relative order of the elements that are placed into
the subrange [first, return value) shall be the same as their relative
order was in the original range [first, last) prior to application of
the algorithm."
</p>

<p>
Comments to the new wording:
</p>

<p>
a) the wording "was ...  prior to application of the algorithm" is used
to explicitly distinguish the original range not only by means of
iterators, but also by a 'chronological' factor from the resulting range
[first, return value). It might be redundant.
</p>

<p>
[1]:
The wording of these references is not always unambiguous, and provided
examples partially contradict verbal description of the algorithms,
because the verbal description resembles the problematic wording of
ISO/IEC 14882:2003.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The LWG believes that the standard is sufficiently clear, and that
  there is no evidence of any real-world confusion about this point.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
