<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="91" status="CD1">
<title>Description of operator&gt;&gt; and getline() for string&lt;&gt; might cause endless loop</title>
<section><sref ref="[string.io]"/></section>
<submitter>Nico Josuttis</submitter>
<date>29 Sep 1998</date>

<discussion>
<p>Operator &gt;&gt; and getline() for strings read until eof()
in the input stream is true. However, this might never happen, if the
stream can't read anymore without reaching EOF. So shouldn't it be
changed into that it reads until !good() ? </p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>In <sref ref="[string.io]"/>, paragraph 1, replace:</p>
<blockquote><p>
Effects: Begins by constructing a sentry object k as if k were
constructed by typename basic_istream&lt;charT,traits&gt;::sentry k( is). If
bool( k) is true, it calls str.erase() and then extracts characters
from is and appends them to str as if by calling str.append(1, c). If
is.width() is greater than zero, the maximum number n of characters
appended is is.width(); otherwise n is str.max_size(). Characters are
extracted and appended until any of the following occurs:
</p></blockquote>
<p>with:</p>
<blockquote><p>
Effects: Behaves as a formatted input function (<sref ref="[istream.formatted.reqmts]"/>).  After constructing a sentry object, if the
sentry converts to true, calls str.erase() and then extracts
characters from is and appends them to str as if by calling
str.append(1,c). If is.width() is greater than zero, the maximum
number n of characters appended is is.width(); otherwise n is
str.max_size(). Characters are extracted and appended until any of the
following occurs:
</p></blockquote>

<p>In <sref ref="[string.io]"/>, paragraph 6, replace</p>
<blockquote><p>
Effects: Begins by constructing a sentry object k as if by typename
basic_istream&lt;charT,traits&gt;::sentry k( is, true). If bool( k) is true,
it calls str.erase() and then extracts characters from is and appends
them to str as if by calling str.append(1, c) until any of the
following occurs:
</p></blockquote>
<p>with:</p>
<blockquote><p>
Effects: Behaves as an unformatted input function (<sref ref="[istream.unformatted]"/>), except that it does not affect the value returned
by subsequent calls to basic_istream&lt;&gt;::gcount().  After
constructing a sentry object, if the sentry converts to true, calls
str.erase() and then extracts characters from is and appends them to
str as if by calling str.append(1,c) until any of the following
occurs:
</p></blockquote>

<note>Redmond: Made changes in proposed resolution.  <tt>operator&gt;&gt;</tt>
should be a formatted input function, not an unformatted input function.
<tt>getline</tt> should not be required to set <tt>gcount</tt>, since
there is no mechanism for <tt>gcount</tt> to be set except by one of
<tt>basic_istream</tt>'s member functions.</note>

<note>Cura&ccedil;ao: Nico agrees with proposed resolution.</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The real issue here is whether or not these string input functions
get their characters from a streambuf, rather than by calling an
istream's member functions, a streambuf signals failure either by
returning eof or by throwing an exception; there are no other
possibilities.  The proposed resolution makes it clear that these two
functions do get characters from a streambuf.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
