<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2116" status="New">
<title><tt>std::swap noexcept(what?)</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[meta.unary.prop]"/></section>
<submitter>Dave Abrahams</submitter>
<date>9 Dec 2011</date>

<discussion>

<p>
IMO if we specified <tt>is_[nothrow_]constructible</tt> in terms of a variable
declaration whose validity requires destructibility, it is clearly a bug
in our specification and a failure to realize the actual original
intent. The specification should have been in terms of placement-new.
<p/>
Daniel:<br/>
At the time of the specification this was intended and the solution is
<em>not</em> done by removing the destruction semantics of <tt>is_constructible</tt>.
<p/>
The design of <tt>is_constructible</tt> was also impacted by the previous
<tt>Constructible</tt> concept that <em>explicitly</em> contained destruction semantics,
because during conceptification of the library it turned out to simplify
the constraints  in the library because you did not need to add
<tt>Destructible</tt> all the time. It often was implied but never spoken out
in C++03.
<p/>
Pure construction semantics was considered as useful as well, so <tt>HasConstructor</tt> 
did also exist and would surely be useful as trait as well.
<p/>
Another example that is often overlooked: This also affects wrapper types like <tt>pair</tt>, 
<tt>tuple</tt>, <tt>array</tt> that contain potentially more than one type:
This is easy to understand if you think of <tt>T1</tt> having a deleted destructor
and <tt>T2</tt> having a constructor that may throw: Obviously the compiler has
potentially need to use the <tt>destructor</tt> of <tt>T1</tt> in the <em>constructor</em>
of <tt>std::pair&lt;T1, T2&gt;</tt> to ensure that the core language requirements
are satisfied (All previous fully constructed sub-objects must be destructed).
<p/>
The core language also honors this fact in <sref ref="[class.copy]"/> p11:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
A defaulted copy&#47;move constructor for a class <tt>X</tt> is defined as deleted (<sref ref="[dcl.fct.def.delete]"/>) 
if <tt>X</tt> has:<br/>
[&hellip;]<br/>
&mdash; any direct or virtual base class or non-static data member of a type with a destructor that is deleted
or inaccessible from the defaulted constructor,<br/>
[&hellip;]
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Dave:<br/>
This is about <tt>is_nothrow_constructible</tt> in particular. The fact that it is 
foiled by not having a <tt>noexcept</tt> dtor is a defect.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
