<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2157" status="Open">
<title>How does <tt>std::array&lt;T,0&gt;</tt> initialization work when <tt>T</tt> is not default-constructible?</title>
<section><sref ref="[array.zero]"/></section>
<submitter>Daryle Walker</submitter>
<date>8 May 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
Objects of <tt>std::array&lt;T,N&gt;</tt> are supposed to be initialized with aggregate initialization (when 
not the destination of a copy or move). This clearly works when <tt>N</tt> is positive. What happens when <tt>N</tt> 
is zero?  To continue using an (inner) set of braces for initialization, a <tt>std::array&lt;T,0&gt;</tt> implementation 
must have an array member of at least one element, and let default initialization take care of those secret elements.  
This cannot work when <tt>T</tt> has a set of constructors and the default constructor is deleted from that set.
Solution: Add a new paragraph in <sref ref="[array.zero]"/>:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The unspecified internal structure of array for this case shall allow initializations like:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
array&lt;T, 0&gt; a = { };
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
and said initializations must be valid even when <tt>T</tt> is not default-constructible.
</p></blockquote>

<note>2012, Portland: Move to Open</note>
<p>
Some discussion to understand the issue, which is that implementations currently have freedom to implement
an empty <tt>array</tt> by holding a dummy element, and so might not support value initialization, which is
surprising when trying to construct an empty container.  However, this is not mandated, it is an unspecified
implementation detail.
</p>

<p>
Jeffrey points out that the implication of <sref ref="[array.overview]"/> is that this initialization syntax
must be supported by empty <tt>array</tt> objects already.  This is a surprising inference that was not
obvious to the room, but consensus is that the reading is accurate, so the proposed resolution is not necessary,
although the increased clarity may be useful.
</p>

<p>
Further observation is that the same clause effectively implies that <tt>T</tt> must always be DefaultConstructible,
regardless of <tt>N</tt> for the same reasons - as an <i>initializer-list</i> may not supply enough values, and the
remaining elements must all be value initialized.
</p>

<p>
Concern that we are dancing angels on the head of pin, and that relying on such subtle implications in wording is
not helpful.  We need a clarification of the text in this area, and await wording.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to N3376.</p>

<p>Add the following new paragraph between the current <sref ref="[array.zero]"/> p1 and p2:</p>

<blockquote><p>
-1- <tt>array</tt> shall provide support for the special case <tt>N == 0</tt>.
<p/>
<ins>-?- The unspecified internal structure of <tt>array</tt> for this case shall allow initializations like:</ins>
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
<ins>array&lt;T, 0&gt; a = { };</ins>
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
<ins>and said initializations must be valid even when <tt>T</tt> is not default-constructible.</ins>
<p/>
-2- In the case that <tt>N == 0</tt>, <tt>begin() == end() ==</tt> unique value. The return value of 
<tt>data()</tt> is unspecified.
<p/>
-3- The effect of calling <tt>front()</tt> or <tt>back()</tt> for a zero-sized array is undefined.
<p/>
-4- Member function <tt>swap()</tt> shall have a <em>noexcept-specification</em> which is equivalent to 
<tt>noexcept(true)</tt>.
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
