<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="446" status="NAD Editorial">
<title>Iterator equality between different containers</title>
<section><sref ref="[iterator.requirements]"/><sref ref="[container.requirements]"/></section>
<submitter>Andy Koenig</submitter>
<date>16 Dec 2003</date>

<discussion>
<p>
What requirements does the standard place on equality comparisons between
iterators that refer to elements of different containers.  For example, if
<tt>v1</tt> and <tt>v2</tt> are empty vectors, is <tt>v1.end() == v2.end()</tt> 
allowed to yield true? Is it allowed to throw an exception?
</p>

<p>
The standard appears to be silent on both questions.
</p>
<note>Sydney: The intention is that comparing two iterators from
different containers is undefined, but it's not clear if we say that,
or even whether it's something we should be saying in clause 23 or in
clause 24.  Intuitively we might want to say that equality is defined
only if one iterator is reachable from another, but figuring out how
to say it in any sensible way is a bit tricky: reachability is defined
in terms of equality, so we can't also define equality in terms of
reachability.
</note>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote><p>
Daniel volunteered to work on this.
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2009-09-20 Daniel provided wording.
</note>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
Leave as Open. Alisdair has volunteered to refine the wording.
</p></blockquote>

<note>
2010 Pittsburgh:  Moved to NAD Editorial.  Rationale added below.
</note>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>
Solved by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2010/n3066.html">N3066</a>.
</p>
</rationale>

<resolution>
<p>
Insert a new paragraph between <sref ref="[iterator.requirements]"/>/7+8:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
[..] The result of the application of functions in the library to invalid
ranges is undefined.
</p>

<p><ins>The result of directly or indirectly evaluating any comparison function
or the binary - operator with two iterator values as arguments that
were obtained
from two different ranges <tt>r1</tt> and <tt>r2</tt> (including their past-the-end values) which
are not subranges of one common range is undefined, unless explicitly
described otherwise.</ins>
</p>

</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
