<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="305" status="CD1">
<title>Default behavior of codecvt&lt;wchar_t, char, mbstate_t&gt;::length()</title>
<section><sref ref="[locale.codecvt.byname]"/></section>
<submitter>Howard Hinnant</submitter>
<date>24 Jan 2001</date>

<discussion>
<p>22.2.1.5/3 introduces codecvt in part with:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  codecvt&lt;wchar_t,char,mbstate_t&gt; converts between the native
  character sets for tiny and wide characters. Instantiations on
  mbstate_t perform conversion between encodings known to the library
  implementor.
</p></blockquote>

<p>But 22.2.1.5.2/10 describes do_length in part with:</p>

<blockquote><p>
  ... codecvt&lt;wchar_t, char, mbstate_t&gt; ... return(s) the lesser of max and 
  (from_end-from).
</p></blockquote>

<p>
The semantics of do_in and do_length are linked.  What one does must
be consistent with what the other does.  22.2.1.5/3 leads me to
believe that the vendor is allowed to choose the algorithm that
codecvt&lt;wchar_t,char,mbstate_t&gt;::do_in performs so that it makes
his customers happy on a given platform.  But 22.2.1.5.2/10 explicitly
says what codecvt&lt;wchar_t,char,mbstate_t&gt;::do_length must
return.  And thus indirectly specifies the algorithm that
codecvt&lt;wchar_t,char,mbstate_t&gt;::do_in must perform.  I believe
that this is not what was intended and is a defect.
</p>

<p>Discussion from the -lib reflector:

<br/>This proposal would have the effect of making the semantics of
all of the virtual functions in <tt>codecvt&lt;wchar_t, char,
mbstate_t&gt;</tt> implementation specified.  Is that what we want, or
do we want to mandate specific behavior for the base class virtuals
and leave the implementation specified behavior for the codecvt_byname
derived class?  The tradeoff is that former allows implementors to
write a base class that actually does something useful, while the
latter gives users a way to get known and specified---albeit
useless---behavior, and is consistent with the way the standard
handles other facets.  It is not clear what the original intention
was.</p>

<p>
Nathan has suggest a compromise: a character that is a widened version
of the characters in the basic execution character set must be
converted to a one-byte sequence, but there is no such requirement
for characters that are not part of the basic execution character set.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Change 22.2.1.5.2/5 from:
</p>
<p>
The instantiations required in Table 51 (lib.locale.category), namely
codecvt&lt;wchar_t,char,mbstate_t&gt; and
codecvt&lt;char,char,mbstate_t&gt;, store no characters. Stores no more
than (to_limit-to) destination elements. It always leaves the to_next
pointer pointing one beyond the last element successfully stored.
</p>
<p>
to:
</p>
<p>
Stores no more than (to_limit-to) destination elements, and leaves the
to_next pointer pointing one beyond the last element successfully
stored.  codecvt&lt;char,char,mbstate_t&gt; stores no characters.
</p>

<p>Change 22.2.1.5.2/10 from:</p>

<blockquote><p>
-10- Returns: (from_next-from) where from_next is the largest value in
the range [from,from_end] such that the sequence of values in the
range [from,from_next) represents max or fewer valid complete
characters of type internT. The instantiations required in Table 51
(21.1.1.1.1), namely codecvt&lt;wchar_t, char, mbstate_t&gt; and
codecvt&lt;char, char, mbstate_t&gt;, return the lesser of max and
(from_end-from).
</p></blockquote>

<p>to:</p>

<blockquote><p>
-10- Returns: (from_next-from) where from_next is the largest value in 
the range [from,from_end] such that the sequence of values in the range 
[from,from_next) represents max or fewer valid complete characters of 
type internT. The instantiation codecvt&lt;char, char, mbstate_t&gt; returns 
the lesser of max and (from_end-from). 
</p></blockquote>

<note>Redmond: Nathan suggested an alternative resolution: same as
above, but require that, in the default encoding, a character from the
basic execution character set would map to a single external
character.  The straw poll was 8-1 in favor of the proposed
resolution.</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The default encoding should be whatever users of a given platform
would expect to be the most natural.  This varies from platform to
platform.  In many cases there is a preexisting C library, and users
would expect the default encoding to be whatever C uses in the default
"C" locale.  We could impose a guarantee like the one Nathan suggested
(a character from the basic execution character set must map to a
single external character), but this would rule out important
encodings that are in common use: it would rule out JIS, for
example, and it would rule out a fixed-width encoding of UCS-4.</p>

<note>Cura&ccedil;ao: fixed rationale typo at the request of Ichiro Koshida;
&quot;shift-JIS&quot; changed to &quot;JIS&quot;.</note>

</rationale>

</issue>
