<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2062" status="Open">
<title>Effect contradictions w&#47;o no-throw guarantee of <tt>std::function</tt> swaps</title>
<section><sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/>, <sref ref="[func.wrap.func.mod]"/></section>
<submitter>Daniel Kr&uuml;gler</submitter>
<date>28 May 2011</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Howard Hinnant observed in reflector message c++std-lib-30841 that <sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/> 
makes the member swap <tt>noexcept</tt>, even though the non-member swap is not <tt>noexcept</tt>. 
<p/>
The latter was an outcome of the discussions during the Batavia meeting and the Madrid meeting 
involving LWG <iref ref="1349"/>, which seems to indicate that the remaining <tt>noexcept</tt> 
specifier at the member swap is incorrect and should be removed.
<p/>
But if we allow for a potentially throwing member swap of <tt>std::function</tt>, this causes 
another conflict with the exception specification for the following member function:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;class F&gt; function&amp; operator=(reference_wrapper&lt;F&gt; f) <span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bolder">noexcept</span>;
</pre><blockquote><p>
<i>Effects</i>: <tt>function(f).<span style="color:#C80000;font-weight:bolder">swap</span>(*this);</tt>
</p>
</blockquote></blockquote>
<p>
Note that in this example the sub-expression <tt>function(f)</tt> does not cause any problems,
because of the nothrow-guarantee given in <sref ref="[func.wrap.func.con]"/> p. 10. The problem
is located in the usage of the swap which could potentially throw given the general latitude. 
<p/>
So, either the Madrid meeting decision need to be revised (and both member and free swap of 
<tt>std::function</tt> should be noexcept), or this function needs to be adapted as well,
e.g. by taking the exception-specification away or by changing the semantics.
<p/>
One argument for "swap-may-throw" would be to allow for small-object optimization techniques
where the copy of the target may throw. But given the fact that the swap function has been guaranteed 
to be "Throws: Nothing" from TR1 on, it seems to me that that there would still be opportunities to 
perform small-object optimizations just restricted to the set of target copies that cannot throw. 
<p/>
In my opinion member swap of <tt>std::function</tt> has always been intended to be no-throw, because
otherwise there would be no good technical reason to specify the effects of several member 
functions in terms of the "construct-swap" idiom (There are three functions that are defined
this way), which provides the strong exception safety in this case. I suggest to enforce that both 
member swap and non-member swap of <tt>std::function</tt> are nothrow functions as it had been guaranteed 
since TR1 on.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>This wording is relative to the FDIS.</p>
<ol>
<li><p>Modify the header <tt>&lt;functional&gt;</tt> synopsis in <sref ref="[function.objects]"/> as indicated:</p>
<blockquote><pre>
namespace std {
  [&hellip;]

  template&lt;class R, class... ArgTypes&gt;
  void swap(function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp;, function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp;) <ins>noexcept</ins>;

  [&hellip;]
}
</pre></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Modify the class template <tt>function</tt> synopsis in <sref ref="[func.wrap.func]"/> as indicated:</p>
<blockquote><pre>
namespace std {
  [&hellip;]

  <i>// [func.wrap.func.alg], specialized algorithms:</i>
  template&lt;class R, class... ArgTypes&gt;
  void swap(function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp;, function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp;) <ins>noexcept</ins>;

  [&hellip;]
}
</pre></blockquote>
</li>

<li><p>Modify <sref ref="[func.wrap.func.alg]"/> as indicated:</p>
<blockquote><pre>
template&lt;class R, class... ArgTypes&gt;
void swap(function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp; f1, function&lt;R(ArgTypes...)&gt;&amp; f2) <ins>noexcept</ins>;
</pre><blockquote><p>
-1- <i>Effects</i>: <tt>f1.swap(f2);</tt>
</p></blockquote></blockquote>
</li>

</ol>

</resolution>

</issue>
