<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="325" status="CD1">
<title>Misleading text in moneypunct&lt;&gt;::do_grouping</title>
<section><sref ref="[locale.moneypunct.virtuals]"/></section>
<submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
<date>02 Jul 2001</date>

<discussion>
<p>The Returns clause in 22.2.6.3.2, p3 says about
moneypunct&lt;charT&gt;::do_grouping()
</p>

<blockquote><p>
    Returns: A pattern defined identically as the result of
    numpunct&lt;charT&gt;::do_grouping().241)
</p></blockquote>

<p>Footnote 241 then reads</p>

<blockquote><p>
    This is most commonly the value "\003" (not "3").
</p></blockquote>

<p>
The returns clause seems to imply that the two member functions must
return an identical value which in reality may or may not be true,
since the facets are usually implemented in terms of struct std::lconv
and return the value of the grouping and mon_grouping, respectively.
The footnote also implies that the member function of the moneypunct
facet (rather than the overridden virtual functions in moneypunct_byname)
most commonly return "\003", which contradicts the C standard which
specifies the value of "" for the (most common) C locale.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>Replace the text in Returns clause in 22.2.6.3.2, p3 with the following:</p>

<blockquote><p>
    Returns: A pattern defined identically as, but not necessarily
    equal to, the result of numpunct&lt;charT&gt;::do_grouping().241)
</p></blockquote>

<p>and replace the text in Footnote 241 with the following:</p>

<blockquote><p>
    To specify grouping by 3s the value is "\003", not "3".
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>
The fundamental problem is that the description of the locale facet
virtuals serves two purposes: describing the behavior of the base
class, and describing the meaning of and constraints on the behavior
in arbitrary derived classes.  The new wording makes that separation a
little bit clearer.  The footnote (which is nonnormative) is not
supposed to say what the grouping is in the "C" locale or in any other
locale. It is just a reminder that the values are interpreted as small
integers, not ASCII characters.
</p>
</rationale>
</issue>
