<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="786" status="NAD Editorial">
<title>Thread library timed waits, UTC and monotonic clocks</title>
<section><sref ref="[time]"/></section>
<submitter>Christopher Kohlhoff, Jeff Garland</submitter>
<date>3 Feb 2008</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The draft C++0x thread library requires that the time points of type
<tt>system_time</tt> and returned by <tt>get_system_time()</tt> represent Coordinated
Universal Time (UTC) (section <sref ref="[datetime.system]"/>). This can lead to
surprising behavior when a library user performs a duration-based wait,
such as <tt>condition_variable::timed_wait()</tt>. A complete explanation of the
problem may be found in the
<a href="http://www.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/009695399/xrat/xsh_chap02.html#tag_03_02_08_19">Rationale for the Monotonic Clock</a>
section in POSIX, but in summary:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
Operations such as <tt>condition_variable::timed_wait()</tt> (and its POSIX
equivalent, <tt>pthread_cond_timedwait()</tt>) are specified using absolute times
to address the problem of spurious wakeups.
</li>

<li>
The typical use of the timed wait operations is to perform a relative
wait. This may be achieved by first calculating an absolute time as the
sum of the current time and the desired duration. In fact, the C++0x
thread library includes duration-based overloads of
<tt>condition_variable::timed_wait()</tt> that behave as if by calling the
corresponding absolute time overload with a time point value of
<tt>get_system_time() + rel_time</tt>.
</li>

<li>
A UTC clock may be affected by changes to the system time, such as
synchronization with an external source, leap seconds, or manual changes
to the clock.
</li>

<li>
Should the clock change during a timed wait operation, the actual
duration of the wait will not be the expected length. For example, a
user may intend a timed wait of one second duration but, due to an
adjustment of the system clock backwards by a minute, the wait instead
takes 61 seconds.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
POSIX solves the problem by introducing a new monotonic clock, which is
unaffected by changes to the system time. When a condition variable is
initialized, the user may specify whether the monotonic clock is to be
used. (It is worth noting that on POSIX systems it is not possible to
use <tt>condition_variable::native_handle()</tt> to access this facility, since
the desired clock type must be specified during construction of the
condition variable object.)
</p>

<p>
In the context of the C++0x thread library, there are added dimensions
to the problem due to the need to support platforms other than POSIX:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
Some environments (such as embedded systems) do not have a UTC clock, but do have a monotonic clock.
</li>

<li>
Some environments do not have a monotonic clock, but do have a UTC clock.
</li>

<li>
The Microsoft Windows API's synchronization functions use relative
timeouts based on an implied monotonic clock. A program that switches
from the Windows API to the C++0x thread library will now find itself
susceptible to clock changes.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
One possible minimal solution:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
Strike normative references to UTC and an epoch based on 1970-01-01.
</li>

<li>
Make the semantics of <tt>system_time</tt> and <tt>get_system_time()</tt>
implementation-defined (i.e standard library implementors may choose the
appropriate underlying clock based on the capabilities of the target
platform).
</li>

<li>
Add a non-normative note encouraging use of a monotonic clock.
</li>

<li>
Remove <tt>system_time::seconds_since_epoch()</tt>.
</li>

<li>
Change the constructor <tt>explicit system_time(time_t secs, nanoseconds ns
= 0)</tt> to <tt>explicit system_time(nanoseconds ns)</tt>.
</li>
</ul>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
Addressed by
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2661.html">N2661: A Foundation to Sleep On</a>.
</rationale>

</issue>
