<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="951" status="Ready">
<title>Various threading bugs #1</title>
<section><sref ref="[time.traits.is_fp]"/></section>
<submitter>Pete Becker</submitter>
<date>7 Jan 2009</date>

<discussion>

<p>
Related to <iref ref="953"/>.
</p>

<p>
<sref ref="[time.traits.is_fp]"/> says that the type <tt>Rep</tt> "is
assumed to be ... a class emulating an integral type." What are the
requirements for such a type?
</p>
<note>
2009-05-10 Howard adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<tt>IntegralLike</tt>.
</blockquote>

<note>
Batavia (2009-05):
</note>
<blockquote>
<p>
As with issue <iref ref="953"/>,
we recommend this issue be addressed in the context of providing concepts for the entire <tt>thread</tt> header.
</p>
<p>
We look forward to proposed wording.
</p>
<p>
Move to Open.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-08-01 Howard adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
I have surveyed all clauses of <sref ref="[time.traits.duration_values]"/>,
<sref ref="[time.traits.specializations]"/> and <sref ref="[time.duration]"/>.
I can not find any clause which involves the use of a <tt>duration::rep</tt> type
where the requirements on the <tt>rep</tt> type are not clearly spelled out.
These requirements were carefully crafted to allow any arithmetic type, or
any user-defined type emulating an arithmetic type.
</p>

<p>
Indeed, <tt>treat_as_floating_point</tt>
becomes completely superfluous if <tt>duration::rep</tt> can never be a class type.
</p>

<p>
There will be some <tt>Rep</tt> types which will not meet the requirements of
<em>every</em> <tt>duration</tt> operation.  This is no different than the fact
that <tt>vector&lt;T&gt;</tt> can easily be used for types <tt>T</tt> which are
not <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt>, even though some members of <tt>vector&lt;T&gt;</tt>
require <tt>T</tt> to be <tt>DefaultConstructible</tt>.  This is why the requirements
on <tt>Rep</tt> are specified for each operation individually.
</p>

<p>
In <sref ref="[time.traits.is_fp]"/> p1:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class Rep&gt; struct treat_as_floating_point 
  : is_floating_point&lt;Rep&gt; { };
</pre>

<blockquote>
The <tt>duration</tt> template uses the <tt>treat_as_floating_point</tt> trait to help
determine if a <tt>duration</tt> object can be converted to another <tt>duration</tt>
with a different tick period. If <tt>treat_as_floating_point&lt;Rep&gt;::value</tt> is
<tt>true</tt>, then <tt>Rep</tt> is a floating-point type and implicit conversions are
allowed among <tt>duration</tt>s. Otherwise, the implicit convertibility depends
on the tick periods of the <tt>duration</tt>s. If <tt>Rep</tt> is <u>a class type which
emulates a floating-point type</u>, the author of <tt>Rep</tt> can specialize
<tt>treat_as_floating_point</tt> so that <tt>duration</tt> will treat this <tt>Rep</tt> as if it
were a floating-point type. Otherwise <tt>Rep</tt> is assumed to be an integral
type or <u>a class emulating an integral type</u>.
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>
The phrases "a class type which emulates a floating-point type" and
"a class emulating an integral type" are clarifying phrases which refer to
the summation of all the requirements on the <tt>Rep</tt> type specified in
detail elsewhere (and <em>should not</em> be repeated here).
</p>

<p>
This specification has been implemented, now multiple times, and the experience
has been favorable.  The current specification clearly specifies the requirements
at each point of use (though I'd be happy to fix any place I may have missed,
but none has been pointed out).
</p>

<p>
I am amenable to improved wording of this paragraph (and any others), but do not have any
suggestions for improved wording at this time.  I am <em>strongly</em> opposed to
changes which would significantly alter the semantics of the
specification under <sref ref="[time]"/> without firmly grounded and
documented rationale, example implementation, testing, and user
experience which relates a positive experience.
</p>

<p>
I recommend NAD unless someone wants to produce some clarifying wording.
</p>
</blockquote>

<note>
2009-10 Santa Cruz:
</note>

<blockquote>
Stefanus to provide wording to turn this into a note.
</blockquote>

<note>
2010-02-11 Stefanus provided wording.
</note>


<note>
2010 Rapperswil:
</note>

<blockquote>
Move to Ready.
</blockquote>


</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Change <sref ref="[time.traits.is_fp]"/>/1:
</p>

<blockquote>
1 The <tt>duration</tt> template uses the <tt>treat_as_floating_point</tt> trait
to help determine if a <tt>duration</tt> object can be converted to another
<tt>duration</tt> with a different tick period. If
<tt>treat_as_floating_point&lt;Rep&gt;::value</tt> is <tt>true</tt>, then
<del><tt>Rep</tt> is a floating-point type and</del> implicit conversions are allowed among
<tt>duration</tt>s. Otherwise, the implicit convertibility depends on the tick
periods of the <tt>duration</tt>s. <del>If <tt>Rep</tt> is a class type which
emulates a floating-point type, the author of <tt>Rep</tt> can specialize
<tt>treat_as_floating_point</tt> so that duration will treat this <tt>Rep</tt>
as if it were a floating-point type. Otherwise <tt>Rep</tt> is assumed to be an
integral type or a class emulating an integral type.</del>
<ins>[<i>Note:</i> The intention of this trait is to indicate whether a given
class behaves like a floating point type, and thus allows division of one value
by another with acceptable loss of precision. If
<tt>treat_as_floating_point&lt;Rep&gt;::value</tt> is <tt>false</tt>,
<tt>Rep</tt> will be treated as if it behaved like an integral type for the
purpose of these conversions. &mdash; <i>end note</i>]</ins>
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
