<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="813" status="CD1">
<title>"empty" undefined for <tt>shared_ptr</tt></title>
<section><sref ref="[util.smartptr.shared]"/></section>
<submitter>Matt Austern</submitter>
<date>26 Feb 2008</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Several places in <sref ref="[util.smartptr.shared]"/> refer to an "empty" <tt>shared_ptr</tt>.
However, that term is nowhere defined. The closest thing we have to a
definition is that the default constructor creates an empty <tt>shared_ptr</tt>
and that a copy of a default-constructed <tt>shared_ptr</tt> is empty. Are any
other <tt>shared_ptr</tt>s empty? For example, is <tt>shared_ptr((T*) 0)</tt> empty? What
are the properties of an empty <tt>shared_ptr</tt>? We should either clarify this
term or stop using it.
</p>
<p>
One reason it's not good enough to leave this term up to the reader's
intuition is that, in light of
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/JTC1/sc22/WG21/docs/papers/2007/n2351.htm">N2351</a>
and issue <iref ref="711"/>, most readers'
intuitive understanding is likely to be wrong. Intuitively one might
expect that an empty <tt>shared_ptr</tt> is one that doesn't store a pointer,
but, whatever the definition is, that isn't it.
</p>

<note>
Peter adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
Or, what is an "empty" <tt>shared_ptr</tt>?
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>
Are any other <tt>shared_ptrs</tt> empty?
</p>
<p>
Yes. Whether a given <tt>shared_ptr</tt> instance is empty or not is (*)
completely specified by the last mutating operation on that instance.
Give me an example and I'll tell you whether the <tt>shared_ptr</tt> is empty or
not.
</p>
<blockquote><p>
(*) If it isn't, this is a legitimate defect.
</p></blockquote>
</li>

<li>
<p>
For example, is <tt>shared_ptr((T*) 0)</tt> empty?
</p>
<p>
No. If it were empty, it would have a <tt>use_count()</tt> of 0, whereas it is
specified to have an <tt>use_count()</tt> of 1.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
What are the properties of an empty <tt>shared_ptr</tt>?
</p>
<p>
The properties of an empty <tt>shared_ptr</tt> can be derived from the
specification. One example is that its destructor is a no-op. Another is
that its <tt>use_count()</tt> returns 0. I can enumerate the full list if you
really like.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
We should either clarify this term or stop using it.
</p>
<p>
I don't agree with the imperative tone
</p>
<p>
A clarification would be either a no-op - if it doesn't contradict the
existing wording - or a big mistake if it does.
</p>
<p>
I agree that a clarification that is formally a no-op may add value.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
However, that term is nowhere defined.
</p>
<p>
Terms can be useful without a definition. Consider the following
simplistic example. We have a type <tt>X</tt> with the following operations
defined:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
X x;
X x2(x);
X f(X x);
X g(X x1, X x2);
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
A default-constructed value is green.<br/>
A copy has the same color as the original.<br/>
<tt>f(x)</tt> returns a red value if the argument is green, a green value otherwise.<br/>
<tt>g(x1,x2)</tt> returns a green value if the arguments are of the same color, a red value otherwise.
</p>

<p>
Given these definitions, you can determine the color of every instance
of type <tt>X</tt>, even if you have absolutely no idea what green and red mean.
</p>

<p>
Green and red are "nowhere defined" and completely defined at the same time.
</p>
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Alisdair's wording is fine.
</p>
</blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Append the following sentance to <sref ref="[util.smartptr.shared]"/>
</p>
<blockquote><p>
The <code>shared_ptr</code> class template stores a pointer, usually obtained
via <code>new</code>. <code>shared_ptr</code> implements semantics of
shared ownership; the last remaining owner of the pointer is responsible for
destroying the object, or otherwise releasing  the resources associated with
the stored pointer. <ins>A <code>shared_ptr</code> object that does not own
a pointer is said to be <i>empty</i>.</ins>
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
