<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="877" status="NAD Future">
   <title>to <tt>throw()</tt> or to <i>Throw:</i> Nothing.</title>
   <section><sref ref="[library]"/></section>
   <submitter>Martin Sebor</submitter>
   <date>23 Aug 2008</date>
   <discussion>
       <p>

Recent changes to
the <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2008/n2691.pdf">working
draft</a> have introduced a gratuitous inconsistency with the C++ 2003
version of the specification with respect to exception guarantees
provided by standard functions. While the C++ 2003 standard
consistenly uses the empty exception specification, <tt>throw()</tt>,
to declare functions that are guaranteed not to throw exceptions, the
current working draft contains a number of "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing."
clause to specify essentially the same requirement. The difference
between the two approaches is that the former specifies the behavior
of programs that violate the requirement (<tt>std::unexpected()</tt>
is called) while the latter leaves the behavior undefined.

       </p>
       <p>

A survey of the working draft reveals that there are a total of 209
occurrences of <tt>throw()</tt> in the library portion of the spec,
the majority in clause 18, a couple (literally) in 19, a handful in
20, a bunch in 22, four in 24, one in 27, and about a dozen in D.9.

       </p>
       <p>

There are also 203 occurrences of "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing." scattered
throughout the spec.

       </p>
       <p>

While sometimes there are good reasons to use the "<i>Throws:</i>
Nothing."  approach rather than making use of <tt>throw()</tt>, these
reasons do not apply in most of the cases where this new clause has
been introduced and the empty exception specification would be a
better approach.

       </p>
       <p>

First, functions declared with the empty exception specification
permit compilers to generate better code for calls to such
functions. In some cases, the compiler might even be able to eliminate
whole chunks of user-written code when instantiating a generic
template on a type whose operations invoked from the template
specialization are known not to throw. The prototypical example are
the <tt>std::uninitialized_copy()</tt>
and <tt>std::uninitialized_fill()</tt> algorithms where the
entire <tt>catch(...)</tt> block can be optimized away.

       </p>
       <p>

For example, given the following definition of
the <tt>std::uninitialized_copy</tt> function template and a
user-defined type <tt>SomeType</tt>:

       </p>
       <blockquote>
           <pre>
template &lt;class InputIterator, class ForwardIterator&gt;
ForwardIterator
uninitialized_copy (InputIterator first, InputIterator last, ForwardIterator res)
{
   typedef iterator_traits&lt;ForwardIterator&gt;::value_type ValueType;

   ForwardIterator start = res;

   try {
       for (; first != last; ++first, ++res)
           ::new (&amp;*res) ValueType (*first);
   }
   catch (...) {
       for (; start != res; --start)
           (&amp;*start)->~ValueType ();
       throw;
   }
   return res;
}

struct SomeType {
   SomeType (const SomeType&amp;) <ins>throw ()</ins>;
}</pre>
       </blockquote>
       <p>

compilers are able to emit the following efficient specialization
of <tt>std::uninitialized_copy&lt;const SomeType*, SomeType*&gt;</tt>
(note that the <tt>catch</tt> block has been optimized away):

       </p>
       <blockquote>
           <pre>
template &lt;&gt; SomeType*
uninitialized_copy (const SomeType *first, const SomeType *last, SomeType *res)
{
   for (; first != last; ++first, ++res)
       ::new (res) SomeType (*first);

   return res;
}</pre>
       </blockquote>
       <p>

Another general example is default constructors which, when decorated
with <tt>throw()</tt>, allow the compiler to eliminate the
implicit <tt>try</tt> and <tt>catch</tt> blocks that it otherwise must
emit around each the invocation of the constructor
in <i>new-expressions</i>.

       </p>
       <p>

For example, given the following definitions of
class <tt>MayThrow</tt> and <tt>WontThrow</tt> and the two
statements below:

       </p>
       <blockquote>
           <pre>
struct MayThrow {
   MayThrow ();
};

struct WontThrow {
   WontThrow () <ins>throw ()</ins>;
};

MayThrow  *a = new MayThrow [N];
WontThrow *b = new WontThrow [N];</pre>

       </blockquote>
       <p>

the compiler generates the following code for the first statement:

       </p>
       <blockquote>
           <pre>
MayThrow *a;
{
   MayThrow *first = operator new[] (N * sizeof (*a));
   MayThrow *last  = first + N;
   MayThrow *next  = first;
   try {
       for ( ; next != last; ++next)
           new (next) MayThrow;
   }
   catch (...) {
       for ( ; first != first; --next)
           next->~MayThrow ();
       operator delete[] (first);
       throw;
   }
   a = first;
}</pre>
       </blockquote>
       <p>

but it is can generate much more compact code for the second statement:

       </p>
       <blockquote>
           <pre>
WontThrow *b    = operator new[] (N * sizeof (*b));
WontThrow *last = b + N;
for (WontThrow *next = b; next != last; ++next)
   new (next) WontThrow;
</pre>
       </blockquote>
       <p>

Second, in order for users to get the maximum benefit out of the new
<tt>std::has_nothrow_xxx</tt> traits when using standard library types
it will be important for implementations to decorate all non throwing
copy constructors and assignment operators with <tt>throw()</tt>. Note
that while an optimizer may be able to tell whether a function without
an explicit exception specification can throw or not based on its
definition, it can only do so when it can see the source code of the
definition. When it can't it must assume that the function may
throw. To prevent violating the One Definition Rule,
the <tt>std::has_nothrow_xxx</tt> trait must return the most
pessimistic guess across all translation units in the program, meaning
that <tt>std::has_nothrow_xxx&lt;T&gt;::value</tt> must evaluate to
<tt>false</tt> for any <tt>T</tt> whose <tt>xxx</tt>
(where <tt>xxx</tt> is default or copy ctor, or assignment operator)
is defined out-of-line.

       </p>
       <p>

<b>Counterarguments:</b>

       </p>
       <p>

During the discussion of this issue
on <a href="mailto:c++std-lib@accu.org">c++std-lib@accu.org</a>
(starting with post <tt>c++std-lib-21950</tt>) the following arguments
in favor of the "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing." style have been made.

       </p>
         <ol>
           <li>

Decorating functions that cannot throw with the empty exception
specification can cause the compiler to generate suboptimal code for
the implementation of the function when it calls other functions that
aren't known to the compiler not to throw (i.e., that aren't decorated
with <tt>throw()</tt> even if they don't actually throw). This is a
common situation when the called function is a C or POSIX function.

           </li>
           <li>

Alternate, proprietary mechanisms exist (such as
GCC <a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc-4.3.0/gcc/Function-Attributes.html#index-g_t_0040code_007bnothrow_007d-function-attribute-2160"><tt>__attribute__((nothrow))</tt></a>
or Visual
C++ <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/49147z04(VS.80).aspx"><tt>__declspec(nothrow)</tt></a>)
that let implementers mark up non-throwing functions, often without
the penalty mentioned in (1) above. The C++ standard shouldn't
preclude the use of these potentially more efficient mechanisms.

           </li>
           <li>

There are functions, especially function templates, that invoke
user-defined functions that may or may not be
declared <tt>throw()</tt>. Declaring such functions with the empty
exception specification will cause compilers to generate suboptimal
code when the user-defined function isn't also declared not to throw.

           </li>
        </ol>
       <p>

The answer to point (1) above is that implementers can (and some have)
declare functions with <tt>throw()</tt> to indicate to the compiler
that calls to the function can safely be assumed not to throw in order
to allow it to generate efficient code at the call site without also
having to define the functions the same way and causing the compiler
to generate suboptimal code for the function definition. That is, the
function is declared with <tt>throw()</tt> in a header but it's
defined without it in the source file. The <tt>throw()</tt>
declaration is suppressed when compiling the definition to avoid
compiler errors. This technique, while strictly speaking no permitted
by the language, is safe and has been employed in practice. For
example, the GNU C library takes this approach. Microsoft Visual C++
takes a similar approach by simply assuming that no function with C
language linkage can throw an exception unless it's explicitly
declared to do so using the language extension <tt>throw(...)</tt>.

       </p>
       <p>

Our answer to point (2) above is that there is no existing practice
where C++ Standard Library implementers have opted to make use of the
proprietary mechanisms to declare functions that don't throw. The
language provides a mechanism specifically designed for this
purpose. Avoiding its use in the specification itself in favor of
proprietary mechanisms defeats the purpose of the feature. In
addition, making use of the empty exception specification
inconsistently, in some areas of the standard, while conspicuously
avoiding it and making use of the "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing." form in
others is confusing to users.

       </p>
       <p>

The answer to point (3) is simply to exercise caution when declaring
functions and especially function templates with the empty exception
specification. Functions that required not to throw but that may call
back into user code are poor candidates for the empty exception
specification and should instead be specified using "<i>Throws:</i>
Nothing." clause.

      </p>

<note>
2009-07 Frankfurt
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
We need someone to do an extensive review.
</p>
<p>
NAD Future.
</p>
</blockquote>

   </discussion>
   <resolution>
       <p>

We propose two possible solutions. Our recommendation is to adopt
Option 1 below.

       </p>
       <p>

<b>Option 1:</b>

       </p>
       <p>

Except for functions or function templates that make calls back to
user-defined functions that may not be declared <tt>throw()</tt>
replace all occurrences of the "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing." clause with
the empty exception specification. Functions that are required not to
throw but that make calls back to user code should be specified to
"<i>Throw:</i> Nothing."

       </p>
       <p>

<b>Option 2:</b>

       </p>
       <p>

For consistency, replace all occurrences of the empty exception
specification with a "<i>Throws:</i> Nothing." clause.

       </p>
   </resolution>
</issue>
