<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="495" status="CD1">
<title>Clause 22 template parameter requirements</title>
<section><sref ref="[localization]"/></section>
<submitter>Beman Dawes</submitter>
<date>10 Jan 2005</date>

<discussion>
<p>It appears that there are no requirements specified for many of the
template parameters in clause 22. It looks like this issue has never
come up, except perhaps for Facet.</p>

<p>Clause 22 isn't even listed in 17.3.2.1 [lib.type.descriptions],
either, which is the wording that allows requirements on template
parameters to be identified by name.</p>

<p>So one issue is that 17.3.2.1 [lib.type.descriptions] Should be
changed to cover clause 22. A better change, which will cover us in
the future, would be to say that it applies to all the library
clauses. Then if a template gets added to any library clause we are
covered.</p>

<p>charT, InputIterator, and other names with requirements defined
elsewhere are fine, assuming the 17.3.2.1 [lib.type.descriptions] fix.
But there are a few template arguments names which I don't think have
requirements given elsewhere:</p>

<ul>
<li>internT and externT.  The fix is to add wording saying that internT
and externT must meet the same requirements as template arguments
named charT.</li>

<li>stateT.  I'm not sure about this one. There already is some wording,
but it seems a bit vague.</li>

<li>Intl.  [lib.locale.moneypunct.byname] The fix for this one is to
rename "Intl" to "International". The name is important because other
text identifies the requirements for the name International but not
for Intl.</li>
</ul></discussion>

<resolution>
<p>Change <sref ref="[type.descriptions]"/>, paragraph 1, from:</p>
<blockquote><p>
The Requirements subclauses may describe names that are used to
specify constraints on template arguments.153) These names are used in
clauses 20, 23, 25, and 26 to describe the types that may be supplied
as arguments by a C++ program when instantiating template components
from the library. 
</p></blockquote>
<p>to:</p>
<blockquote><p>
The Requirements subclauses may describe names that are used to
specify constraints on template arguments.153) These names are used in
library clauses to describe the types that may be supplied as
arguments by a C++ program when instantiating template components from
the library.
</p></blockquote>

<p>In the front matter of class 22, locales, add:</p>
<blockquote><p>
Template parameter types internT and externT shall meet the
requirements of charT (described in <sref ref="[strings]"/>).
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>
 Again, a blanket clause isn't blanket enough. Also, we've got a
 couple of names that we don't have blanket requirement statements
 for. The only issue is what to do about stateT. This wording is
 thin, but probably adequate.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
