<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1202" status="NAD">
<title><tt>integral_constant</tt> needs a spring clean</title>
<section><sref ref="[meta.help]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>5 Sep 2009</date>

<discussion>
<p>
The specification of <tt>integral_constant</tt> has been inherited
essentially unchanged from TR1:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class T, T v&gt;
struct integral_constant {
  static const T value = v;
  typedef T value_type;
  typedef integral_constant&lt;T,v&gt; type;
};
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
In light of 0x language changes there are several things we might
consider changing, notably the form of specification for value.
</p>

<p>
The current form requires a static data member have storage allocated
for it, where we could now implement without this using the new enum
syntax:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class T, T v&gt;
struct integral_constant {
  <b>enum : T { value = v };</b>
  typedef T value_type;
  typedef integral_constant type;
};
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
The effective difference between these two implementation is:
</p>

<ol style="list-style-type:lower-roman">
<li>
No requirement to allocate storage for data member (which we hope but do
not guarantee compilers strip today)
</li>

<li>
You can no longer take the address of the constant as
<tt>&amp;integral_constant&lt;T,v&gt;::value;</tt>
</li>
</ol>

<p>
Also note the editorial change to drop the explicit qualification of
<tt>integral_constant</tt> in the <tt>typedef type</tt>.  This makes it quite clear we
mean the current instantiation, and cannot be mistaken for a recursive
metaprogram.
</p>

<p>
Even if we don't mandate this implementation, it would be nice to give
vendors freedom under QoI to choose their preferred representation.
</p>

<p>
The other side of this issue is if we choose to retain the static
constant form.  In that case we should go further and insist on
<tt>constexpr</tt>, much like we did throughout <tt>numeric_limits</tt>:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
template &lt;class T, T v&gt;
struct integral_constant {
  static <b>constexpr</b> T value = v;
  typedef T value_type;
  typedef integral_constant type;
};
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
[Footnote] It turns out <tt>constexpr</tt> is part of the Tentatively Ready
resolution for <iref ref="1019"/>.  I don't want to interfere with that issue, but
would like a new issue to consider if the fixed-base enum implementation
should be allowed.
</p>

<note>
2009-09-05 Daniel adds:
</note>

<blockquote>
<p>
I think that the suggested resolution is incomplete and
may have some possible unwanted side-effects. To understand
why, note that <tt>integral_constant</tt> is <em>completely</em> specified
by code in <sref ref="[meta.help]"/>. While this is usually considered
as a good thing, let me give a possible user-defined
specialization that would break given the suggested changes:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
enum NodeColor { Red, Black };

std::integral_constant&lt;NodeColor, Red&gt; red;
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
The reason why that breaks is due to the fact that
current core language rules does only allow integral
types as enum-bases, see <sref ref="[dcl.enum]"/>/2.
</p>

<p>
So, I think that we cannot leave the implementation the
freedom to decide which way they would like to provide
the implementation, because that is easily user-visible
(I don't speak of addresses, but of instantiation errors),
therefore if applied, this should be either specified or
wording must be added that gives a note about this
freedom of implementation.
</p>

<p>
Another possible disadvantage seems to me that user-expectations
are easy to disappoint if they see a failure
of the test
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
assert(typeid(std::integral_constant&lt;int, 0&gt;::value) == typeid(int));
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
or of
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
static_assert(std::is_same&lt;decltype(std::integral_constant&lt;int, 0&gt;::value), const int&gt;::value, "Bad library");
</pre></blockquote>

</blockquote>

<note>
2010-01-14 Moved to Tentatively NAD after 5 positive votes on c++std-lib.
</note>

</discussion>

<rationale>
<p>
We think that the suggested resolution is incomplete and may have some possible
unwanted side-effects.  (see Daniel's 2009-09-05 comment for details).
</p>
</rationale>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
