<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1521" status="NAD Future">
<title>Requirements on internal pointer representations in containers</title>
<section><sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/></section>
<submitter>Mike Spertus</submitter>
<date>16 Oct 2010</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses US-104, US-141</b></p>

<p>
The standard doesn't say that containers should use abstract pointer 
types internally. Both Howard and Pablo agree that this is the intent. 
Further, it is necessary for containers to be stored, for example, in 
shared memory with an interprocess allocator (the type of scenario that 
allocators are intended to support).
</p>
<p>
In spite of the (possible) agreement on intent, it is necessary to make 
this explicit:
</p>
<p>
An implementations may like to store the result of dereferencing the 
pointer (which is a raw reference) as an optimization, but that prevents 
the data structure from being put in shared memory, etc. In fact, a 
container could store raw references to the allocator, which would be a 
little weird but conforming as long as it has one by-value copy. 
Furthermore, pointers to locales, ctypes, etc. may be there, which also 
prevents the data structure from being put in shared memory, so we 
should make explicit that a container does not store raw pointers or 
references at all.
</p>

<note>
Pre-batavia
</note>
<p>
This issue is being opened as part of the response to NB comments US-104/141. 
See paper <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2010/n3171.pdf">N3171</a>
in the pre-Batavia mailing. 
</p>

<note>2011-03-23 Madrid meeting</note>

<p>Deferred</p>

<note>
2011 Batavia
</note>

<p>
This may be an issue, but it is not clear.  We want to gain a few years experience
with the C++11 allocator model to see if this is already implied by the existing
specification.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Add to the end of <sref ref="[container.requirements.general]"/> p. 8:
</p>
<blockquote><p>
[..] In all container types defined in this Clause, the member <tt>get_allocator()</tt> returns 
a copy of the allocator used to construct the container or, if that allocator has been replaced, 
a copy of the most recent replacement. <ins>The container may not store internal objects whose 
types are of the form  <tt>T *</tt> or <tt>T &amp;</tt> except insofar as they are part of the 
item type or members.</ins>
</p></blockquote>
</resolution>

</issue>
