<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="511" status="NAD">
<title>Input_type for binomial_distribution</title>
<section><sref ref="[rand.dist]"/><sref ref="[tr.rand.dist.bin]"/></section>
<submitter>Walter Brown</submitter>
<date>3 Jul 2005</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Unlike all other distributions in TR1, this binomial_distribution has an
implementation-defined  input_type.  We believe this is an unfortunate choice,
because it hinders users from writing portable code.  It also hinders the
writing of compliance tests.  We recommend instead:
</p>
<blockquote><pre>
typedef  RealType  input_type;
</pre></blockquote>
<p>
While this choice is somewhat arbitrary (as it was for some of the other
distributions), we make  this particular choice because (unlike all other
distributions) otherwise this template would not publish its RealType
argument and so users could not write generic code that accessed this
second template parameter.  In this respect, the choice is consistent with
the other distributions in  TR1. 
</p>
<p>
We have two reasons for recommending that a real type be specified instead.
One reason is  based specifically on characteristics of binomial distribution
implementations, while the other is based on mathematical characteristics of
probability distribution functions in general.
</p>
<p>
Implementations of binomial distributions commonly use Stirling approximations
for values in certain ranges.  It is far more natural to use real values to
represent these approximations than it would be to use integral values to do
so.  In other ranges, implementations reply on the Bernoulli  distribution to
obtain values.  While TR1's bernoulli_distribution::input_type is specified as
int, we believe this would be better specified as double.
</p>
<p>
This brings us to our main point:  The notion of a random distribution rests
on the notion of a cumulative distribution function, which in turn mathematically
depends on a continuous dependent variable.  Indeed, such a distribution function
would be meaningless if it depended on  discrete values such as integers - and this
remains true even if the distribution function were to take discrete steps.
</p>
<p>
Although this note is specifically about binomial_distribution::input_type,
we intend to recommend that all of the random distributions input_types be
specified as a real type (either a RealType template parameter, or double,
as appropriate).
</p>
<p>
Of the nine distributions in TR1, four already have this characteristic
(uniform_real, exponential_distribution, normal_distribution, and
gamma_distribution).  We have already argued the case for the binomial the
remaining four distributions.
</p>
<p>
In the case of uniform_int, we believe that the calculations to produce an
integer result in a  specified range from an integer in a different specified
range is best done using real arithmetic.  This is because it involves a
product, one of whose terms is the ratio of the extents of the two ranges.
Without real arithmetic, the results become less uniform: some numbers become
more  (or less) probable that they should be.  This is, of course, undesireable
behavior in a uniform distribution.
</p>
<p>
Finally, we believe that in the case of the bernoulli_distribution (briefly
mentioned earlier), as well as the cases of the geometric_distribution and the
poisson_distribution, it would be far more natural to have a real input_type.
This is because the most natural computation involves the  random number
delivered and the distribution's parameter p (in the case of bernoulli_distribution,
for example, the computation is a comparison against p), and p is already specified
in each case as having some real type.
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<blockquote><pre>
typedef  RealType  input_type;
</pre></blockquote>

<note>
Berlin:  Moved to NAD.  N1932 makes this moot: the input_type template parameter has been
eliminated.
</note>
</resolution>

</issue>
