<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="388" status="NAD">
<title>Use of <tt>complex</tt> as a key in associative containers</title>
<section><sref ref="[complex.numbers]"/></section>
<submitter>Gabriel Dos Reis</submitter>
<date>8 Nov 2002</date>

<discussion>
<p>
Practice with <tt>std::complex&lt;&gt;</tt> and the associative containers
occasionally reveals artificial and distracting issues with constructs
resembling: <tt>std::set&lt;std::complex&lt;double&gt; &gt; s;</tt>
</p>

<p>
The main reason for the above to fail is the absence of an appropriate
definition for <tt>std::less&lt;std::complex&lt;T&gt; &gt;</tt>. That in turn comes from
the definition of the primary template <tt>std::less&lt;&gt;</tt> in terms of
<tt>operator&lt;</tt>.
</p>

<p>
The usual argument goes as follows: Since there is no ordering over
the complex field compatible with field operations it makes little
sense to define a function <tt>operator&lt;</tt> operating on the datatype
<tt>std::complex&lt;T&gt;</tt>.  That is fine. However, that reasoning does not carry
over to <tt>std::less&lt;T&gt;</tt> which is used, among other things, by associative
containers as an ordering useful to meet complexity requirements.
</p>

<p>Related issue: <iref ref="348"/>.</p>

<note>
Pre Bellevue: Reopened at the request of Alisdair.
</note>

<note>
Bellevue:
</note>

<blockquote><p>
This is a request for a design change, and not a defect in the standard.
It is in scope to consider, but the group feels that it is not a change
that we need to do. Is there a total ordering for floating point values,
including NaN? There is not a clear enough solution or big enough
problem for us to solve. Solving this problem would require solving the
problem for floating point, which is equally unclear. The LWG noted that
users who want to put objects into an associative container for which
<tt>operator&lt;</tt> isn't defined can simply provide their own comparison 
function object. NAD
</p></blockquote>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>Informally: Add a specialization of <tt>std::less</tt> for <tt>std::complex</tt>.</p>
</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>Discussed in Santa Cruz.  An overwhelming majority of the LWG
believes this should not be treated a DR: it's a request for a design
change, not a defect in the existing standard.  Most people (10-3)
believed that we probably don't want this change, period: as with
issue <iref ref="348"/>, it's hard to know where to draw the line.
The LWG noted that users who want to put objects into an associative
container for which <tt>operator&lt;</tt> isn't defined can simply
provide their own comparison function object.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
