<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="280" status="CD1">
<title>Comparison of reverse_iterator to const reverse_iterator</title>
<section><sref ref="[reverse.iterators]"/></section>
<submitter>Steve Cleary</submitter>
<date>27 Nov 2000</date>

<discussion>
<p>
This came from an email from Steve Cleary to Fergus in reference to
issue <iref ref="179"/>. The library working group briefly discussed
this in Toronto and believed it should be a separate issue.  There was
also some reservations about whether this was a worthwhile problem to
fix.
</p>

<p>
Steve said: &quot;Fixing reverse_iterator. std::reverse_iterator can
(and should) be changed to preserve these additional
requirements.&quot; He also said in email that it can be done without
breaking user's code: &quot;If you take a look at my suggested
solution, reverse_iterator doesn't have to take two parameters; there
is no danger of breaking existing code, except someone taking the
address of one of the reverse_iterator global operator functions, and
I have to doubt if anyone has ever done that. . .  <i>But</i>, just in
case they have, you can leave the old global functions in as well --
they won't interfere with the two-template-argument functions.  With
that, I don't see how <i>any</i> user code could break.&quot;
</p>
</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
<b>Section:</b> <sref ref="[reverse.iterator]"/>
add/change the following declarations:</p>
<pre>
  A) Add a templated assignment operator, after the same manner
        as the templated copy constructor, i.e.:

  template &lt; class U &gt;
  reverse_iterator &lt; Iterator &gt;&amp; operator=(const reverse_iterator&lt; U &gt;&amp; u);

  B) Make all global functions (except the operator+) have
  two template parameters instead of one, that is, for
  operator ==, !=, &lt;, &gt;, &lt;=, &gt;=, - replace:

       template &lt; class Iterator &gt;
       typename reverse_iterator&lt; Iterator &gt;::difference_type operator-(
                 const reverse_iterator&lt; Iterator &gt;&amp; x,
                 const reverse_iterator&lt; Iterator &gt;&amp; y);

  with:

      template &lt; class Iterator1, class Iterator2 &gt;
      typename reverse_iterator &lt; Iterator1 &gt;::difference_type operator-(
                 const reverse_iterator &lt; Iterator1 &gt; &amp; x,
                 const reverse_iterator &lt; Iterator2 &gt; &amp; y);
</pre>
<p>
Also make the addition/changes for these signatures in 
<sref ref="[reverse.iter.ops]"/>.
</p>

<note>
Copenhagen: The LWG is concerned that the proposed resolution 
introduces new overloads.  Experience shows that introducing
overloads is always risky, and that it would be inappropriate to
make this change without implementation experience.  It may be
desirable to provide this feature in a different way.
</note>

<note>
Lillehammer: We now have implementation experience, and agree that
this solution is safe and correct.
</note>

</resolution>

</issue>
