<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="1526" status="Deferred">
<title>[FCD] C++ should not impose thread safety requirements on C99 library implementations</title>
<section><sref ref="[res.on.data.races]"/></section>
<submitter>BSI</submitter>
<date>24 Mar 2011</date>

<discussion>
<p><b>Addresses GB-111</b></p>

<p>Section <sref ref="[res.on.data.races]"/>, Data Race Avoidance, requires the C++ Standard Library to avoid data races 
that might otherwise result from two threads making calls to C++ Standard Library functions on 
distinct objects. The C standard library is part of the C++ Standard Library and some C++ Standary library 
functions (parts of the Localization library, as well as Numeric Conversions in 21.5), are specified 
to make use of the C standard library. Therefore, the C++ standard indirectly imposes a requirement 
on the thread safety of the C standard library. However, since the C standard does not address the 
concept of thread safety conforming C implementations exist that do no provide such guarantees. 
This conflict needs to be reconciled.</p>

<p>Suggested resolution by national body comment:</p>

<blockquote><p>
remove the requirement to make use of <tt>strtol()</tt> and <tt>sprintf()</tt> since these functions depend on the 
global C locale and thus cannot be made thread safe.
</p></blockquote>

<note>2011-03-24 Madrid meeting</note>

<p>Deferred</p>

<note>
2011 Bloomington
</note>
<p>
Alisdair: PJ, does this cause a problem in C?
</p>
<p>
PJ: Every implementation know of is thread safe.
</p>
<p>
Pete: There a couple of effects that are specified on strtol() and sprintf() which is a problem.
</p>
<p>
PJ: When C++ talks about C calls it should be "as if" calling the function.
</p>
<p>
Pete: Culprit is to string stuff. My fault.
</p>
<p>
PJ: Not your fault. You did what you were told. Distinct resolution to change wording.
</p>
<p>
Dietmar: What would we break if we change it back?
</p>
<p>
Pete: Nothing. If implemented on top of thread safe C library you are just fine.
</p>
<p>
Alisdair: Anyone want to clean up wording and put it back to what Pete gave us?
</p>
<p>
Alisdair: No volunteers. Do we want to mark as NAD? We could leave it as deferred.
</p>
<p>
Stefanus: Did original submitter care about this?
</p>
<p>
Lawrence: There is some work to make local calls thread safe. The resolution would be to call those thread safe version.
</p>
<p>
Pete: "As if called under single threaded C program"
</p>
<p>
<b>Action Item</b> (Alisdair): Write wording for this issue.
</p>

</discussion>

<rationale><p>No consensus to make a change at this time</p></rationale>

<resolution>
</resolution>

</issue>
