<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="2204" status="New">
<title><tt>basic_string</tt> move-assingment is declared <tt>noexcept</tt> but may throw</title>
<section><sref ref="[basic.string]"/></section>
<submitter>Alisdair Meredith</submitter>
<date>25 Oct 2012</date>

<discussion>

<p>
For C++11, we added a non-throwing exception specification to the move-assignment operator
in the primary template for <tt>basic_string</tt>, but this cannot be honored when assigning
to an object using a stateful allocator that does not compare equal to the source object's
allocator, and when the allocators do not propagate (the default).  Such a 'move' turns into
a 'copy' using the destination object's allocator, and allocating the new string can clearly
throw.  This is still a well-defined 'terminate' call, but probably not what was intended.
</p>

<p>
Likewise - we <i>do</i> want to retain this property for at least the 4 basic string alias types,
and possibly for any container with a stateless always-equal allocator, such as the default
<tt>std::allocator</tt>, or for any allocator that does propagate on move-assignment, as there
should be no allocations or (potentially throwing) copy operations in such cases.  (Hence, the
initially proposed resolution is probably incomplete.)
</p>

<p>
It seems we were more aware of this risk when specifying the move-assignment operator of
the other standard containers in clause 23, none of which have an exception specification
on their move-assignment operator.
</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>
Ammend the member function declaration in the class template definition, <sref ref="[basic.string]"/>:
</p>

<blockquote><pre>
<tt>
namespace std {
  template&lt;class charT, class traits = char_traits&lt;charT>,
    class Allocator = allocator&lt;charT> >
  class basic_string {
  public:
    // ...

    ~basic_string();
    basic_string&amp; operator=(const basic_string&amp; str);
    basic_string&amp; operator=(basic_string&amp;&amp; str) <del>noexcept</del>;
    basic_string&amp; operator=(const charT* s);
    basic_string&amp; operator=(charT c);
    basic_string&amp; operator=(initializer_list&lt;charT>);

    // ...
  };
}
</tt>
</pre></blockquote>

<p>
Ammend the function signature in <sref ref="[string.cons]"/>, p21:
</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
<tt>
basic_string&lt;charT,traits,Allocator>&amp;
  operator=(basic_string&lt;charT,traits,Allocator>&amp;&amp; str)<del> noexcept</del>;
</tt>
</pre>
<p>
-21- <i>Effects</i>: If <tt>*this</tt> and <tt>str</tt> are not the same object, modifies
<tt>*this</tt> as shown in Table 71.<del> [Note: A valid implementation is <tt>swap(str)</tt>.
— end note ]</del>
</p>
<p>
-22- If <tt>*this</tt> and <tt>str</tt> are the same object, the member has no effect.
</p>
<p>
-23- <i>Returns</i>: <tt>*this</tt>
</p>
</blockquote>

</resolution>

</issue>
