<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE issue SYSTEM "lwg-issue.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
] >

<issue num="324" status="CD1">
<title>Do output iterators have value types?</title>
<section><sref ref="[output.iterators]"/></section>
<submitter>Dave Abrahams</submitter>
<date>7 Jun 2001</date>

<discussion>

<p>Table 73 suggests that output iterators have value types.  It 
requires the expression "*a = t".  Additionally, although Table 73
never lists "a = t" or "X(a) = t" in the "expressions" column, it
contains a note saying that "a = t" and "X(a) = t" have equivalent
(but nowhere specified!) semantics.</p>

<p>According to 24.1/9, t is supposed to be "a value of value type
T":</p>

    <blockquote><p>
    In the following sections, a and b denote values of X, n denotes a
    value of the difference type Distance, u, tmp, and m denote
    identifiers, r denotes a value of X&amp;, t denotes a value of
    value type T.
    </p></blockquote>

<p>Two other parts of the standard that are relevant to whether
output iterators have value types:</p>

<ul>
    <li>24.1/1 says "All iterators i support the expression *i,
    resulting in a value of some class, enumeration, or built-in type
    T, called the value type of the iterator".</li>

    <li>
    24.3.1/1, which says "In the case of an output iterator, the types
    iterator_traits&lt;Iterator&gt;::difference_type
    iterator_traits&lt;Iterator&gt;::value_type are both defined as void."
    </li>
</ul>

<p>The first of these passages suggests that "*i" is supposed to
return a useful value, which contradicts the note in 24.1.2/2 saying
that the only valid use of "*i" for output iterators is in an
expression of the form "*i = t".  The second of these passages appears
to contradict Table 73, because it suggests that "*i"'s return value
should be void.  The second passage is also broken in the case of a an
iterator type, like non-const pointers, that satisfies both the output
iterator requirements and the forward iterator requirements.</p>

<p>What should the standard say about <tt>*i</tt>'s return value when
i is an output iterator, and what should it say about that t is in the
expression "*i = t"?  Finally, should the standard say anything about
output iterators' pointer and reference types?</p>

</discussion>

<resolution>
<p>24.1 p1, change</p>

<blockquote>
<p>All iterators <tt>i</tt> support the expression <tt>*i</tt>, resulting
in a value of some class, enumeration, or built-in type <tt>T</tt>,
called the value type of the iterator.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>to</p>

<blockquote>
<p>All input iterators <tt>i</tt> support the expression <tt>*i</tt>,
resulting in a value of some class, enumeration, or built-in type
<tt>T</tt>, called the value type of the iterator. All output
iterators support the expression <tt>*i = o</tt> where <tt>o</tt> is a
value of some type that is in the set of types that are <i>writable</i> to
the particular iterator type of <tt>i</tt>.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>24.1 p9, add</p>

<blockquote>
<p><tt>o</tt> denotes a value of some type that is writable to the
output iterator.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Table 73, change</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
*a = t
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>to</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
*r = o
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>and change</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
*r++ = t
</pre>
</blockquote>

<p>to</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
*r++ = o
</pre>
</blockquote>

<note>post-Redmond: Jeremy provided wording</note>

</resolution>

<rationale>
<p>The LWG considered two options: change all of the language that
seems to imply that output iterators have value types, thus making it
clear that output iterators have no value types, or else define value
types for output iterator consistently.  The LWG chose the former
option, because it seems clear that output iterators were never
intended to have value types.  This was a deliberate design decision,
and any language suggesting otherwise is simply a mistake.</p>

<p>A future revision of the standard may wish to revisit this design
decision.</p>
</rationale>

</issue>
